<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>The historie of Iudith in forme of a poeme. Penned in French, by the noble poet, G. Salust. Lord of Bartas. Englished by Tho. Hudson.</title>
            <title>Histoire de Judit. English</title>
            <author>Du Bartas, Guillaume de Salluste, seigneur, 1544-1590.</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1584</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 203 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 62 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2013-12">2013-12 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A11417</idno>
            <idno type="STC">STC 21671</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC S110849</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">99846317</idno>
            <idno type="PROQUEST">99846317</idno>
            <idno type="VID">11277</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>To the extent possible under law, the Text Creation Partnership has waived all copyright and related or neighboring rights to this keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above, according to the terms of the CC0 1.0 Public Domain Dedication (http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/). This waiver does not extend to any page images or other supplementary files associated with this work, which may be protected by copyright or other license restrictions. Please go to https://www.textcreationpartnership.org/ for more information about the project.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. A11417)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 11277)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Early English books, 1475-1640 ; 551:02)</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>The historie of Iudith in forme of a poeme. Penned in French, by the noble poet, G. Salust. Lord of Bartas. Englished by Tho. Hudson.</title>
                  <title>Histoire de Judit. English</title>
                  <author>Du Bartas, Guillaume de Salluste, seigneur, 1544-1590.</author>
                  <author>Hudson, Thomas, 16th/17th cent.</author>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>[8], 35, 35-92, [11] p.   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>By Thomas Vautroullier,</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>Imprinted at Edinburgh :</pubPlace>
                  <date>1584.</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>In verse.</note>
                  <note>A translation of: Histoire de Judit.</note>
                  <note>At foot of title: Cum priuilegio regali.</note>
                  <note>The pages after 92 numbered: 95, 96, 91, 94-96, [5 unnumbered].</note>
                  <note>Reproduction of the original in the Henry E. Huntington Library and Art Gallery.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,368 texts created during Phase 1 of the project (2000-2009), initially available only to institutions that contributed to their creation, were released into the public domain on 1 January 2015. The approximately 40,000 texts produced during Phase 2 (2009- ), of which 34,963 had been released as of 2020, originally similarly restricted, were similarly freed from all restrictions on 1 August 2020. As of that date anyone is free to take and use these texts for any purpose (modify them, annotate them, distribute them, etc.). But we do respectfully request that due credit and attribution be given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term>Judith --  (Jewish heroine) --  Poetry --  Early works to 1800.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2012-07</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2012-07</date>
            <label>SPi Global</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2012-08</date>
            <label>Geremy Carnes</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2012-08</date>
            <label>Geremy Carnes</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2013-02</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <front>
         <div type="title_page">
            <pb facs="tcp:11277:1"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:11277:1" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <p>THE HISTORIE OF IVDITH IN FORME OF A POEME.</p>
            <p>Penned in French, by the Noble Poet, <hi>G. Saluſt.</hi> Lord of Bartas.</p>
            <p>Engliſhed by Tho. Hudſon.</p>
            <q>
               <l>Ye learned: bind your browes with Laurer band,</l>
               <l>I preaſe not for to touch it with my hand.</l>
            </q>
            <p>Imprinted at Edinburgh, by Thomas Vautroullier. 1584.</p>
            <p>CVM PRIVILEGIO REGALI.</p>
         </div>
         <div type="dedication">
            <pb facs="tcp:11277:2"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:11277:2"/>
            <head>TO THE MOST HIGH AND mightie Prince, <hi>Iames</hi> the Sixt, King of <hi>Scot<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>land</hi> his Maieſties moſt humble Seruant, Tho. Hudſon vvisheth long life vvith euer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>laſting felicitie.</head>
            <p>
               <seg rend="decorInit">A</seg>S your Maieſtie Sir, after your accuſtomed &amp; verte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous maner was ſometyme diſcourſing at Table with ſuch your Domeſtiques, as chaunced to bee attendant.</p>
            <p>It pleaſed your High<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe (not onely to eſteeme the percles ſtile of the Greke HOMER, and the Latin VIRGIL to be inimitable to vs, whoſe toung is barba<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rous and corrupted:) But alſo to alledge partly throw delite your Maieſt. tooke in the Hautie ſtile of thoſe moſt famous Writers, and partly to ſounde the opinion of others, that alſo the loftie Phraſe, the graue inditement, the facou<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>d
<pb facs="tcp:11277:3"/>
               <gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ermes of the French Saluſt (for the like re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſemblaunce) could not be followed, nor ſuffi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ciently expreſſed in our rude and impolliſhed engliſh language. Wherein, I more boldly the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> aduiſedly [with your Maieſt lycence] declared my ſimple opinion. Not calling to mind that I was to giue my verdit in preſens of ſo ſharp &amp; clear-eied a cenſure as your highneſſe is: But raſhly I alledged that it was nothing impoſſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble euen to followe the footſteppes of the ſame great Poet SALVST, and to tranſlate his vearſe (which neuertheleſſe is of it ſelfe exqui<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſite) ſuccintlie, and ſenſibly in our owne vul<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gar ſpecch. Whereupon, it pleaſed your Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ieſtie (amongſte the reſt of his workes) to aſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſigne me, <hi>The Hiſtorie of Iudith,</hi> as an agreable Subiect to your highneſſe, to be turned by me into Engliſh verſe: Not for any ſpeciall gift or Science that was in mee, who am inferiour in knowledge and crudition to the leaſt of your Maieſties Court: But by reaſon (peraduenture) of my bolde aſſertion your Maieſtie, who will not haue the meaneſt of your houſe vnoccu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pied, would haue mee to beare the yoke, and driue forth the pennance, that I had raſhly pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cured. Indeede, the burden appeared heauy, &amp;
<pb facs="tcp:11277:3"/>the charge almoſt inſupportable to me, neuer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>theleſſe the feruent deſire which I had to ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>temper vnto your Maieſt. comma<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>dement, the earneſt entention to verifie my raſh ſpeaking, and the aſſured confidence which I ankred on your highneſſe helpe and correction, encoura<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ged me ſo, and lightned on ſuch wiſe my heauy burden, that I haue with leſſe paine, brought my half diſpaired worke to finall end. In the which I haue ſo behaued my ſelf, that through your Maieſt. concurrence, I haue not exceeded the number of the lynes writte<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> by my author: In euerie one of the which, hee alſo hath two ſillabes mo then my Engliſh beares. And this notwithſtanding, I ſuppoſe your Maieſt. ſhall find litle of my Authors meaning pretermitted. Wherefore if thus much be done by me, who am of an other profeſsion, and of ſo ſimple lit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trature, I leaue it to be co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ſired by your Maieſt. what ſuch as ar co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ſummat in letters &amp; knowes the weightie words, the pithie ſentences, the polliſhed tearmes, and full efficacie of the En<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gliſh toung would haue done. Receiue the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> Sir, of your owne Seruant, this litle worke at your owne commandement enterpriſed, corrected by your Maieſt. owne hande, and dedicated to
<pb facs="tcp:11277:4"/>your owne highneſſe. If I haue done well, let the praiſe redound to your Maieſt. whoſe cen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſure I haue vnderlyen. If otherwiſe, let my de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fault of ſkill, bee imputed to my ſelfe, or at the leaſt my good entention allowed, whereby o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thers may haue occaſion to do better. To your highnes conſideration, referring Sir, both my deligence done in this ſmall tranſlation, &amp; the inueterate affection which I haue, and ought alwayes to beare vnto your Maieſt. I commit with all humilitie, your highnes, your Realme and eſtate, to the gouernement of God, who gouerneth all the Worlde.</p>
         </div>
         <div type="sonnet">
            <pb facs="tcp:11277:4"/>
            <head>SONNET.</head>
            <l>SInce ye immortall ſiſters nine hes left</l>
            <l>All other countries lying farre or nere:</l>
            <l>To follovv him vvho from them all you reft,</l>
            <l>And novv hes cauſde your reſidence be here</l>
            <l>VVho though a ſtraunger yet he lovde ſo dere</l>
            <l>This Realme and me, ſo as he ſpoilde his avvne,</l>
            <l>And all the brookes &amp; banks, &amp; fountains clere</l>
            <l>That be therein of you as he hath shavvne</l>
            <l>in this his vvork: the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> let your breath be blavvne,</l>
            <l>In recompence of this his vvilling minde</l>
            <l>On me: that ſine may vvith my pen bee dravvne</l>
            <l>His praiſe: for though himſelfe be not inclynde</l>
            <l>Nor preaſeth but to touch the Laurer tre:</l>
            <l>Yet vvell he merits crovvnd thervvith to be.</l>
            <trailer>FINIS.</trailer>
         </div>
         <div type="sonnet">
            <pb facs="tcp:11277:5"/>
            <head>SONNET,</head>
            <l>The <hi>Muſes</hi> nyne haue not reueald to me</l>
            <l>What ſacred ſeedes are in their gardens ſowne</l>
            <l>Nor how their <hi>Salust</hi> gaines the <hi>Laurer</hi> tre</l>
            <l>Which throw thy toyle in <hi>Brittain</hi> grou<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>d is grown</l>
            <l>But ſith they ſe thy trauell treuly ſhowne</l>
            <l>In verteus ſkoole th'expyring tyme to ſpend</l>
            <l>So haue they to his hienes made it knowne</l>
            <l>Whoſe Princely power may dewly the defend</l>
            <l>Then yow that on the <hi>Holy mount</hi> depend</l>
            <l>In chriſtall ayr and drinks the cleared ſpring</l>
            <l>Of <hi>Poetrie</hi> I do yow recommend</l>
            <l>To the protection of this godly King</l>
            <l>VVho for his verteus and his gifts deuyne</l>
            <l>Is only <hi>Monark</hi> of the <hi>Muſes</hi> nyne.</l>
            <trailer>FINIS.</trailer>
            <closer>
               <signed>M. V. F.</signed>
            </closer>
         </div>
         <div type="author_to_the_reader">
            <pb facs="tcp:11277:5"/>
            <head>THE AVTHORS ADMONI<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>TION TO THE READER.</head>
            <p>BEloued <hi>Reader,</hi> it is about fourtene years past ſince <hi>I</hi> was commanded by the late Illuſtrate and moſt vertuous Princeſſe <hi>Iean, Queene of Na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uarre,</hi> to reduce the <hi>Hiſtorie of Iudith,</hi> in forme of a <hi>Poeme Epique,</hi> wherein <hi>I</hi> haue not ſo much aimed to follow the phraſe or text of the byble, as <hi>I</hi> haue preaſed (without wandring from the veritie of the Hiſtorie) to imitate <hi>Homer</hi> in his <hi>Iliades,</hi> and <hi>Virgill</hi> in his <hi>Aene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>idos,</hi> and others who hath left to vs workes of ſuch like matter: thereby to render my worke ſo much the more delectable. And if the effect hath not anſweared to my deſire, <hi>I</hi> beſeech thee to laye the fault vppon her who propoſed to me ſo meane a <hi>Thean e</hi> or ſubiect, and not on mee who could not honeſtly diſobeye. Yet in ſo much as <hi>I</hi> am the first in <hi>Fraunce,</hi> who in a iuſt <hi>Poeme</hi> hath treated in our toung of ſacred things, I hope of thy fauour to receiue ſome excuſe, ſeing that things of ſo great weight cannot be both perfectly begunne and en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded together. If thou neither alow my ſtile nor work<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>manſhip, at least thou ſhalt be driuou to alow the honeſt pretence and holy deſire which <hi>I</hi> haue to ſee the youth of <hi>Fraunce</hi> ſo holyly by mine example exercyſed.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>I</hi> may not forget that they doe greatly wrong mee, Who thinkes that in diſcriuing the <hi>Cataſtrophe</hi> of this Hiſtorie (truelie tragicall) thinkes that <hi>I</hi> am be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>comme a voluntairy Aduocate to theſe trouble ſome &amp; ſedicious ſprites (who for to ſerue their temerarious paſſions, and priuate inſpirations) conſpires against the
<pb facs="tcp:11277:6"/>liues of placed princes. For ſo much doe I diſaſſent that this example and the like ought to be drawen in conſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>que<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ce, that I am verily perſwaded that the act of <hi>Ahud,</hi> of <hi>Iaell,</hi> and of <hi>Iudith,</hi> who vnder coulour of obeiſance and pretext of amitie layde their reuenging handes vppon <hi>Aeglon, Siſara,</hi> &amp; <hi>Holophernes:</hi> had beene worthie of a hundreth gallowes, a hundreth fires, and a hundreth wheeles, if they had not beene peculiar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly choſen of God for to vnloſe the chaines, and breake the bands which retainde the <hi>Hebrewe</hi> people in more then <hi>Aegiptian</hi> ſeruitude, and expreſly called to kill thoſe tyrants with a death as ſhamefull as their liues were wicked and abhominable. But ſeing this queſtion is ſo diffuſe that it cannot bee abſolued in few words, &amp; that my braine is to weake for ſo high an enterpriſe, <hi>I</hi> ſend you to thoſe who haue ſpent more oyle and tyme in turning the leaues of the ſacred ſcriptures, then <hi>I</hi> haue done for the preſent. It mee ſufficeth for the tyme to admoniſh the <hi>Reader,</hi> to attempt nothing without a cleare and indubitable vocation of God againſt thoſe whom he hath erected aboue vs and aboue althing, not to abuſe the lawe of humaine hoſpitalitie, and other ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly bands for to giue place to theſe frenetike oppinions ſo to aboliſh a prete<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ted tyrannie. <hi>I</hi> haue alſo to warne thee of two different ſortes of men of the which one ſort is ſo depraued that they can heare nothing, but that which is altogether prophane, and the other is ſo ſuperſticious that they make conſcience not only to write, but alſo to reade of holy things in vearſe, as though that the mea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſure and iointure of ſillabes were ſo conſtrained as it
<pb facs="tcp:11277:6"/>were vnpoſſible to keepe the ſence vnperuerted, or at least exceſſiuely obſcured. Now if <hi>I</hi> perceine that this my firſt aſſay may be to thee agreable, <hi>I</hi> ſhall continue more gladly my new commenced race in ſuch ſort that thou ſhalt not repent thine indulgence, nor <hi>I</hi> my paſſed paines. But if co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>trarie fall, in time to come <hi>I</hi> wilbe ware to lay out my ſmall pack in this ample <hi>Theatre</hi> of <hi>Fraunce,</hi> where there is almoſt as many Iudgements as beholders. A Dieu.</p>
            <closer>
               <signed>GSSDB.</signed>
            </closer>
         </div>
         <div type="argument">
            <pb facs="tcp:11277:7"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:11277:7"/>
            <head>THE ARGVMENT OF THE WHOLE HISTORIE OF IVDITH.</head>
            <p>AFter that the Children of IZREL were deliuered from captiuitie &amp; returned to their la<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>d, the cittie of IERVSALEM ree<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dified, the Temple builded, and prepared to the ſcruice of the Lorde, the multitude of the peo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple being ſcattred in ſundry townes &amp; places of the land, where they liued in peaceable reſt: the Lorde knowing man to bee negligent of God &amp; his ſaluation, chiefly when hee liues at eaſe, and all things frames vnto his frail deſire, to th'end that his people ſhould no<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t fall in ſuch an inconuenient, would exerciſe them with a fearefull affliction and temptation, ſending vp<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pon their countrey an armie ſo great in nom<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ber and puiſlance, that made the whole earth to tremble. This expeditio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> was vnder the <hi>Per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſian Monark,</hi> named in the hiſtory <hi>Nabuchad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nezar</hi> (which neuertheleſſe is not his right name.) His chief Lieutenant generall &amp; Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ductor of the whole Armie, was <hi>Holophernes,</hi> who (wherſoeuer he came) ouerthrewe all re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ligio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>, permitting none to inuocate or acknow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledge any other God, but NABVCHADNE<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ZAR,
<pb facs="tcp:11277:8"/>his Maiſter, whome hee enforced to conſtitute and eſtabliſh for the onely God. So entred hee <hi>Iudea</hi> with entent to diſtroye it all, which the people perceiuing his power to be ſo great that no nation could reſiſt him, and alſo knowing his cruell hatred, were ſore affraide, and almoſt driuen to extreame deſpe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ration ſeing none other thing preſent before them, but ruine and diſtruction. And this the Lord ſuffred, to ſhow (in time) his work to be more wonderfull. For the people being hum<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bled, and hauing called to the lorde for mercy &amp; ſuccour at his hand, hee both hard and ſuc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>coured them at neede. The meane was not through ſtrength or ſtoutnes of ſome worthie Captain, but by the hand of IVDITH, a te<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>der feeble woma<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>, to the ſhame of this moſt proud &amp; cruell tyrant, and all his heathen hoſte. For ſhe cut off his head, put all his camp to flight, diſtroyd his men of Armes, in ſuch wiſe that they fled here and there, &amp; ſeeking to ſaue their liues. left all their tents and baggage. Thus the Lord by the weake, and thoſe that are not re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>garded, makes his works admirable. By one ſelfe meane he ſaued his owne, &amp; executed his iuſtice againſt his enemies. In which we haue
<pb facs="tcp:11277:8"/>to conſider his ſinguler prouidence and good<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nes, and the care which he hath in eſpeciall for his faithfull, and all his whole church. This Hiſtory is entituled by the name of IVDITH, becauſe it conteines the narration of her great vertues, and for that the Lord vſed her as an in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtrument for the deliuerance of his people. It is not certaine who was the firſt Author hereof, neuertheleſſe the reading of it hath bene receiued in the Church for the doctrine &amp; vtilitie of the ſame.</p>
         </div>
      </front>
      <body>
         <div n="1" type="book">
            <argument>
               <pb facs="tcp:11277:9"/>
               <head>THE SOMMARIE OF THE I. BOOK.</head>
               <p>¶ <hi>Holophernes</hi> lieutenant generall and cheif of the army of <hi>Nebuchadn<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>
                     <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>zer</hi> King of the <hi>A<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>ſirians,</hi> was in the feild for to ſubd<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>we duers people &amp; amongſt others the <hi>Iewes.</hi> All the <hi>Nation</hi> is ſeazed with great feare, for the cruelties committed by the enemye. Then as it falles out in bruits of warre, all the whole people were troubled, ſome ſauing themſelves in cor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ners for feare, others attending in great perplexitie, ſom ſad and <hi>Tragi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>c<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>ll</hi> end the beſt ſort calles vpon God. This whyle <hi>Ioachim</hi> the chefe Prieſt goue<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ned the people: he by his letters &amp; expres command<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ment recalles thoſe that wer fled and ſcattred, and made them returne to <hi>Ieruſalem</hi> wher, in preſence of the <hi>Leu<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>ts,</hi> he made ſacr<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>fice &amp; er<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>eſt pray<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>r vnto God to with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>drawe hi<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> y<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>e and to be mercyfull to his people, which done he enters in coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſell and requyres his Princes to conſulte vpon the cauſe, and conſider what is moſt expedient, and to prefer the loue of Gods L<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>we and the coun<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>rie, before all priuate things: the firſt that gainſtands this exhortation an hyp<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>crite &amp; fauourer of the enemye, who giues counſell to render them to <hi>Holophernes</hi> calling him a Prince gratious to thoſe that appl<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>udes to him, &amp; inuincible in battell to thoſe that dar reſiſt him. But the ſecound Lord replying zealouſly againe, detecteth his fals hypocriſie and c<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>rles ſecuritie, exp<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ſing the people to the mercy of a barbarous go<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>es enemy before the duity they ought to their God and their countrye: and to eſtablish in place of the true God, a wicked <hi>Nemrod</hi> conſummat in all impietie &amp; wickednes, to abolish all vertue &amp; godlynes, for he proves that if the nation should be roted out for the right re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ligion, God should be more honnored in the death of the <hi>Iewes</hi> then in their lyues: and that it is more worthy to dye <hi>Hebrewes</hi> then to lyue infidells. And freemen then sklaves. Short<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>y that they ought to preferre honour and d<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>tie before feare, and a vaine hope to prolong their dolefull daies. This re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ply encouraged all the a<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ſ<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ſtants wherof Ioachim, giue thanks to God, and reſoluing him ſelfe vpon a iuſt defence for the conſeruation of the ſeruice of God, and the fredome of his nation, and the lyues of the innocent againſt this v<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>lanous inuaſion: nyſely departed the regiments of townes to perſones con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>venient, who paſt to their a<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ſ<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>gned places, <gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>hone preparing according to them power vnto the war with courage, paine, and dilignce.</p>
            </argument>
            <pb facs="tcp:11277:9"/>
            <head>THE FIRST BOOKE OF IVDITH.</head>
            <div type="introduction">
               <lg>
                  <l>I Sing the vertues of a valiant Dame,<note place="margin">Propoſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion and ſomme of this work.</note>
                  </l>
                  <l>Who in defence of <hi>Iacob</hi> ouercame:</l>
                  <l>Th' <hi>Aſſyrian</hi> Prince, and ſlew that <hi>Pagan</hi> ſtout,</l>
                  <l>Who had beſet <hi>Bethulia</hi> walles about.</l>
               </lg>
               <lg>
                  <l>O thou, who kept thine <hi>Izak</hi> from the thrall<note place="margin">Inuocario<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> of the true God.</note>
                  </l>
                  <l>Of Infideles, and ſtelde the courage ſmall,</l>
                  <l>Of feeble <hi>Iudith,</hi> with a manly ſtrength:</l>
                  <l>VVith ſacred furie fill my hart at length.</l>
                  <l>And with thy <hi>Holy</hi> ſprite, my ſprite enſpire,</l>
                  <l>For matter ſo deuine, Lord I require</l>
                  <l>No humaine ſtile, but that the Reader may,</l>
                  <l>Great profit reape, I ioye, thou praiſe alway.</l>
               </lg>
               <lg>
                  <l>
                     <hi>And ſince in vulgar verſe</hi> I <hi>preaſe to ſing,</hi>
                     <note place="margin">Dedicatio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> of the Au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thour al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tred by the tran<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſlatour.</note>
                  </l>
                  <l>
                     <hi>This godly Pooeme to a Chriſtian King,</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>
                     <hi>To him who God in goodneſſe hath crect</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>
                     <hi>For princely Piller, to his owne elect:</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>
                     <hi>For lawfull Lord, to raigne with trueth and right:</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>
                     <hi>For loue ſome Laurer, to the verteous wight:</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>
                     <hi>Him</hi> (I <hi>beſeech</hi>) <hi>this trauel to defend,</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>
                     <hi>That to his pleaſure</hi> I <hi>the ſame may end.</hi>
                  </l>
               </lg>
            </div>
            <div type="poem">
               <pb facs="tcp:11277:10"/>
               <lg>
                  <l>WHen <hi>Izrell</hi> was in quiet reſt and peace,</l>
                  <l>And fruitfully the ground gaue her encreaſe,</l>
                  <l>VVhich ſeauentie yeare vntilled lay beforne</l>
                  <l>And nothing bare but thiſtle, weede, and thorne.</l>
                  <l>It pleaſed <hi>God</hi> (vpon his iuſt correction)</l>
                  <l>T'awake his owne, that were of his election,</l>
                  <l>Leaſt that the lo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>gſom peace ſhould the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> withhold:</l>
                  <l>And dull their ſpirites, as doth the warriour bolde,</l>
                  <l>Who ſpoils his horſe with pampring in the ſtable,</l>
                  <l>That makes him for the manaige more vnable.</l>
                  <l>He ſpred their land with bands of enmies ſtout,</l>
                  <l>VVhoſe cloudes of ſhot, bedimd their land about.</l>
                  <l>Their <hi>Hoſte,</hi> with arrows, pikes, and ſta<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>dards, ſtood<note place="margin">The Ar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mie of <hi>He<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lepherne.</hi>
                     </note>
                  </l>
                  <l>As briſtel pointed, as a thornie wood.</l>
                  <l>Their multitude of men, the riuers dride,</l>
                  <l>VVhich throw the wealthy <hi>Iuda</hi> ſweete did ſlide:</l>
                  <l>So that ſlood <hi>Iordane</hi> finding drye his banke,</l>
                  <l>for ſhame he bluſht, and down his head he ſhra<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ke,</l>
                  <l>For woe that he his credit could not keepe,</l>
                  <l>To ſend one waue, for tribute to the deepe.</l>
               </lg>
               <lg>
                  <l>Scarſe had the Harueſt ma<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> with hooke in hand,</l>
                  <l>Diſpoilde the fruite and let the ſtuble ſtand:</l>
                  <l>Scarſe had the hungrie Gleaner put in bind,</l>
                  <l>The ſcattred graine, the Sherer left behind:</l>
                  <l>And ſcarſe the ſlapping flaile began to threſh</l>
                  <l>VVhen vnto <hi>Iacob,</hi> newes was brought a freſh.</l>
                  <l>That <hi>Holophern,</hi> his frontiers did inuade,</l>
                  <l>And paſt all Riuers, ſtraites, and murders made</l>
                  <l>So vile, that none he left that drew the breath:</l>
                  <l>But olde and young, he put to ſodaine death:</l>
                  <pb facs="tcp:11277:10"/>
                  <l>The ſucking babes vpon their mothers knee:</l>
                  <l>His cruell cutthroates made them all to dee.</l>
                  <l>Then like a ſlocke of ſheepe that doth beholde,</l>
                  <l>A wolfe come from the wood vpon their fold,</l>
                  <l>Shapes no defence, but runnes athwart the landes,</l>
                  <l>And ſhortly makes of one, a hundreth bands,</l>
                  <l>So <hi>Iſacks</hi> ſonnes, indreading for to feele<note place="margin">
                        <hi>The</hi> Ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>breus.</note>
                  </l>
                  <l>This tyrant, who purſued them at the heele,</l>
                  <l>Diſſundring fled, and ſought their liues to ſaue:</l>
                  <l>In hils, and dales, and euerie deſert caue.</l>
               </lg>
               <lg>
                  <l>The ſheepherd of his flocke had now no care:<note place="margin">Feare of the eni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mie.</note>
                  </l>
                  <l>But fearing death ſled to ſome mountaine bare.</l>
                  <l>The Craftsman now his lumes away hath laide:</l>
                  <l>The Marchant left his traffike and his trade,</l>
                  <l>To hide himſelfe more ſafely in a vault:</l>
                  <l>Then in a Rampier, to ſuſtaine th'aſſault.</l>
                  <l>The Lords eſteemde them ſelfes in furer holde:</l>
                  <l>In Dennes of beaſts, then caſtles gilt with golde.</l>
                  <l>Feare lent the wings for aged folke to flie,</l>
                  <l>And made them mount to places that were hie.</l>
                  <l>Feare made the wofull wemen for to beare,</l>
                  <l>Their cradles ſweere to hilles that higheſt weare:</l>
                  <l>Feare made the wofull child to waile and weep,</l>
                  <l>For want of ſpeede, on foote and hand to creep:</l>
                  <l>Alwhere was nothing hard but hideous cryes,</l>
                  <l>And pittious plaints that did the harts agryes.</l>
               </lg>
               <lg>
                  <l>O Lord (ſaid they) wilt thou ſtill day by day,<note place="margin">Affiction cauſeth prayes</note>
                  </l>
                  <l>The arrowes of thine anger neuer ſtay?</l>
                  <l>Wilt thou that <hi>Calde</hi> conquer vs againe?</l>
                  <l>Shall <hi>Iuda</hi> yet the <hi>Heathen</hi> yoke ſuſtaine?</l>
                  <pb n="4" facs="tcp:11277:11"/>
                  <l>wilt thou againe that they make euerie towne,</l>
                  <l>But ſtonie he apes of houſes caſten downe?</l>
                  <l>Againe ſhall ſacrilegious fire deuore,</l>
                  <l>thy holy houſe where we do thee adore?</l>
               </lg>
               <lg>
                  <l>Then <hi>Ioachim</hi> the prieſt of God moſt hie,</l>
                  <l>who ouer <hi>Iuda</hi> then had chiefe degrie:</l>
                  <l>Stood like a Pylot ſtout in tempeſt great,</l>
                  <l>who ſeeing wind and weather for to threat,</l>
                  <l>Yet to his mates, his feare, no terrour drawes,</l>
                  <l>Nor leaues his ſhip vnto the wrackfull wawes.</l>
                  <l>But with diſguiſing feare, his face vp caſts,</l>
                  <l>And ſtoutly doth gainſtand the balefull blaſts:</l>
                  <l>Right ſo this prudent prelate ſent in haſte,</l>
                  <l>two hundreth men to paſſe where men were plaſte</l>
                  <l>In places ſtrong, and thence commanded them,</l>
                  <l>For to repaire vnto <hi>Ieruſalem.</hi>
                  </l>
               </lg>
               <lg>
                  <l>Now ſince th'Eternall did reueale his will,</l>
                  <l>Vpon the ſacred top of <hi>Syna</hi> Hill,</l>
                  <l>the Arke of <hi>God</hi> which wiſedome more did holde,</l>
                  <l>In Tables two, then all the <hi>Grekes</hi> haue tolde.</l>
                  <l>And more then euer <hi>Rome</hi> could comprehend,</l>
                  <l>In huge of learned bookes that they pend:</l>
                  <l>Long wandred it throw tribs, throw kin and kin,<note place="margin">
                        <hi>Sam.</hi> 1.4. <hi>Sam.</hi> 2.6.</note>
                  </l>
                  <l>and found no certaine place of reſting in.</l>
                  <l>Yea ſometime it the ſhamefull ſpoile hath beene</l>
                  <l>to ſacrilegious hands of <hi>Paleſtene,</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>vntill that time, that <hi>Ieſſies</hi> holie race,</l>
                  <l>for euer lodged it in <hi>Iebus</hi> place.<note place="margin">Ieruſalem</note>
                  </l>
               </lg>
               <lg>
                  <l>But for that <hi>Dauids</hi> ha<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ds with blood were filde</l>
                  <l>throu infinits of humaines he had kilde.</l>
                  <pb n="5" facs="tcp:11277:11"/>
                  <l>the king of peace would haue a king of reſt,</l>
                  <l>to build his <hi>Temple</hi> farre aboue the beſt:<note place="margin">
                        <hi>Sam</hi> 2.7.</note>
                  </l>
                  <l>His houſe, whoſe front vpreard ſo high and eavne,</l>
                  <l>that lightlied earth, &amp; ſeemd to threat the heavne</l>
                  <l>vntill that wicked time a tyrant vile,</l>
                  <l>Of name and deede that bare the ſemble ſtile,<note place="margin">Nabu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chadne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>zer. <hi>Chr.</hi> 2.036</note>
                  </l>
                  <l>that did this king, that building braue he wract,</l>
                  <l>And to the ſacred ground al whole it ſackt.</l>
               </lg>
               <lg>
                  <l>Yet when, long after, <hi>Abrahms</hi> holie race,</l>
                  <l>Of <hi>Tiger</hi> bankes had left the captiue place,<note place="margin">Eſa. <hi>6.</hi>
                     </note>
                  </l>
                  <l>with combers great they redefied with paine,</l>
                  <l>that moſt renowmed houſe of <hi>God</hi> againe.</l>
                  <l>Which though vnto the firſt it ſeemde as ſmall,</l>
                  <l>As to a Princes houſe, a ſheepherds hall,</l>
                  <l>And though the hugenes were not as it was:</l>
                  <l>yet ſure the height and beutie did ſurpas,</l>
                  <l>And ouerſeilde the famous worke of <hi>Pharie:</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>
                     <hi>Epheſus</hi> temple, and the tombe of <hi>Carie.</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>The <hi>Rhodian Collos,</hi> and the <hi>Caldean</hi> wall,</l>
                  <l>that <hi>Semirame</hi> ſet vp with tourrets tall.</l>
                  <l>Alſo the wondrous worke of this ſame temple,</l>
                  <l>Might ſerue a <hi>Creſiphon</hi> for his exemple:</l>
                  <l>
                     <hi>Lyſippus</hi> eke to carue by ſquare and line,</l>
                  <l>Or guide <hi>Appelles</hi> penſile moſt deuine.</l>
                  <l>Heare in this place, all <hi>Izrel</hi> moſt deuoute,</l>
                  <l>withdrew them ſelues to <hi>Salem</hi> round aboute,<note place="margin">Ieruſalem</note>
                  </l>
                  <l>As when the heavne his ſluces opens wide,</l>
                  <l>And makes the floods vpon the ground to glide,</l>
                  <l>the brookes that breakes adoune from diuers hils</l>
                  <l>with courſe impetious till one deepe diſtils.</l>
               </lg>
               <pb n="6" facs="tcp:11277:12"/>
               <lg>
                  <l>Amongſt the Dames, that there deuouteſt were</l>
                  <l>The Holy <hi>Iudith,</hi> faireſt did appere:</l>
                  <l>Like <hi>Phoebus</hi> that aboue the ſtarres doth ſhine:</l>
                  <l>It ſeemd that ſhee was made on moulde deuine.</l>
               </lg>
               <lg>
                  <l>This Primate then aſſiſted with his kinne</l>
                  <l>Of great <hi>Eleazar</hi> (prieſts whoſe head and chinne,</l>
                  <l>Was neuer ſhaue) deuoutly on he preaſt:</l>
                  <l>A pearled Myter on his balmed creaſt.</l>
                  <l>And with a holy Alb, with garnettes ſpred,</l>
                  <l>And golden Belles, his ſacred bodie cled.</l>
                  <l>And ſlew, and burnt, the bulks (as was the guiſe)</l>
                  <l>Of many a kid, and <gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>alfe for ſacrifiſe.</l>
                  <l>And with their blood, the Alters hornes he dyed,</l>
                  <l>And praying thus, to <hi>God</hi> immortall cryed.</l>
               </lg>
               <lg>
                  <l>"O Lord of Hoſtes, we come not vnto thee,<note place="margin">Prayer.</note>
                  </l>
                  <l>"To wey our merits with thy maieſtie:</l>
                  <l>"Nor to proteſt before thy heauenly might,</l>
                  <l>"That ſackleſſy, thy ſcourge doth on vs light:</l>
                  <l>"But rather we confeſſe (as true it is)</l>
                  <l>"Our ſinnes, haue iuſtly merite more then this.</l>
                  <l>"But Lord if thou thy couenant would forget,</l>
                  <l>"VVhich thou with <hi>Abrahm</hi> made, &amp; ſo wilt ſet</l>
                  <l>"For mercie great, thy iuſtice moſt ſeueare,</l>
                  <l>"Thou ſhould a greater plague vpon vs reare.</l>
                  <l>"Change then our proces from thy iuſtice ſeate,</l>
                  <l>"And ſaue vs at thy throne of mercie great.</l>
                  <l>"Forgiue vs Lord and holde farre from vs all,</l>
                  <l>"Theſe plagues, that on our heads are like to fall.</l>
               </lg>
               <lg>
                  <l>Alas what helpeth vs thy heauie ſtroke,</l>
                  <l>To binde our necks to ſuch a ſeruile yoke,</l>
                  <pb n="7" facs="tcp:11277:12"/>
                  <l>VVherewith th'<hi>Aſſyrian</hi> tyra<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ts long haue grieued</l>
                  <l>Thine <hi>Izak,</hi> till their bondage thou relieued.</l>
                  <l>If ſo this natiue ground that new is tilde,</l>
                  <l>If ſo theſe Hoſtries new with folke refilde:</l>
                  <l>If ſo (alas) our chaſt and modeſt Dames,</l>
                  <l>Our infants young, our Virgins good of fames,</l>
                  <l>Should be a praye to <hi>Ammon,</hi> and to <hi>Perſe,</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>To <hi>Calde,</hi> and the mutine <hi>Parthian</hi> fierſe,</l>
                  <l>If that we ſee this Alter made prophane,</l>
                  <l>And witches it abuſe with Idols vaine:</l>
                  <l>Yet, Lord if thou no pittie on vs take,</l>
                  <l>At leaſt great <hi>God,</hi> do for thy glories ſake.</l>
                  <l>Haue pittie on this holy building nowe,</l>
                  <l>Where not a God hath ſacrifice but thou:</l>
                  <l>VVhere not a God but thou haſt reſidence,</l>
                  <l>To feile the ſauour ſweete of frankenſence.</l>
               </lg>
               <lg>
                  <l>Hold back (O Lord) the <hi>Caldean</hi> creſſets bright</l>
                  <l>From theſe rich <hi>Cedar</hi> vaults of ſtately hight.</l>
                  <l>Preſerue theſe veſſels, ornaments of gold,</l>
                  <l>From ſacrilegious hands of neighbours bolde.</l>
                  <l>And let the blood of beaſts before thy face,</l>
                  <l>Thy Iuſtice ſtay, and grant thy ſeruants grace.</l>
               </lg>
               <lg>
                  <l>This prayer done, the people went their way,</l>
                  <l>Then <hi>Ioachim</hi> conuende that preſent day:</l>
                  <l>the Princes all of <hi>Iuda,</hi> and them praide,</l>
                  <l>gainſt this miſchiefe for counſell, and thus ſaid.</l>
               </lg>
               <lg>
                  <l>Companions, if your former zeale remaine,<note place="margin">Exhorta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion.</note>
                  </l>
                  <l>If ardent loue to god ye ſtill retaine:</l>
                  <l>If wife, or childe, may cauſe your care or loue,</l>
                  <l>VVhich ſhould the Centers of your ſenſes moue:</l>
                  <pb n="8" facs="tcp:11277:13"/>
                  <l>If in your breſts a noble hart doth bide,</l>
                  <l>Let deede beare witnes at this wofull tide.</l>
                  <l>For ſauing <hi>God</hi> and your foreſight, in deede</l>
                  <l>t'is done, t'is done with vs, and all our ſeede.</l>
                  <l>And after this, th'<hi>Immortall</hi> ſhall not ſee</l>
                  <l>this after fume before his maieſtee.</l>
               </lg>
               <lg>
                  <l>VVhe<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> th'<hi>Air</hi> is calme, &amp; ſtill as dead &amp; deafe,<note place="margin">Compari<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon.</note>
                  </l>
                  <l>And vnder heavne quakes not an aſpin leafe,</l>
                  <l>VVhen Seas are calme, and thouſand veſſels fleete</l>
                  <l>Vpo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> the ſleeping ſeas with paſſage ſweete.</l>
                  <l>And when the variant wind is ſtill and lowne,</l>
                  <l>the cunning Pylot neuer can be knowne.</l>
               </lg>
               <lg>
                  <l>But whe<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> the cruell ſtorme doth threat the bark,</l>
                  <l>to drowne in deepes of pits infernall dark,</l>
                  <l>while toſſing teares both ruther maſt &amp; ſaile,</l>
                  <l>While mounting ſeemes the Azur ſkye to ſkaile:</l>
                  <l>while driues perforce vpon ſome deadly ſhore,</l>
                  <l>there is the Pylot knowne and not before.</l>
               </lg>
               <lg>
                  <l>Alas I pray you then what care and ſtrifes,</l>
                  <l>Haue we to keepe our honours, goods, and lifes:</l>
                  <l>Forget not then the care of this ſame place,</l>
                  <l>your countreyes weale, gods glorie and his grace:</l>
                  <l>But humblie giue your ſelues into the hand</l>
                  <l>Of god moſt high, and with a holy brand,</l>
                  <l>,repurge your ſprits from euerie hatefull ſinne,</l>
                  <l>,which cauſeth <hi>God</hi> his Iuſtice to begin:</l>
                  <l>And ſee what may to <hi>God</hi> be agreable,</l>
                  <l>For <hi>Iacobs</hi> weale, and for you profitable.</l>
               </lg>
               <lg>
                  <l>This ſaid: an ancient traitour from his youth,</l>
                  <l>who foſtred gall in hart, with hony in mouth,</l>
                  <pb n="9" facs="tcp:11277:13"/>
                  <l>Enforcing from his eyes ſome fained teare,</l>
                  <l>(to cloke his malice) ſpacke as ye ſhall heare,</l>
               </lg>
               <lg>
                  <l>My toung me failes, my hair for dread vpſtarts,<note place="margin">The Ora<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion of a ſubtill worldling</note>
                  </l>
                  <l>My heauie ſpirite, from penſiue corps departs.</l>
                  <l>VVhen I bethinke me of yone tyrant ſtout,</l>
                  <l>who hath bedround the world with bloud about:</l>
                  <l>Approching threats our townes with firie flames,</l>
                  <l>Our ſelfs with death, diſhonour to our Dames.</l>
                  <l>Yet when I call to minde the curtſie great,</l>
                  <l>That this great Lord doth vſe, who doth entreate</l>
                  <l>Not onely thoſe that beaſtiall are become,</l>
                  <l>And haue their hope in brutall Idols dome,</l>
                  <l>But euen to zealous folke who do embrace,</l>
                  <l>The faith, and law, like vs of <hi>Abrahms</hi> race:</l>
                  <l>who being well aduiſde, did humblie ſue</l>
                  <l>His pardon, and eſcapte his vengeance due,</l>
                  <l>then thanke I <hi>God</hi> who ſends vs ſuch a foe,</l>
                  <l>As plagues the proude, and lets the humble goe:</l>
                  <l>For we aſſoone, ſhall vanquiſh him with teares,</l>
                  <l>As will be long, to wrak him with our weares.</l>
                  <l>Then whileſt we may haue choice of either ſtate</l>
                  <l>of peace or warres, his fauour, or his hate.</l>
                  <l>Let vs not follow (ſeeing ſkath at hand)</l>
                  <l>the follie of our fathers, to gainſtand.</l>
                  <l>But rather let vs beare a lower ſaile,</l>
                  <l>And ſerue his king as beſt for our awaile.</l>
                  <l>But thinke not yet, that I this councell giue</l>
                  <l>for craft, or warrant for my ſelfe to liue:</l>
                  <l>For I haue els my dayes ſo nearly ſpent,</l>
                  <l>that for to dye I could be well content.</l>
                  <pb n="10" facs="tcp:11277:14"/>
                  <l>The <hi>Aſſyrian</hi> neede not in my breſt to</l>
                  <l>ſtrike,</l>
                  <l>His fethred Dart, nor yet his trembling pike:</l>
                  <l>Yea if my youth to me ſhould eft returne,</l>
                  <l>And make my youthly bloode within me burne,</l>
                  <l>So honour I my <hi>God,</hi> and contrey deare,</l>
                  <l>that for to dye for them, I would not feare:</l>
                  <l>As <hi>Sampſon</hi> did, if ſo my death might yeld:</l>
                  <l>The victorie of the <hi>Vizroy,</hi> and the field.</l>
                  <l>But moſt (I feare) leaſt we with curious zeale,</l>
                  <l>Fight for the lawe, yet fight againſt her weale,</l>
                  <l>Againſt our ſelfs, to bring ſo great a wracke:</l>
                  <l>that proude, and cruell tyrants ſhall vs ſacke,</l>
                  <l>And grow in pride (ſuppreſſing <hi>Iudaes</hi> ſtrength)</l>
                  <l>For to contemne the glorie of <hi>God</hi> at length.</l>
                  <l>For <hi>Iſraell</hi> being loſt, who ſhall enſue,</l>
                  <l>to render here to <hi>God</hi> deuotions due?</l>
                  <l>what people ſparſed on this earthly ball</l>
                  <l>From <hi>Indian</hi> ſhoare to where the Sunne doth fall.</l>
                  <l>Or from the Climate of the northren blaſt,</l>
                  <l>Vnto that place where ſommer aye doth laſt:</l>
                  <l>Hath <hi>God</hi> elect, ſaue <hi>Iſraell</hi> for his owne</l>
                  <l>Vpon this Hill to haue his glorie ſhowne?</l>
               </lg>
               <lg>
                  <l>At this: the valiant <hi>Cambris</hi> of renowne,</l>
                  <l>with righteous rage grew pale and gan to frowne,</l>
                  <l>And brake the ſilence with a vehement ſtile,</l>
                  <l>His courage movde the Princes all the while.</l>
               </lg>
               <lg>
                  <l>Nay rather where I ſtand let ope the ground</l>
                  <l>(Quod he) to ſwallowe me, in pit profound<note place="margin">Azealous godly an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſwere.</note>
                  </l>
                  <l>Yea, rather righteous heauen let firie blaſt,</l>
                  <l>Light on my head that thou on <hi>Sodom</hi> caſt,</l>
                  <pb n="11" facs="tcp:11277:14"/>
                  <l>Eare I my malice cloke or ouerſile,</l>
                  <l>In giuing <hi>Izac</hi> ſuch a councell vile.</l>
                  <l>For if the Leader of this folke prophane</l>
                  <l>Vpon our bodies onelie ſought to raigne,</l>
                  <l>Although that we haue dearely bought alwaye</l>
                  <l>Our freedome from our firſt maternall daye</l>
                  <l>(which dearer is then gold for to be kept)</l>
                  <l>I would aſſent, the holie Church except,</l>
                  <l>But ſince more pride this tyrants hart enroules</l>
                  <l>to lay a greater burden on our ſoules:</l>
                  <l>Who are the vaſſalles of that onely King,</l>
                  <l>That thu<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>der ſends &amp; Scepters down doth thring:</l>
                  <l>,Should we forget him who made vs of nought,</l>
                  <l>,More the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> al wo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>drous things that he hath wroght</l>
                  <l>who treates and loues vs like our father and king,</l>
                  <l>Still vnder ſhadowes of his wondrous wing?</l>
                  <l>Will he that we receaue a Prince ambitious?</l>
                  <l>for <hi>God,</hi> a gods contemner <hi>Nemrode</hi> vitious?</l>
                  <l>whoſe beaſtly life is of ſo vile a fame,</l>
                  <l>That of a man he merits not the name?</l>
                  <l>Goe to, goe to, let men, for men aſſaye</l>
                  <l>with ſword and ſhot, to deale it as we may:</l>
                  <l>The victorie lyes not in mortall hands,</l>
                  <l>Nor barded horſe, nor force of armed bands.</l>
                  <l>theſe are but ſeconde inſtruments of God,</l>
                  <l>VVho, as him liſt, may ſend them euen or od.</l>
                  <l>But if our ſoueraigne God willes ſuch anoye,</l>
                  <l>that folke vncircumſiſde, our land diſtroye,</l>
                  <l>Becauſe we him offend while we haue breath,</l>
                  <l>Alas, yet honour, honour him in death.</l>
                  <pb n="12" facs="tcp:11277:15"/>
                  <l>And if we loſe, and all be ouercome,</l>
                  <l>Let patience winne the glorie of martyrdome.</l>
               </lg>
               <lg>
                  <l>Forſooth, though <hi>Aſſurs</hi> ſoldiers braue &amp; bold</l>
                  <l>Extinguiſh quite the race of <hi>Izak</hi> old,</l>
                  <l>yet ſhall they not deface the liuing lorde,</l>
                  <l>As theſe <hi>Apoſtats</hi> falſly doe afforde.</l>
                  <l>For he, who people firſt this world ſo round,</l>
                  <l>But with one man, from whome the reſt abound</l>
                  <l>And who long after, in an arke of woode</l>
                  <l>Repaird the waſte, made by the genrall floode:</l>
                  <l>May he not eke tranſforme the hardned ſtone,</l>
                  <l>To people who will honour him alone?</l>
                  <l>And may not he do now, as he hath donne,</l>
                  <l>who gaue to <hi>Abrahms</hi> barren wife a ſonne?</l>
                  <l>Them giuing Children moe, then in the heauen</l>
                  <l>Are ſtarrie Circles, light as firie leauen,</l>
                  <l>And mo, then Northre<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> winds that driues the Rack</l>
                  <l>Of <hi>Cyrene</hi> ſands in number can compack</l>
                  <l>VVho will obſerue his law a hundreth fold</l>
                  <l>More zealouſly then wee, who ſhould it holde.</l>
                  <l>,Then, fathers choſe you warres, for better tels,</l>
                  <l>,To loſe like <hi>Iewes,</hi> then winne like infidels:</l>
                  <l>,Let not the greede of gaine your harts attame,</l>
                  <l>,to leaue the right, preferre not, feare to ſhame.</l>
               </lg>
               <lg>
                  <l>Scarſe ended was th'Oration of this Lord,</l>
                  <l>when all the Princes with a ſound accorde:</l>
                  <l>By worde and deed confirmde his good aduiſe:</l>
                  <l>The chiefe Prieſt gladdeſt of this enterpriſe,</l>
                  <l>Vnto the heauen held vp his handes and face,</l>
                  <l>And ſaid, I thanke the lord who of his grace</l>
                  <pb n="13" facs="tcp:11277:15"/>
                  <l>,Conioynes no leſſe our wils, the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> bolds our harts,</l>
                  <l>,A ſure preſage that <hi>God</hi> is on our parts.</l>
               </lg>
               <lg>
                  <l>This done, vnto his princes he deuides</l>
                  <l>The tribes and townes &amp; ordaines them for guides</l>
                  <l>for feare leaſt ſome of them led with ambition</l>
                  <l>In <hi>Izrell</hi> might ſtirre vp ſome new ſedition,</l>
                  <l>So they withdrew, and ſtoutly did prouide</l>
                  <l>this furious ſtorme of <hi>Mars</hi> for to abide.</l>
               </lg>
               <lg>
                  <l>Then as ye ſee ſomtime the home bees,</l>
                  <l>Exerſe themſelfs on buddes of ſweeteſt trees,</l>
                  <l>
                     <note place="margin">Compari<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon.</note>
                  </l>
                  <l>where they ſometime aſſault the buzzing waſpe,</l>
                  <l>That comes to neare their flowrs away to claſpe,</l>
                  <l>Or when they hony drawe from ſmelling time,</l>
                  <l>Or from the palme, or Roſes of the prime:</l>
                  <l>And how they draw their wax with wo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>drous art,</l>
                  <l>Obſeruing iointure iuſt in euerie part,</l>
                  <l>Both vp and downe they build te<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> thouſand ſhops,</l>
                  <l>with equall ſpace fulfilde vp to the tops:</l>
                  <l>Or where the maiſter Bee, of thouſand bands,</l>
                  <l>Conducts the reſt in legions throw the lands:</l>
                  <l>who dayly keeps within their Cities wall:</l>
                  <l>Their houſe, their work, their lawes and maners all.</l>
                  <l>So thus the ſonnes of <hi>Iacob</hi> plyde their paine:</l>
                  <l>with hote deſire their quarrell to ſuſtaine.</l>
               </lg>
               <lg>
                  <l>Some built the breaches of their broke<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> towne,<note place="margin">Prepara<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions of defence.</note>
                  </l>
                  <l>that Heauen, and <hi>Panim</hi> yre, had caſten downe.</l>
                  <l>Some other found a cautell gainſt the Ramme,</l>
                  <l>to ſaue the wall vnbroken where it camme.</l>
                  <l>Thus <hi>Iacobs</hi> townes on alſides had their flankes,</l>
                  <l>with <hi>Gabions</hi> ſtro<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>g with bulwarks &amp; with banks.</l>
                  <pb n="14" facs="tcp:11277:16"/>
                  <l>Some others buſy went and came in routs</l>
                  <l>To terrace towers, ſome vnder baſkets louts:</l>
                  <l>Some others alſo wanting time and might,</l>
                  <l>to ſtrength their towns, yet vſde all kind of ſlight,</l>
                  <l>To dig vp ditches deepe for ciſterns good,</l>
                  <l>To draw to them the beſt and neareſt flood.</l>
               </lg>
               <lg>
                  <l>VVhile th'Armorers with ha<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>mers hard &amp; great</l>
                  <l>On ſtudies ſtrong the ſturdie ſteele doth beate,</l>
                  <l>And makes thereof a corpſlet or a iacke,</l>
                  <l>Sometime a belme, ſometime a mace doeth make,</l>
                  <l>whiles ſheepherds they enarme vnuſde to danger</l>
                  <l>whiles ſimple hirds, &amp; whiles the wa<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>dring ſtra<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ger.</l>
                  <l>The tilling Culter then a ſpeare was made,</l>
                  <l>the crooked Sith became an euened blade:</l>
                  <l>the people foode forgetes, no eaſe they take.</l>
                  <l>Some on a horſe, ſome on his proper backe,</l>
                  <l>Some on a Cart, ſome on a Cammell beares,</l>
                  <l>Corne, wine, and fleſh, to ſerue for many yeares,</l>
                  <l>As done theſe <hi>Emets,</hi> that in ſommer tide,<note place="margin">Compari<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon.</note>
                  </l>
                  <l>Comes out in ſwarmes their houſes to prouide:</l>
                  <l>In Harueſt time (their toyle may beſt be ſeene</l>
                  <l>In paths where they their cariage bring betwene)</l>
                  <l>their youth they ſend to gather in the ſtore,</l>
                  <l>There ſick and old at home do keepe the ſkore,</l>
                  <l>And ouer grainels great they take the charge,</l>
                  <l>Oft turning corne within a chamber large</l>
                  <l>(when it is dight) leaſt it do ſproute or ſeede,</l>
                  <l>Or come againe, or weeules in it breede.</l>
               </lg>
               <trailer>FINIS.</trailer>
            </div>
         </div>
         <div n="2" type="book">
            <pb n="15" facs="tcp:11277:16"/>
            <argument>
               <head>THE SOMMARIE OF THE II. BOOKE.</head>
               <p>¶ We haue hard before, how the people of God vſed al diligence to maintaine the libertie of Gods true religion and their Countrey. Now is ſet forth the ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>treame pride of <hi>Holophernes,</hi> who thought with one worde to ouerthrow them all: But to make himſelfe ſome paſtime, he aſſembleth his counſell to vnderſtand of them what people they were, that inhabited the mountaines in the Frontieres of <hi>Iudea,</hi> that durſt make him reſ<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ſtaunce Vpon this he is informed by the mouth of one of his chiefe Captaines of that, which hee looked not for: to witte, a diſcours of the Hiſtorie of the <hi>Iewes,</hi> from the time of <hi>Abrahams</hi> comming out of <hi>Caldea,</hi> to enter in to the lande of promiſe vnto their deliuerance from the captiuitie of <hi>Babylon,</hi> following the order of the times quoted by the holie Scriptures with the praiſes of the prouidence of the almightie God, in defending of his Church, and a sharpe threatning to thoſe that dare preſume to diſquiet the ſame The chiefe Conſellers of the Heathen hearing this, become more cruell, enſencing their <hi>Generall</hi> to murder this Captaine. But <hi>Holopherne</hi> with vaine ambition deferreth their bloodie re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>queſt, and after that he had outraged him in words, he further blaſphemeth the liuing Lord. And laſtly cauſed him to be bound hand and foote, and ſo ca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ried neare to the Citie of <hi>Bethulia,</hi> where he is by the beſieged Souldiers brought into the Citie, and there declareth his caſe, exhorting them to conti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nue conſtant to God, and their Countrey, and promiſeth his aſſistance to his liues end.</p>
            </argument>
            <head>THE SECOND BOOKE OF IVDITH.</head>
            <lg>
               <l>NOw <hi>Holophern</hi> in <hi>Seythique</hi> Rampier ſtood,</l>
               <l>with ſta<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>dards pight of youthly heathe<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> blood:</l>
               <l>Of nothing thinking leſſe, then warre and fight,</l>
               <l>But in deuiſing paſtime day and night:</l>
               <l>till he was war, that <hi>Iacob</hi> would aduance,</l>
               <l>Againſt his <hi>Pamm</hi> force and arrogance.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>A packe of what a packe of countrcy clownes</l>
               <l>(Quod <hi>Holophern</hi>) that them to battell bownes,</l>
               <pb n="16" facs="tcp:11277:17"/>
               <l>with beggers, bolts, and Leuers, to arreſt</l>
               <l>My warriours ſtrong with whome I haue ſuppreſt</l>
               <l>Both <hi>Tigris</hi> ſwift, &amp; faire <hi>Euphrates</hi> ſtreame,<note place="margin">People of Aſia.</note>
               </l>
               <l>with froſty <hi>Taurus</hi> and rocke <hi>Niphatheame.</hi>
               </l>
               <l>Are they not wrackt? ye cheefs of <hi>Moabits,</hi>
               </l>
               <l>And valiant <hi>Fphrem,</hi> ye ſtrong <hi>Ammonits:</hi>
               </l>
               <l>ye that as neighbours knowes this folke of olde,</l>
               <l>That ſcattred thus, doe all theſe mountaines hold:</l>
               <l>Tell me what men are they, of what of ſpring</l>
               <l>what is their force, their cuſtomes and their king?</l>
               <l>'For wiſe is he that wots with whome hee playes,</l>
               <l>'And halfe is victor as the Prouerbe ſayes.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>The Lord of <hi>Ammon</hi> then, with reurence due,</l>
               <l>Right wiſely ſpack the Duke, and yet, for true,</l>
               <l>He was a <hi>Panim</hi> both of faith, and kinde:</l>
               <l>But ſo (with fained toung) hee ſpake his minde:</l>
               <l>And all the <hi>Hebreus</hi> acts diſcourſt ſo well,</l>
               <l>That <hi>Eſdr'</hi> and <hi>Moyſes</hi> ſeemde in him to dwell,</l>
               <l>As did that ſprite that made the Prophete bleſſe,<note place="margin">Nomb. <hi>23</hi>
                  </note>
               </l>
               <l>the <hi>Iſralits</hi> whome <hi>Balac</hi> did addreſſe,</l>
               <l>To curſe them all, and wadge his couetous toung.</l>
               <l>which ſpake co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>trarie that he would haue ſoung:</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>So, pleaſe it you my Lord, I ſhall diſcire,</l>
               <l>The ſtorie of <hi>Izrell,</hi> yet ſo doing I,</l>
               <l>Am like the modeſt Bee, that takes but ſmall</l>
               <l>Of euerie flowre, though ſhe haue choice of all:</l>
               <l>For where ſhe liſt the ſweeteſt of ſhe crops.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>Theſe people that ye ſee on mountaine tops,<note place="margin">A briefe diſcourſe of th'eſtat of the Iewes.</note>
               </l>
               <l>Encamped in theſe craggs, are of the line,</l>
               <l>Of <hi>Abraham,</hi> who (ſeruing <hi>God</hi> deuine,</l>
               <pb n="17" facs="tcp:11277:17"/>
               <l>That mightie <hi>God</hi> of gods who create all,</l>
               <l>And firmely knit and built this mightie ball)</l>
               <l>Came to this land that then was tilde and ſowne,<note place="margin">Gen. <hi>12.</hi>
                  </note>
               </l>
               <l>And by the name of wealthie <hi>Canaan</hi> knowne.</l>
               <l>VVhere onely God his wealth did multiplie,</l>
               <l>In goods, and ſiluer, gold, and familie.</l>
               <l>And when of age he was an hundreth yeare,</l>
               <l>His wife eke barren, neuer child did beare.</l>
               <l>God gaue them <hi>Izak,</hi> ſwearing that his ſeede,</l>
               <l>Should many Scepters rule and land beſpreede.</l>
               <l>But when that holy <hi>Abraham</hi> was olde:</l>
               <l>And hoped well the promiſe made ſhould holde,</l>
               <l>(O pitious caſe) <hi>Th'immortall</hi> voyce him ſpak:</l>
               <l>And bad him ſacrifice his ſonne <hi>Izak.</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Gen. <hi>
                        <gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="2 letters">
                           <desc>••</desc>
                        </gap>.</hi>
                  </note>
               </l>
               <l>Then like a ſhip betweene two winds beſet,</l>
               <l>Vpon the raging ſea on both ſides bet,</l>
               <l>In doubtſome feare, ne wots what way to keepe,</l>
               <l>Leaſt one of them, confound her in the deepe:</l>
               <l>Makes cloſe her ports, and ſlides on <hi>Neptuns</hi> back:</l>
               <l>At pleaſure of the boiſteous winds to wrack.</l>
               <l>So felt this <hi>Hebrew</hi> in his hart to fight,</l>
               <l>Both loue, and duetie, reaſon, faith and right.</l>
               <l>Nor wiſt he way to take, his troubled ſoule,</l>
               <l>From this to that, continually did roule,</l>
               <l>vntill the time, his heavnly feare and loue:</l>
               <l>His naturall earthlie pitie did remoue.</l>
               <l>Then hauing built the fire and all, anone</l>
               <l>His ſonne he layd vpon the ſacred ſtone,</l>
               <l>And with a trembling hand the cutlaſſe drewe,</l>
               <l>with heauied arme the ſtroke for to enſewe.</l>
               <pb n="18" facs="tcp:11277:18"/>
               <l>When lo: th'Eternall ſtaid the balefull knife,</l>
               <l>And downe it fell, &amp; ſpaird the guiltles life.</l>
               <l>Then <hi>God</hi> content to haue ſo great aſſaye,</l>
               <l>Of <hi>Abrahms</hi> faith: defended him alwaye.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>Of <hi>Izak. lacob</hi> came, &amp; <hi>lacob</hi> than,</l>
               <l>Of valiant ſonne had twelue in <hi>Canaan,</hi>
               </l>
               <l>who (forſt by famine) fled to <hi>Aegipt</hi> land,<note place="margin">Exod. <hi>1.</hi>
                  </note>
               </l>
               <l>wherfore a while, there dwelling good they fand</l>
               <l>&amp; grew ſo great in nomber, that they were,</l>
               <l>a feare to thoſe, that had them harbrowde there,</l>
               <l>And though th'<hi>Egyptians</hi> dayly them oppreſt,</l>
               <l>And burthens on their ſweating backs were dreſt:</l>
               <l>Yet like the valiant <hi>Palme</hi> they did ſuſtaine,</l>
               <l>Their peiſant weight redreſſing vp againe,</l>
               <l>This movde King <hi>Pharo</hi> to command through all</l>
               <l>Great <hi>Nilus</hi> land, where raine doth neuer fall,</l>
               <l>He bad his folke ſhould ſlay where ſo they came,</l>
               <l>All children males the ſeede of <hi>Abrahame,</hi>
               </l>
               <l>Aſſoone as they from mothers wombs were free,</l>
               <l>Their day of birth ſhould be their day to dee.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>O cruell <hi>Tiger</hi> thinks thou that this deede</l>
               <l>Of <hi>Izak</hi> may cut of th'immortall ſeede?<note place="margin">Excla<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mation.</note>
               </l>
               <l>well may it ſtay the ſucklings for to liue,</l>
               <l>&amp; kill th'accuſtomde frute that heavne doth giue:</l>
               <l>But ſpite of this, men <hi>Iacobs</hi> ſeede ſhall ſee</l>
               <l>In flouring ſtate to rule all <hi>Cananee.</hi>
               </l>
               <l>The firſt of euerie houſe ſhall feele the hand</l>
               <l>And wrath of <hi>God</hi> againſt this law to ſtand.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>It fortunde <hi>Pharos</hi> daughter with her traine</l>
               <l>Of Ladies faire to play them on the plaine,</l>
               <pb n="19" facs="tcp:11277:18"/>
               <l>Vpon the ſhoare where <hi>Goſſan</hi> floode doth ſlide</l>
               <l>where after many paſtimes they had tride,</l>
               <l>She hard an enfant weepe amongſt the reedes,</l>
               <l>Then iudging it for one of <hi>Izaks</hi> ſeeds:</l>
               <l>As ſo it was, yet, with <hi>Paternall</hi> feare,</l>
               <l>Againſt his piteous plaint ſhe cloſde her eare:</l>
               <l>But after vewing in that enfants face,</l>
               <l>I know not what of fauour and of grace,</l>
               <l>which did preſage his greatnes to enſewe:</l>
               <l>Loue vanquiſt lawe, and pittie dread withdrewe:</l>
               <l>So from the ſloode not onely ſhe him caught,</l>
               <l>But curiouſly ſhe cauſde him to be taught:</l>
               <l>As her owne ſonne, O ſonne elect of <hi>God,</hi>
               </l>
               <l>That once ſhall rule the people with thy rod.<note place="margin">Admira<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion.</note>
               </l>
               <l>Thou haſte not found a ſeruant for thy mother,</l>
               <l>But euen a Quene to nurſe thee and none other.</l>
               <l>"Now ſee how <hi>God</hi> alwayes for his elect</l>
               <l>"Of wicked things can draw a good effect</l>
               <l>"his prouidence hath made a wicked thing</l>
               <l>"Vnto his owne great profit for to bring.<note place="margin">Note.</note>
               </l>
               <l>"VVhen <hi>Ioſephs</hi> brether ſold him like a ſlaue,<note place="margin">Gen. <hi>41.</hi>
                  </note>
               </l>
               <l>"He after came a kingly place to haue.</l>
               <l>"Of <hi>Haman</hi> proude the darke enuious hate,</l>
               <l>"brought <hi>Mardoche</hi> the iuſt to great eſtate.<note place="margin">Est.</note>
               </l>
               <l>"for where his enmie ſought his ſhamefull end</l>
               <l>"the ſame vnto the worker he did ſend.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>This <hi>Hebrew Moyſes</hi> once as he did keepe</l>
               <l>On <hi>Horeb</hi> mount his father <hi>Iethro</hi> his ſheepe:<note place="margin">Father in Law.</note>
               </l>
               <l>He ſaw a fearefull ſight, a flaming fire:</l>
               <l>Encloſe a thornie buſh whole and entire</l>
               <pb n="20" facs="tcp:11277:19"/>
               <l>From whence a mightie voyce vnto him ſpake,</l>
               <l>which made the grou<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>d betwene the <hi>Poles</hi> to ſhake</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>I <hi>am that one, is, was,</hi> and ay ſhall bee,<note place="margin">Exod. 3.</note>
               </l>
               <l>who creat all of nought, as pleaſeth mee,</l>
               <l>I can deſtroye, I am the great, and Iuſt,</l>
               <l>the faire, the good, the <hi>Hoſie</hi> one to truſt:</l>
               <l>whoſe ſtro<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>g rightha<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>d this world hath ſet in frame,</l>
               <l>I am th'<hi>Almightie God of Abrahame.</hi>
               </l>
               <l>I plague my foes, and graunt my ſeruants grace,</l>
               <l>All thoſe that knowledge me and all their race.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>Then follow thou my will, &amp; quickly go,</l>
               <l>From me, to that Prophane King <hi>Pharao,</hi>
               </l>
               <l>who holds the towrs of <hi>Memphis</hi> and the field.</l>
               <l>Of <hi>Nilus</hi> ſhore that rich encreaſe doth yeld.</l>
               <l>And bid him let my people freely go:</l>
               <l>But if with hardned hart, he will not ſo.</l>
               <l>Stretch out thy ſtaffe for to confirme thy charge,</l>
               <l>And it ſhall turne into a <hi>Serpent</hi> large.</l>
               <l>And this he ſhortly did, the thing to proue.</l>
               <l>It quickned ſo, and on the ground gan moue.</l>
               <l>(O Miracle) he ſaw without all faile,</l>
               <l>It grewe a <hi>Serpent</hi> fell with head and taile:</l>
               <l>which crangling crept, &amp; ranne from trod to trod</l>
               <l>In many a knot, till time th'Almightie God</l>
               <l>Commanded him the ſame for to retaine,</l>
               <l>which to the former ſhape returnde againe.</l>
               <l>Thus ſiling humain ſight, it chaunged forme,</l>
               <l>One while a Rod, one while a creeping worme.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>Then armed with this ſtaffe the lord him ſent,</l>
               <l>The proude Idolatrous princes to torment.</l>
               <pb n="21" facs="tcp:11277:19"/>
               <l>He in the name of <hi>God</hi> full oft did pray,</l>
               <l>the King, to let the <hi>Hebrews</hi> go their way,</l>
               <l>Vnto the deſert, where he did deuiſe,</l>
               <l>To offer <hi>God</hi> a pleaſant ſacrifiſe.</l>
               <l>But <hi>Pharo</hi> cloſde his eare againſt the Lorde,</l>
               <l>And to his holie word would not accorde.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>Then <hi>God</hi> th'Eternall wrought by <hi>Moyſes</hi> hand</l>
               <l>to approue his worde great wonders in that land.<note place="margin">Exod. <hi>4</hi>
                  </note>
               </l>
               <l>For he not onely Riuers turnd to bloode, <note place="margin">Exod. <hi>7.</hi>
                  </note>
               </l>
               <l>But alſo all th heads of <hi>Nilus</hi> floode,</l>
               <l>(which wattreth wealthie <hi>Egypt</hi> with his ſources)</l>
               <l>was turnd to blood amid their ſiluer courſes:</l>
               <l>So that the king him ſelfe his life to feede</l>
               <l>was faine to vſe ſuch water for his neede.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>This <hi>Moyſes</hi> made the froggs in millions creep,<note place="margin">Exod. <hi>8</hi>
                  </note>
               </l>
               <l>From floods and ponds, &amp; ſcrall fro<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> ditches deep,</l>
               <l>who cled all <hi>Miſraim</hi> with their filthie frie,</l>
               <l>Euen on the king, an all his familie.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>To young and old of either <hi>Sexe</hi> that while,<note place="margin">Exod. <hi>9.</hi>
                  </note>
               </l>
               <l>He ſent a plague of ſcalding botches vile:</l>
               <l>So that the <hi>Memphits</hi> layd on beds to reſt,</l>
               <l>with vncouth venim dayly were oppreſt,</l>
               <l>to <hi>Medciners,</hi> the medcine vailed not,</l>
               <l>So ſore the poiſond plague did vndercot.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>He alſo ſmote the forreſts, herbs and gras,</l>
               <l>The flocks of ſheepe and euerie beaſt that was:</l>
               <l>throw poiſon of th'infected ground ſo fell,</l>
               <l>The Morrain made them all to dye or ſwell:</l>
               <l>So that the ſhepherd by the riuer ſide,</l>
               <l>His flock hath rather dead then ſicke eſpide.</l>
               <pb n="22" facs="tcp:11277:20"/>
               <l>He, earthly duſt, to lothly lice did change,</l>
               <l>And dimd the Ayre, with ſuch a cloud ſo ſtraunge</l>
               <l>Of flyes, graſhoppers, hornets, clegs, &amp; clocks,</l>
               <l>That day and night throw houſes flew in flocks,<note place="margin">Exod. <hi>10.</hi>
                  </note>
               </l>
               <l>that with inciſions ſharpe did ſheare the ſkinnes,</l>
               <l>of <hi>Aegipt Panims</hi> throw their proudeſt ynnes.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>And when the heavne moſt quiet ſeemd &amp; fair,</l>
               <l>th'Eternall ſent a tempeſt through the air,</l>
               <l>&amp; at (this <hi>Hebrews</hi> prayer) ſuch a reare</l>
               <l>Of thunder fell, that brought them all in feare.</l>
               <l>Here lay a Bull that woodran while he braſt,</l>
               <l>There lay the Keeper, brunt with thunder blaſt,</l>
               <l>And now the forreſt high that hid the air,</l>
               <l>with many a ſpreeding arme, is ſpoild and bair.</l>
               <l>So that the ſap that grafters keeps with paine,</l>
               <l>which ſhould reſtore the ſtock, and leafe again:</l>
               <l>Is loſte (alas) in leſſe then half a daye,</l>
               <l>the huſbands hoped fiuite gone to decaye.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>VVhat more? th'Eternall darkned ſo the ſkye,</l>
               <l>For three dayes ſpace none could another ſpye,</l>
               <l>that cloude ſo thick, the <hi>Memphis</hi> rebels fand,</l>
               <l>that they might firmly feele it with their hand,</l>
               <l>If ſeemd that <hi>Phoebus</hi> left his ancient round,</l>
               <l>And dwelt three dayes with men of vnderground.</l>
               <l>"And as the ſnne at one ſelfe time is felt,</l>
               <l>"with heate to harden clay, and wax doth melt:</l>
               <l>"ſo <hi>Amrams</hi> ſacred ſonne in theſe proiects</l>
               <l>"made one ſelfe cauſe, haue two contrarie effects.</l>
               <l>"For <hi>Izak,</hi> humbly knew their Lord deuine,</l>
               <l>"But <hi>Pharo,</hi> more and more did ſtill repine,</l>
               <pb n="23" facs="tcp:11277:20"/>
               <l>"Like to the corpſlet colde the more t'is bet</l>
               <l>"with hammers hard, more hardnes it doth get.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>Yet when his ſonne was ſlaine by th'<hi>Angels</hi> ha<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>d,<note place="margin">Exod. <hi>1<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>
                     </hi>
                  </note>
               </l>
               <l>Amongſt the eldeſt heires of <hi>Aegipt</hi> land:</l>
               <l>He was afraide, and let them go that night,<note place="margin">Heyrs.</note>
               </l>
               <l>where pleaſed them to ſerue their <hi>God</hi> of might:</l>
               <l>VVho ſent a cloude before them all the day,</l>
               <l>By night a Piller of fire, to guide their way.</l>
               <l>But ſodainly this tyrant did gainſtand</l>
               <l>His former graunt, and armd all <hi>Aegipt</hi> land</l>
               <l>VVith hote purſute againſt all <hi>lacobs</hi> hoſte,</l>
               <l>that were encamped on the Red-ſea coſte.</l>
               <l>Such noyſe was neuer ſince the foraigne tide,</l>
               <l>Brak throw <hi>Gibraltar,</hi> when it did deuide</l>
               <l>the <hi>Calp,</hi> from <hi>Abill,</hi> or when <hi>Sicill</hi> ſtrand</l>
               <l>Deuorſed was from her <hi>italia</hi> land:</l>
               <l>As was in theſe two campes that one with boſte,</l>
               <l>that other with their waillings filde the coſte:</l>
               <l>It ſeemd the ſounds of furious horſe and men,</l>
               <l>With hornes &amp; pypes to heavne reſounded then.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>O Iugler, ſaid the <hi>Iewes,</hi> what hatefull ſtrife<note place="margin">
                     <hi>Exod.</hi> 14. They <gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="3 letters">
                        <desc>•••</desc>
                     </gap>
                     <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mure.</note>
               </l>
               <l>Hath moued thee to change our happie life.</l>
               <l>What are we fiſhes for to ſwimme the ſeas?</l>
               <l>Or are we foules to fly where as we pleas?</l>
               <l>Beyond the Sea, or ouer hills to ſoare?</l>
               <l>VVas there not graues for vs on <hi>Goſſen</hi> ſhoare:</l>
               <l>But in this deſart heare to dye or haue</l>
               <l>the bloodred <hi>Occean</hi> Sea, to be our graue.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>Then <hi>Moyſes</hi> with his quickned rod that tide</l>
               <l>He ſmote the ſea, which (fearefull) did deuide</l>
               <pb n="24" facs="tcp:11277:21"/>
               <l>Diſcouering land that ſunne had neuer ſeene,</l>
               <l>And ſtaid the ſea, as there two walles had beeues</l>
               <l>which made a paſſage dry of ample ſpace,</l>
               <l>For all to paſſe who were of I <hi>ſaks</hi> race.</l>
               <l>But contrarie the Red-ſea did deuower,</l>
               <l>The barbrous tyrant with his mightie power,</l>
               <l>who proudly durſt himſelf to that preſent,</l>
               <l>which opened but to ſaue the innocent.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>O happie race, ſince god doth arme for thee,</l>
               <l>Both fire and aire, the winds, the clouds and ſee,</l>
               <l>which all vnto thy paye haue whole enclinde,</l>
               <l>Let not co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ſuming time we are out of minde:</l>
               <l>So rare a grace, but let thine elders ſhewe</l>
               <l>this to their noble ſeed that ſhall enſe we:</l>
               <l>And let their ſonnes, vnto their ſonnes recorde</l>
               <l>Throw all the world rheſe wonders of the lorde.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>
                  <hi>God,</hi> with Coeleſtiall breade (in time of neede)</l>
               <l>His loued <hi>Iacob</hi> fourtie yeare did feede:<note place="margin">Exod. 16</note>
               </l>
               <l>And gaue them water from the ſolide ſtone,</l>
               <l>which of it ſelfe, had neuer moiſture none.</l>
               <l>Their caps, their cotes, &amp; ſhoes, that they did weas</l>
               <l>God kept all freſh and newe, full fourtie year.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>And larder, leaſt their ſoules for want of food,</l>
               <l>ſhould faint faile: he of his mercies good<note place="margin">Exod. 20.</note>
               </l>
               <l>Gaue them his law, pronounced by his voyce,</l>
               <l>His ſprite to theirs, in him for to reioyce.</l>
               <l>So teaching them, and vs in precepts ten,</l>
               <l>Our ductie firſt to god, and next to men,</l>
               <l>To th' end that man to man ſhould truely ſtand,</l>
               <l>And ioy ne with God, and neuer break that band.</l>
            </lg>
            <pb n="25" facs="tcp:11277:21"/>
            <lg>
               <l>This mightie <hi>Prophet</hi> dead: Duke <hi>Ioſua</hi> than,<note place="margin">Ioſua</note>
               </l>
               <l>Their Captaine ſtout this <hi>Palmy</hi> prouince wan:</l>
               <l>Throw might of <hi>God</hi> he Scepters did ſubdewe</l>
               <l>Of thirtie tyran kings, whome all he ſlew.</l>
               <l>At his commandment like the thunder ſound,</l>
               <l>The Rampers ſtroug fell fearefully to ground:</l>
               <l>Before the <hi>Tortuſe,</hi> or the horned Ramme,</l>
               <l>Had bet, or mined, from their wall a dramme:</l>
               <l>For euen of hornes, full hoarſe, their fimple blaſt</l>
               <l>An engine was, their towres adoune to caſt.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>He prayd the heavne for to prolong the daye,</l>
               <l>And made the horſes of the ſunne to ſtaye,</l>
               <l>To th'e<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>d, the night ſhould not with cloud be eled</l>
               <l>To ſaue the faithles, that before him fled.</l>
               <l>Now when this <hi>Panim</hi> ſcourge (with age at laſt)</l>
               <l>Had left this life, and vnto heauen paſt:</l>
               <l>Then <hi>Izak</hi> had of Rulers ſundrie men,</l>
               <l>whoſe golrious acts deſerues eternall pen.</l>
               <l>who knowes not <hi>Samgar, Barac,</hi> and <hi>Othoniell?</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Indger.</note>
               </l>
               <l>The valiant <hi>Delbor, Ahud,</hi> and good <hi>Samuell?</hi>
               </l>
               <l>What land (O <hi>Sampſon</hi>) rings not thy renowne,</l>
               <l>who ſole, vnarmed, bet an Army downe?</l>
               <l>what laude to <hi>Iephthe</hi> iuſtly might we lowe:</l>
               <l>Had he not hurt hsi owne, through haſtie vowe?</l>
               <l>What hill or dale, what flood or fixed ground.</l>
               <l>Doth not the famous <hi>Gedeons</hi> praiſe reſounde?</l>
               <l>In later time, their kings ſome good, ſome bad</l>
               <l>Of all the <hi>Hebrew</hi> ſtate the ruling had.</l>
               <l>Had I the Harpe of <hi>Dauid</hi> (holy King)</l>
               <l>None other ſound but <hi>Dauid</hi> would I ſing,</l>
               <pb n="26" facs="tcp:11277:22"/>
               <l>But euen as all the deeds that <hi>Dauid</hi> did,</l>
               <l>Could not be done by none, but by <hi>Dauid:</hi>
               </l>
               <l>So none but <hi>Dauid,</hi> on his yvrie harpe,</l>
               <l>The glorious praiſe of <hi>God</hi> could onely carpe.</l>
               <l>But here his praiſe, I preaſe not to proclame,</l>
               <l>Leaſt I throw want of ſhkill obſcure the ſame.</l>
               <l>Yet leaue I not his Sonne, whome grace deuine<note place="margin">Salomon</note>
               </l>
               <l>made noleſſe rich, then wondrous of engine:</l>
               <l>whoſe doctrine drew to <hi>Salem</hi> from all wheare,</l>
               <l>A hundreth thouſand wyzards him to heare:</l>
               <l>From <hi>Araby,</hi> from <hi>Ynde, to Affrik</hi> ſhore,</l>
               <l>His toung entyſd them with his cunning lore.</l>
               <l>Shall I forget the kings who ouerthrew,<note place="margin">Ioſiat.</note>
               </l>
               <l>Idolatrie and plaſte religion dewe?</l>
               <l>Shall I forget that King, who ſaw deſcend<note place="margin">Hezekiath. Ierulalem</note>
               </l>
               <l>A win ged <hi>Hoſte Solyma</hi> to defend?</l>
               <l>Shall I forget him, who before his eene,<note place="margin">Aſa.</note>
               </l>
               <l>Enchaſt the bands of <hi>Chus</hi> on <hi>Gerar</hi> greene?</l>
               <l>Shall I forget him, who preparing fight<note place="margin">Ioſapbas.</note>
               </l>
               <l>gainſt <hi>Ammon, Seir,</hi> &amp; <hi>Moabs,</hi> Idoll might,</l>
               <l>Saw ech of their three hoſtes on others fall,</l>
               <l>And with them ſelfs their ſelfs, diſconfit all?</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>Yet, for their ſinnes God gaue them in the ha<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ds</l>
               <l>Of <hi>Calde</hi> kings, who conquerd all their lands:</l>
               <l>And tooke king <hi>Zedekee,</hi> and made an end</l>
               <l>Of that Impyre, till God did <hi>Gyrus</hi> ſend,</l>
               <l>VVho ſet them free, and gaue them of his grace</l>
               <l>Two rulers of their owne. And now this place</l>
               <l>Is kept, by ſacred <hi>Ioachim,</hi> whoſe powers</l>
               <l>conſiſts not onely within <hi>Syons</hi> towers:</l>
               <pb n="27" facs="tcp:11277:22"/>
               <l>But <hi>Edom, Sidon, Moab,</hi> and we all</l>
               <l>Do know his ſtrength &amp; knowes him principall.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>Now Sir ye hear the progreſſe firſt &amp; laſt</l>
               <l>Of <hi>Izaks</hi> race in order as it paſt.</l>
               <l>Onewhile the Lord enhau<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ſt them to the ſkye:</l>
               <l>Onewhile he drew them down in deeps to lye.</l>
               <l>'But were he Iudge, or Prince, or king of might,</l>
               <l>'ſho reuld the <hi>Hebre</hi> ws polycie aright,</l>
               <l>'VVhile they obſerude thaliance made before,</l>
               <l>'by their forefathers who to God them ſwore</l>
               <l>'In happie ſtate all others they ſurpaſt:</l>
               <l>'And vnderfoote their proudeſt foes were caſt.</l>
               <l>'And all the world, that their deſtruction ſought</l>
               <l>'Againſt their ſtate, and name, preuailed nought.</l>
               <l>'But contrarie: as oft as they aſtraide</l>
               <l>'From god their guide, he on their ſhoulders laid:</l>
               <l>'The Barbare yock of <hi>Moab,</hi> &amp; oftymes</l>
               <l>'Of <hi>Paleſtine</hi> &amp; <hi>Ammon,</hi> for their crymes,</l>
               <l>'The heauie hand of God was ſeene to be,</l>
               <l>'On their ingratefull infidelitie.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>Now, if ſo be that any odious ſinne,</l>
               <l>Prouoke their Lord his Iuſtice to beginne:</l>
               <l>Then myne not you their towres nor tourets tall,</l>
               <l>Nor bring the wrackſom engine to their wall:</l>
               <l>Nor place thy battries braue, not yet aduenter,</l>
               <l>with thy couragious camp the breacth to enter.</l>
               <l>For if <hi>Libanus</hi> mout or <hi>Carmell</hi> faire</l>
               <l>Or <hi>Niphathaei</hi> ſhould parke them from repaire:</l>
               <l>If <hi>Ynde</hi> and <hi>Nilus</hi> with the <hi>Rhene</hi> and <hi>Rhone</hi>
               </l>
               <l>to cloſe them round about, ſhould runne in one.</l>
               <pb n="28" facs="tcp:11277:23"/>
               <l>For their defence: yet ſhall they not withſtand.</l>
               <l>(With all their force) thy furious fighting hand.</l>
               <l>But if they haue not broke the bnad in deede</l>
               <l>That God with <hi>Abrahm</hi> made &amp; with his ſeedc:</l>
               <l>Beware my Lorde, beware to touch or moue</l>
               <l>Theſe people that the Lord ſo much doth loue.</l>
               <l>For though ſouth <hi>Autan,</hi> would diſpeople his la<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ds,</l>
               <l>And bring the blackeſt <hi>Mores</hi> to ſwarme in ba<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ds:</l>
               <l>If <hi>Northren Boreas,</hi> vnder his anners colde,</l>
               <l>would bring to field his hideous Soldiers bolde:</l>
               <l>If <hi>Zyphirus</hi> from ſweete <hi>Heſperia</hi> coſte,</l>
               <l>would ſend his choſen armed men to <hi>Hoſte:</hi>
               </l>
               <l>If <hi>Eurus,</hi> for to ayde thine enterpriſe,</l>
               <l>would bring his men fro<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> whence the ſun doth riſe:</l>
               <l>Yet all their numbres hudge, and forces ſtrong,</l>
               <l>Can neuer do to <hi>Iſrel</hi> any wrong,</l>
               <l>Nor hurt one hair if their great <hi>God</hi> ſay nay.</l>
               <l>That god will them defend becauſe he may:</l>
               <l>with one ſmall blaſt confound all kings that darre,</l>
               <l>(As thou doeſt now) prouoke him vnto warre.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>Then like as ye beholde the quiet ſee,</l>
               <l>Not raging when the winds engen dring be:</l>
               <l>But blauncheth firſt, then growes in litle ſpace,</l>
               <l>In wallowing wa wes to flow with fomy face:</l>
               <l>And laſtly beats the banks, and ſhips vnſhrouds,</l>
               <l>with wrackfull waues vphoiſt to higheſt clouds:</l>
               <l>So, almoſt all the princes of that hoſte,</l>
               <l>VVith in ward anger gan to be emboſte,</l>
               <l>As oft as they the praiſe of <hi>God</hi> did heare,</l>
               <l>So to his ſpeech encreaſt their ſpitefull cheare:</l>
               <pb n="29" facs="tcp:11277:23"/>
               <l>which in the end, to blaſphemie them brought,</l>
               <l>Th' immortall <hi>God</hi> of gods to ſet at nought.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>Kill &amp; cut off (quoth they) this traitour fine,</l>
               <l>Whoſe ſubtill talke, with all his whole engine,</l>
               <l>Pretends to ſaue theſe <hi>Hebrcwsews</hi> from our hands,</l>
               <l>And threts vs with vaine gods of forraine lands:</l>
               <l>For if it plaeaſe you (noble prince) to ſend,</l>
               <l>But twentie men of value that are kend,</l>
               <l>VVithin your camp, theſe reckleſſe rebels then</l>
               <l>ſhalbe a pray to all your warlike men.</l>
               <l>(O wicked wight) but then the <hi>Vizroy</hi> ſtout,</l>
               <l>with powre, apeaſde the murmur of the route:</l>
               <l>And to him ſaid: O ſhameles <hi>Prophet</hi> thou,</l>
               <l>what <hi>Sybill</hi> or what charmer tell mee now?</l>
               <l>VVhat Diuell or <hi>Damon</hi> ſo doth thee enſpire,</l>
               <l>that <hi>Izrell</hi> ſhall: of vs haue his deſire,</l>
               <l>Such men, as with no <hi>God</hi> can be content:</l>
               <l>But ſuch as pleaſed <hi>Moyſes</hi> to inuent</l>
               <l>Of his owne head, a <hi>God</hi> that hath no power<note place="margin">Blaſphe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mie.</note>
               </l>
               <l>for to deliuer them, nor thee this hower?</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>Haue we an other <hi>God,</hi> or king of kings,</l>
               <l>then our great Perſian <hi>Monark</hi> now that rigns?</l>
               <l>VVhoſe barded horſe orerunns the Nations all,</l>
               <l>whoſe armed men, out of theſe mountains tall</l>
               <l>ſhall rake theſe Rebels that from <hi>Egypt</hi> came</l>
               <l>To this, where they vniuſtly keep the ſame?</l>
               <l>Dye, dye, thou ſhalt, ô wretch, thy toung vntrue,</l>
               <l>And double hart, ſhall haue their wages due.</l>
               <l>But, foole, what ſpcake I thus? no haſte a while</l>
               <l>Thy blood (O villaine) ſhall not me defile.</l>
               <pb n="30" facs="tcp:11277:24"/>
               <l>so iuſt a paine, ſo ſoone thou ſhalt not haue,</l>
               <l>for thy deceipt, ſo ſoone to go to graue.</l>
               <l>'For in a wretches ſodaine death, at ones</l>
               <l>'Their longſome ill is buried with their bones.</l>
               <l>But to that end I may prolong thy ſtrife,</l>
               <l>In <hi>Bethull</hi> towne I will prolong thy life:</l>
               <l>where euerie howre, thou ſhalt haue ſuch affraye</l>
               <l>to dye vndead a thouſand tymes a daye,</l>
               <l>till time, with the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> who thou ſo ſtro<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>g hath thought</l>
               <l>to ſhameful end with them thou ſhalt be brought.</l>
               <l>what? wherefore trembleſt thou and art ſo paile,</l>
               <l>VVhat ſorrow makes thy hart ſo ſoone to faile.</l>
               <l>If <hi>God</hi> be god as thou right now haſt ſaid,</l>
               <l>then of thy faith, giue witneſſe vndiſmaid.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>A marſhall of the camp then being preſt</l>
               <l>who was not yet ſo cruell as the reſt.</l>
               <l>There tooke this demy Pagan (<hi>Ammons</hi> lord)</l>
               <l>and ſent him bound to <hi>Bethull</hi> (with a corde)</l>
               <l>Then euen as in his clawes the kite doth beare,</l>
               <l>the chirping chicken throu the weather cleare:</l>
               <l>while that the cakling hen below on ground,</l>
               <l>Bewailes her bird with vaine lamenting ſound.</l>
               <l>So in like woe his worthie men were left,</l>
               <l>For that ſo worthie a chief was them bereft</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>The townſmen the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> beholding neare their wall</l>
               <l>Theſe <hi>Miſcreants,</hi> to armour ſtraight they fall</l>
               <l>yclad in plate and maill &amp; runs in bandes,</l>
               <l>And fearſly fronts their foes with ſteele in hands</l>
               <l>as faſt as done the riuers doune the hils,</l>
               <l>that with their murmur hudge the deepes vpfils.</l>
               <pb n="31" facs="tcp:11277:24"/>
               <l>The Heathen ſeeing this retirde awaye,</l>
               <l>And left the Lord of <hi>Ammon</hi> for a pray</l>
               <l>to th'<hi>Hebrew</hi> ſoldiers who did him conſtraine,</l>
               <l>Though he was willing, with them to remaine.</l>
               <l>VVhen all the folke with preaſe about him paſt</l>
               <l>His eyes and hands vp to the pole he caſt,</l>
               <l>'And thus he ſpak: <hi>O God</hi> that great abyds</l>
               <l>'vpon th'Immortall ſeate and iuſtly guyds</l>
               <l>'the ruled courſe of heavne, whoſe liuing ſpreete,</l>
               <l>'reuiuing ſpreds, &amp; through all things doth fleete:</l>
               <l>'I render thee, O <hi>God</hi> immortall praiſe,</l>
               <l>'for that before I end my wofull dayes</l>
               <l>'Now from th'unfrutefull ſtock thou doeſt me race</l>
               <l>'to graft me in thy frutefull tree of grace,</l>
               <l>'where in diſpite of all co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>trarie ſtrife,</l>
               <l>'I ſhall bring forth the fruits of laſting life.</l>
               <l>And ye, O <hi>Iacobs</hi> ſonnes, thinke not at all</l>
               <l>That I of purpoſe captiue am and thrall:</l>
               <l>So that I meane hereby your wrack to bring</l>
               <l>For <hi>God</hi> he knowes I thinke not ſuch a thing.</l>
               <l>But I am captiue thus becauſe I tolde,</l>
               <l>VVhat wo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>drous works the lord hath done of old,</l>
               <l>to you and your forefathers euer ſtill,</l>
               <l>Delivring them that wold obey his will.</l>
               <l>Then doubt not you a thouſand flaffing flags,</l>
               <l>Nor horrible cryes of hideous heathen hags:</l>
               <l>Coole not your harts, for if the world about,</l>
               <l>would compaſſe you withall their warriours ſtout</l>
               <l>(Prouyding firſt yee ſeeke your help at need</l>
               <l>At power deuine, and not at mortall ſeede)</l>
               <pb n="32" facs="tcp:11277:25"/>
               <l>You ſurely ſhall ſee <hi>Mocmurs</hi> renning flood,</l>
               <l>Made red, with <hi>Aſſurs</hi> hoſte and <hi>Ethnique</hi> blood:</l>
               <l>ye ſurely ſhall, ſee men not vſde to fight,</l>
               <l>Subdue their foes, that ſeemes of greater might.</l>
               <l>The hand of <hi>God</hi> aſſailes you not with hate,</l>
               <l>but for your weale your pride he will abate,</l>
               <l>To let you wit, it is within his power,</l>
               <l>To leaue or to relieue you euery hower.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>As on th'vnſavrie ſtocke the lillie is borne:</l>
               <l>And as the roſe growes on the pricking thorne:</l>
               <l>So modeſt life with ſobs of grieuous ſmart,</l>
               <l>And cryes deuout, comes from an humbled hart:</l>
               <l>For euen the faithfull flocke are like the ground,</l>
               <l>That for good frute, with weeds will ſtill abound.</l>
               <l>If that the ſhare and culter ydle lye,</l>
               <l>That ryues the ſoyle and roots the brambles bye:</l>
               <l>But in the end, <hi>God</hi> will his yre relent,</l>
               <l>Aſſoone as ſinners truely will repent:</l>
               <l>And ſaue you from theſe plagues that preſent be</l>
               <l>In ſhorter time then ye do thinke to ſee.</l>
               <l>take courage friends, &amp; vanquiſh God with teares</l>
               <l>And after, we ſhall vanquiſh with our weares</l>
               <l>theſe enmies all. Now if there reſt in me</l>
               <l>the former force that once was wont to be:</l>
               <l>If elde haue not decaid my courage bolde,</l>
               <l>That I haue had with great experience olde,</l>
               <l>I render me to ſerue you to my end:</l>
               <l>for <hi>Iacobs</hi> weale, <hi>Gods</hi> law for to defend.</l>
            </lg>
            <trailer>FINIS.</trailer>
         </div>
         <div n="3" type="book">
            <pb n="33" facs="tcp:11277:25"/>
            <argument>
               <head>THE SOMMARIE OF THE III. BOOKE.</head>
               <p>¶ In this third booke the <hi>Poet</hi> ſetteth forth the ſeege of <hi>Bethulia,</hi> and the ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tremitie that God permitted them to f<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ele, thereby to giue an entrie to his mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>raculous deliuerance: who is accuſtomed to lead his people to the gates of death, and from thence to retyre them aboue all humaine expectation, to the end they should confeſſe that the arme of fleſh, nor worldly wiſedome main<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teines not the Church: but the onelie fauour of the Almightie to whome the whole glorie of duetie ſhould be rendred. Farder: thre principall things ar to be noted: Firſt, the preparations of the beſeegers, and the defences of the be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſeeged, and how after throw the councell giuen to <hi>Holopherne</hi> for the re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtraint of the water from the towne enſewes a furious aſſault, which the Iewes repelled with great paine: Secondly, the extreame deſolation through want of water, whereof proceedeth ſundrie ſorts of death, with lamentations murmurations, and daunger of mutine within the Cittie, and how the <hi>Go<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uernour</hi> endeuoures himſelf with wiſe and godly admonitio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>s to appeaſe the ſame: But the commons in this hard eſtate regarding no reaſon, required to re<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>der the Citie, rahter the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> to periſh in ſuch appara<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t miſerie. The <hi>Gouernour</hi> being caried with a humaine prudence promiſeth to render the towne with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>in fiue dayes, <gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>f God ſend them no ſuccour. Yet ſuch is the eſtate of gods church in this world, that when all things faileth, God manifeſteth his power: And therefore in the third part is <hi>Iudith</hi> introduced, who (being eſpecially moued by the reading of Holy Scriptures) is encouraged to deliuer her countrie: but when she vnderstoode the reſolution of the Maieſtrats, She (being in eſtima<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion honourable) modeſtly reproues them. After their excuſe, she promiſeth to attempt ſomething for the publike weale: not showing her deuiſe, but onelie deſired to haue paſſage by night vnto the enemies camp, and this is granted.</p>
            </argument>
            <head>THE THIRDE BOOKE OF IVDITH.</head>
            <lg>
               <l>THhe Snoring ſnoute of reſtles <hi>Phlegon</hi> blewe,</l>
               <l>Hote on the <hi>Ynds,</hi> and did the daye renewe</l>
               <l>VVith ſkarlet ſkye, when <hi>Heathen</hi> men awooke</l>
               <l>At ſound of drumme, then pike &amp; dart they tooke:</l>
               <l>In order marching, and to combat calles,</l>
               <l>th'vndaunted ſonnes, within their Cities walles.</l>
               <pb n="34" facs="tcp:11277:26"/>
               <l>The meeds in May with flowers are not ſo dect,</l>
               <l>of ſundrie ſauours, hewes, &amp; ſeere effect,</l>
               <l>As in this campe were people different farre</l>
               <l>In toungs &amp; maners, habits, tents, and warre.</l>
               <l>Yea <hi>Chaos</hi> old, where of the world was founded,</l>
               <l>Of members more confuſe, was tot compounded:</l>
               <l>yet ſoundely they in vnion did accord,</l>
               <l>To wage the warre againſt th' <hi>Almightie</hi> Lord,</l>
               <l>who ſhaks the <hi>Poles,</hi> whoſe only breath doth beat</l>
               <l>
                  <hi>Libanus</hi> mount, and makes <hi>Caucaſus</hi> ſweat.</l>
               <l>There came the <hi>Kettrinks</hi> wilde of colde <hi>Hircania:</hi>
               </l>
               <l>Ioynd with the men of great, and leſſe <hi>Armania.</hi>
               </l>
               <l>VVith coppintanks: and there the <hi>Parthian</hi> tall,</l>
               <l>Aſſaid to ſhoot his ſhafts and flee withall.</l>
               <l>The <hi>Perſians</hi> proud (th' Empyre was in their ha<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ds)</l>
               <l>with plates of gold, ſurbraued all their bands.</l>
               <l>The <hi>Medes</hi> de clarde through fortunes ouerthwart</l>
               <l>they loſt their Scepter, not for lacke of hart:</l>
               <l>And that no coſtly cloath nor rich aray,</l>
               <l>Nor painting fine, that on their face they lay</l>
               <l>nor boprrowde hair, of fair &amp; comly length,</l>
               <l>might oght empair, their ancie<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t power &amp; ſtre<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>gth:</l>
               <l>There were the happie <hi>Arabs</hi> thoſe that buields</l>
               <l>In thatched waggons, wandring throu the fields.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>The ſubtill <hi>Tyrians,</hi> they who firſt were clards,</l>
               <l>that ſtaid the wandring words in leaues &amp; barks.</l>
               <l>The men of <hi>Moab, Edom, Ammon,</hi> and</l>
               <l>the People ſparſt on large <hi>Elimia</hi> land.</l>
               <l>The learned <hi>Memphians,</hi> &amp; the men that dwell</l>
               <l>Near-to the <hi>AEthiopians</hi> black &amp; fell.</l>
               <pb n="35" facs="tcp:11277:26"/>
               <l>In ſhort the moſt of <hi>Aſia</hi> (as it wair)</l>
               <l>Encamped was within that army fair.</l>
               <l>So that this Duke mo forraine ſouldiers lad,</l>
               <l>then all the <hi>Hebrewes</hi> natiue people had.</l>
               <l>But they who did the <hi>Hebrewes</hi> greateſt wrong</l>
               <l>were <hi>Apoſtats</hi> of <hi>Ephrem</hi> fearce &amp; ſtrong:</l>
               <l>who fought with hatefull harts them to deface,</l>
               <l>Leaſt they ſhould be eſteemde of <hi>Izaks</hi> race.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>Then, as in time of ſpring the water is warme,</l>
               <l>&amp; crowding frogs like fiſhes there doth ſwarme:</l>
               <l>But with the ſmalleſt ſtone that you can caſt</l>
               <l>to ſtirre the ſtreame, their crouping ſtayes as faſt:</l>
               <l>So while <hi>Iudea</hi> was in ioyfull dayes,</l>
               <l>The conſtancie of them was worthie prayes:</l>
               <l>for that in euerie purpoſe ye ſhould heare</l>
               <l>the praiſe of <hi>God,</hi> reſounding euerie wheare.</l>
               <l>So, that like burning candles they did ſhine</l>
               <l>Among their faithfull flocke, like men deuine.</l>
               <l>But looke how ſoone they hard of <hi>Holopherne,</hi>
               </l>
               <l>their courage quailde &amp; they began to derne.</l>
               <l>Their ardent zeale with cloſed mouth they choke</l>
               <l>their zeale to hote returnd to fuming ſmoke:</l>
               <l>the feare of loſſe of life &amp; worldly good:</l>
               <l>brought Infidels to ſhed their brothers blood:</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>Alas how many <hi>Ephramits</hi> haue we?</l>
               <l>In our vnhappy time all which we ſee</l>
               <l>within the Church like hypocrits to dwell,</l>
               <l>ſo long as by the ſame they proſper well:</l>
               <l>who feines a zeale, th' Euangill to maintaine</l>
               <l>So long as ſerues their honour, or their gaine.</l>
               <pb n="35" facs="tcp:11277:27"/>
               <l>But turne the chance with ſome contrarie wind<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>,</l>
               <l>So that their browes but half a blaſt doe finde,</l>
               <l>Then faints their harts, and they ſeeke other waye,</l>
               <l>Like bankers out their <hi>God</hi> they diſobaye</l>
               <l>Diſcyphring then their malice to be more</l>
               <l>to gods contempt, then was their zeale before,</l>
               <l>And fights againſt the lord with greater hate,</l>
               <l>Then <hi>Celſus</hi> did, or <hi>Iulian</hi> Apoſtate.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>The <hi>Hebrewes,</hi> now from hights of houſes faire</l>
               <l>VVho ſaw ſo many banners beate the aire:</l>
               <l>And men to march againſt their forces ſmall,</l>
               <l>who now might well decerne their feeble wall:</l>
               <l>They ſwoune with feare, &amp; fand none other aid:</l>
               <l>but of that <hi>God,</hi> to whome their fathers parid.</l>
               <l>O father (quod they) father holie king,</l>
               <l>who ſhields vs alwayes vnderneath thy wing:</l>
               <l>Since now the worlde againſt vs doth conſpire,</l>
               <l>Defende vs mightie Lord we thee require.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>Thus hauing humbley praid the Lord of might,</l>
               <l>the <hi>Gouernour</hi> renforſt his watches witht:</l>
               <l>And fires at midnight built in euerie way,</l>
               <l>which amde the night appeare as cleare as day:</l>
               <l>and wakerife through the corpſgard oft he paſt:</l>
               <l>And thought that <hi>Phoebe</hi> hyed her courſe to faſt</l>
               <l>with horſes paile to ſteale awaye the night,</l>
               <l>to leaue the <hi>Hebrewes</hi> to their enmies ſight.</l>
               <l>Againe, the <hi>Pagan</hi> thought ſhe did but creepe,</l>
               <l>Or that with <hi>Latmies</hi> ſonne ſhe was on ſleepe.</l>
               <l>'But humaine wiſhes neuer hath the powre,</l>
               <l>'to haſte or hold the courſe of heavne one howre.</l>
               <pb n="36" facs="tcp:11277:27"/>
               <l>Then as <hi>Aurora</hi> roſe with ſanguine hewe,</l>
               <l>And our <hi>Horyzon</hi> did the day renewe:</l>
               <l>The <hi>Vizroy</hi> made a thouſand trumpets ſound,</l>
               <l>to drawe his ſeatred Cornets to a round,</l>
               <l>who from all parts with ſpeede aſſembled weare</l>
               <l>About the Genrals tent his will to heare:</l>
               <l>As do the hounds about their hunt at morne</l>
               <l>come gladiſhing at hearing of his horne.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>Now when the towne, his ſomo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ds did diſdaine</l>
               <l>to conquer it perforce he plyde his paine:</l>
               <l>And their, th' <hi>Inginers</hi> haue the <hi>Trepan</hi> dreſt,<note place="margin">Engins of Warres</note>
               </l>
               <l>&amp; reared vp the <hi>Ramme</hi> for batterie beſt:</l>
               <l>Here bends the <hi>Briccoll,</hi> while the cable cracks,</l>
               <l>their Croſbowes were vprent with yron Racks.</l>
               <l>Here croked <hi>Coruies,</hi> fleing bridges tall,</l>
               <l>Their ſcathfull <hi>Scorpions,</hi> that ruynes the wall.</l>
               <l>On euerie ſide they raiſe with iointure meete,</l>
               <l>the tymber towres for to command ech ſtreete.</l>
               <l>The painefull Pioners, wrought againſt their will,</l>
               <l>with fleakes &amp; fagots, ditches vp to fill.</l>
               <l>Or vnderground they delue in duſt with paine,</l>
               <l>to raiſe a mount, or make a mount a plaine.</l>
               <l>Or Cauerns cut, where they might ſoldiers hide,</l>
               <l>t'aſſaile the towne at ſodaine vneſpide.</l>
               <l>Some ladders dreſt to ſkale the wall, or els</l>
               <l>to ſteale vpon the ſleeping <hi>Sentinels.</hi>
               </l>
               <l>Some vndermynes, ſome other vndertooke,</l>
               <l>to fire the gates, or ſmore the towne with ſmoke.</l>
               <l>The greateſt part did yet in trenches lurke</l>
               <l>to ſee what harme their engins firſt would wurke,</l>
               <pb n="37" facs="tcp:11277:28"/>
               <l>that if the wall were bet, they wold not faile</l>
               <l>with braue aſſault the Citie to aſſaile.</l>
               <l>There <hi>Mars</hi> to wremyner, there <hi>Bellona</hi> wood,</l>
               <l>Enforced feeble Cowards to ſuck blood.</l>
               <l>their hidious horſes, braying loude and cleare,</l>
               <l>their <hi>Pagans</hi> fell with clamor hugh to heare,</l>
               <l>made ſuch a dinne as made the heavne reſound,</l>
               <l>retented hell, &amp; tore the fixed ground.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>Yet <hi>God</hi> who keeps his wahch aboue the ſkyes</l>
               <l>For his elect, who neuer ydle lyes:</l>
               <l>tooke pittie on his people in that tide,</l>
               <l>Repreſſing (part) this cruell princes pride</l>
               <l>In cauſing all the chiefes of <hi>Moabits,</hi>
               </l>
               <l>of <hi>Edom</hi> ſtrong, &amp; awfull <hi>Ammonits</hi>
               </l>
               <l>to ſpeake him thus, &amp; thus him terrours dreſt.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>O Prince, that Scepter beares aboue the reſt,</l>
               <l>&amp; giues them law, &amp; holds the world in thrall,</l>
               <l>ſet not thy ſoldiers, to aſſault this wall:</l>
               <l>For neither bow, nor ſling, nor weapons long,</l>
               <l>nor ſword, nor buckler, wilbe found ſo ſtrong:</l>
               <l>As is this threatning rock, whoſe mightie corſe</l>
               <l>ſuſtaines their wall, of ſuch eternall forſe,</l>
               <l>that thou can mak no ſkallade on no coſte:</l>
               <l>But on the corpſes dead, of half thine hoſts.</l>
               <l>'The victor can no honour iuſtly clame</l>
               <l>'to loſe the men who ſhould aduance the ſame.</l>
               <l>'O valiant Prince, that fiſher is nor fine,</l>
               <l>'who for a frog will loſe a golden lyne</l>
               <l>'the holy headband ſeemes not to attyre,</l>
               <l>'the head of him, who in his furious yre</l>
               <pb n="38" facs="tcp:11277:28"/>
               <l>'preferrs the paine of thoſe that haue him teend</l>
               <l>'before the health &amp; ſaftie of one freend.</l>
               <l>You may (my Lord) you may in litle fight,</l>
               <l>ſubdue theſe Roags, &amp; not to loſe a knight.</l>
               <l>Surpriſe me firſt their chiefeſt water ſpring</l>
               <l>from whence theſe rebels do their conduits bring:</l>
               <l>The<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> drought ſhal driue the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> fro<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> their whole defe<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ce,</l>
               <l>In cords to yeld them to thine exellence.</l>
               <l>'The noble Lyon neuer ſleas the leaſt,</l>
               <l>'but alway prayes vpon ſome worthie beaſt.</l>
               <l>'The thunderthro wes his ſulphred ſhafts adowne</l>
               <l>'on <hi>Atlaas</hi> high or colde <hi>Righes</hi> crowne.</l>
               <l>'The tempeſt fell more feruently doth fall,</l>
               <l>'on houſes high, then on the homly hall.</l>
               <l>So you my Lord need not to preaſe your powre,</l>
               <l>Againſt ſuch foes as will themſelfs deuowre.</l>
               <l>Sir, this is not for fauour or for neede,</l>
               <l>Nor that this Citties ſack may cauſe vs dreade.</l>
               <l>Nor that we meane thy high attempts to ſtay,</l>
               <l>For ere we from thy ſtandarts ſtirre away,</l>
               <l>For thee, th' immortall gods we ſhall defie,</l>
               <l>For thee, we ſhall breake downe their alters hie:</l>
               <l>For thee, we frankly ſhall purſue &amp; thole,</l>
               <l>th'eternall heat &amp; colde of either <hi>Pole:</hi>
               </l>
               <l>For thee, our hardy hands ſhall help to teare</l>
               <l>From <hi>Ioue</hi> &amp; <hi>Neptune,</hi> both their Eagle &amp; ſpeare:</l>
               <l>For thee, the ſonne for father ſhall not care:</l>
               <l>Nor father ſonne, nor brother, brother ſpare.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>Now, <hi>Holopherne</hi> to conqueſt whole enclynde</l>
               <l>And weing well this counſell in his minde:</l>
               <pb n="39" facs="tcp:11277:29"/>
               <l>Diſmiſſed from his camp a galliard rout</l>
               <l>Of men to guard the Riuers round about.</l>
               <l>This ſtratageme, the <hi>Hebrews</hi> well might know</l>
               <l>to ſee their fountaines runne with paſſage ſlowe.</l>
               <l>Then manfully their ſoldiers out they ſend,</l>
               <l>againſt their foes, the watter to defend.</l>
               <l>There fought the <hi>Pagan</hi> for to winne him fame,</l>
               <l>the <hi>Hebrew</hi> ment, hee would not dye with ſhame.</l>
               <l>Together ſoone, they ſhock with hatefull yre,</l>
               <l>And firſt, they forſt the heathen to retyre:</l>
               <l>who (turning face) againe do them purſewe,</l>
               <l>&amp; wins the victorie from the victors newe.</l>
               <l>So doubtfull was the fight, none could define</l>
               <l>(Saue <hi>God</hi>) to whome the victrie would encline:</l>
               <l>till <hi>Izrell</hi> was on all ſides ouercled</l>
               <l>with clouds of ſhot, then to their towne they fled,</l>
               <l>As doth the <hi>Pilgrim</hi> paſſing through the plaine,</l>
               <l>who is beſet with tempeſt, haile, or raine,</l>
               <l>who leaues his way, and ſeekes himſelf to hide,</l>
               <l>within ſome caue, or hollow mountaine ſide.</l>
               <l>The <hi>Panims</hi> them purſued without all pittie,</l>
               <l>and <hi>Peſlmell</hi> entred almoſt in the Cittie</l>
               <l>At open gate. Then roſe the crye vnſweete</l>
               <l>Offearefull folke who fled in euerie ſtreete,</l>
               <l>And rent their haire &amp; their affrighted face</l>
               <l>as Panims els had wonne that holy place.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>How flee you cowards now &amp; leaues your Port?</l>
               <l>(the Captaine ſayes) haue ye another fort?</l>
               <l>Thinke ye to finde for ſaftie of your crowne</l>
               <l>In this <hi>Bethulia</hi> another <hi>Bethull</hi> towne?</l>
               <pb n="40" facs="tcp:11277:29"/>
               <l>(Alas) if ye make no defence at all,</l>
               <l>while time this tyrant is without your wall.</l>
               <l>How dare you him reſiſt when he hath wunne</l>
               <l>this forte of yours from which ye feebly runne?</l>
               <l>The co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>mo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>s with this chek, broght to their powers,</l>
               <l>where <hi>Cambris</hi> &amp; Sir <hi>Carmis</hi> like two towers,</l>
               <l>Stoode at th aſſaulted gate &amp; did withſtand</l>
               <l>the Heathen hoſt with ech of them in hand</l>
               <l>An yron mace (in ſtead of launces long)</l>
               <l>&amp; brazen bucklers beating back the throng:</l>
               <l>Their habergions like ſtiddies ſtithe they baire</l>
               <l>with helmets high &amp; pennons pight in aire:</l>
               <l>Of equall age they were, &amp; equall length,</l>
               <l>Of equall courage, &amp; of equall ſtrength:</l>
               <l>Like Poplers twaine that recheth vp their tops</l>
               <l>&amp; holds their heads ſo high that none the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> crops:</l>
               <l>But on the Riuers ſide do ſweetely ſway</l>
               <l>Like germaine brether hailſing oft a day.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>The <hi>Heathen</hi> ſeing thus the <hi>Iewes</hi> deſcend</l>
               <l>with edge of ſword their Citie to defend:</l>
               <l>They left th aſſault, and thence retyring went</l>
               <l>(as they commanded were) vnto their tent.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>But when I thinke how xxx. dayes that towne,</l>
               <l>tormented was with miſchiefe vp and downe.</l>
               <l>Tooſad a ſong I cannot heare inuent</l>
               <l>So great a ſadneſſe right to repreſent.</l>
               <l>My hand for horrour ſhakes, &amp; now nomore</l>
               <l>Can lead my ſacred pen as erſt before:</l>
               <l>For now mine eyes, that watred are with teares</l>
               <l>Declares my matter all of miſchief beares.</l>
               <pb n="41" facs="tcp:11277:30"/>
               <l>Oh Sprite from whence all ſprit &amp; life doth co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>me,</l>
               <l>thou loſde the toung of <hi>Zacharie</hi> that was do<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>me.</l>
               <l>and ſent thy <hi>Heralds</hi> through the world to preach</l>
               <l>thy name: And in a hundreth toungs to teach:</l>
               <l>Guide thou my pen &amp; courage to mnelend,</l>
               <l>that to thy honour I this worke may end.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>Although that <hi>Izak</hi> ſawe on euerie hand</l>
               <l>A world of folke againſt his towne to ſtand:</l>
               <l>yet (tracting time) he thought hee would prouide</l>
               <l>no leſſe to keepe, then coole th' Aſſiegers pride.</l>
               <l>But when they fand the conduits cut and rent,</l>
               <l>By which, there water to their towne was ſent:</l>
               <l>Their courage bolde, &amp; all their craks (alas)</l>
               <l>As lickour faild, ſo did their ſtoutneſſe pas.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>Their Lords preferring death to bondage vile,</l>
               <l>Made them beleeue the thing did them beguile:</l>
               <l>To wit, they gaue men hope htat they might keep</l>
               <l>ſufficient watr' in wels, &amp; ceaſterns deepe:</l>
               <l>Through all the towne, the people to relieue,</l>
               <l>That thirſt ſhould not the ſoldiers greatly grieue.</l>
               <l>The maieſtrats in deed had great regard</l>
               <l>To ſee this water wiſely ſpent and ſpard,</l>
               <l>that Bottell ſweete, which ſerued at the firſt</l>
               <l>to keepe the life, but not to ſlocken thirſt.</l>
               <l>When wels grew drye, the co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>mons ran inrage<note place="margin">A viue deſcriptio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> of thirſt.</note>
               </l>
               <l>&amp; ſought out euerie ſink their thriſt t' aſſwage:</l>
               <l>And dra<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>k with lo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>gſom draught the pools in haſte,</l>
               <l>to quench their thirſt with ilcontented taſte:</l>
               <l>which poyſond ayre, enfect their pureſt breath:</l>
               <l>whereby the drinker drank his preſent death.</l>
            </lg>
            <pb n="42" facs="tcp:11277:30"/>
            <lg>
               <l>O wretched folke, who felt ſo hard a ſtrife,</l>
               <l>Drink, or not drink, both ways muſt loſe their life.</l>
               <l>For he that drank, and he that did refraine,</l>
               <l>Had of their enmies both an equall paine.</l>
               <l>For why? the water vile ſlew them throughout,</l>
               <l>No leſſe, then did their enmies them about.</l>
               <l>That wretched towne had neuer a ſtrete nor rewe,</l>
               <l>But <hi>Parcas</hi> their, had found ſome facion newe.</l>
               <l>to murder men, or martyr them with feares,</l>
               <l>As movde the moſt in durate hart to teares:</l>
               <l>If ſo much water in their braines had beene,</l>
               <l>as might forbeare a drop to wete their eene.</l>
               <l>There plaind the oldman that the ſoldier ſtrong,</l>
               <l>Had reft his Bottell from his head with wrong:</l>
               <l>But while he ſpak his hart (for thirſt) did faint,</l>
               <l>And life him left which fruſtrate his complaint.</l>
               <l>The ſoldier braue, Oh hartbrek, for to tell</l>
               <l>his proper vryne dranke thriſt to expell.</l>
               <l>the wofull mother with her ſpitle fed</l>
               <l>Her litle childe half dead in cradle bed.</l>
               <l>The Lady with her Lord at point of death,</l>
               <l>Embracing fals &amp; yelds their lateſt breath:</l>
               <l>'For cruell thirſt came out of <hi>Cyren</hi> land</l>
               <l>'Where ſhe was foſtred on that burning ſand,</l>
               <l>'with hote intracted toung, &amp; ſoncken eene,</l>
               <l>'with ſtomack worne, &amp; wrinkled viſage keene,</l>
               <l>'with light &amp; meigre corſe and pailed vaines,</l>
               <l>'in ſtead of blood that brimſtone hot retaines:</l>
               <l>'Her poyſond mouth blew throw that holy town,</l>
               <l>'ſuch helliſh ayre, that ſtifled vp &amp; down.</l>
               <pb n="43" facs="tcp:11277:31"/>
               <l>The Arters of the <hi>Iewes</hi> in ſuch a way,</l>
               <l>That noght was ſeene but burials night &amp; daye.</l>
               <l>So that the heavne, to ſee their dollours deepe,</l>
               <l>Could ſcarſly keep his courſe, but preaſd to weep:</l>
               <l>And would haue ioind his teares to their co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>plaint,</l>
               <l>if <hi>God</hi> of hoſts had made them no reſtraint.</l>
               <l>Yea I my ſelf muſt weepe, who cannot ſpeake</l>
               <l>the woes, that makes my heauie hart to breake.</l>
               <l>And ſo will ſilent reſt &amp; not reherſe,</l>
               <l>But conterfait the painter (in my verſe)</l>
               <l>who thought his coulours paile could not declare,</l>
               <l>the ſpeciall woe, king <hi>Agamemnon</hi> bare,<note n="*" place="margin">Looke the table</note>
               </l>
               <l>when ſacrificed was his onely race:</l>
               <l>with bend of black, he bound the fathers face.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>Now while the people were in this eſtate</l>
               <l>&amp; with their princes wrangling in debate,</l>
               <l>They thus beſought the lord for to decide</l>
               <l>betweene their ſimpleſſe &amp; their princes pride.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>The lord be iudge of that which ye haue wrought</l>
               <l>&amp; what your wicked counſells hath vs brought.</l>
               <l>If you had offred peace to this great Lord</l>
               <l>At firſt, we might haue wonne him to accord.</l>
               <l>Then happie happie dayes we might haue ſeene,</l>
               <l>&amp; not ſo many ſouldiers murdred beene.</l>
               <l>Alas what hope haue we within this holde</l>
               <l>Our enmies are more meeke a thouſand folde.</l>
               <l>Then are our owne: they, haps, would vs preſerue,</l>
               <l>our wilfull owne, pretends to ſee vs ſterue.</l>
               <l>Our children do our childrens weale denay,</l>
               <l>&amp; headlong haſtes vnto their owne decay.</l>
               <pb n="44" facs="tcp:11277:31"/>
               <l>VVe know, ô Lord, the breaking of thy lawe,</l>
               <l>hath cauſed thee this ſword on vs to draw</l>
               <l>&amp; iuſtly thou thine yrefull bow doeſt bend</l>
               <l>on our vnloyall heads the ſhot to ſend.</l>
               <l>But thou, who doth not long retaine thine yre,</l>
               <l>Againſt thine owne, thy mercie we require.</l>
               <l>Change thou the purpoſe of our fooliſh guides,</l>
               <l>&amp; of theſe <hi>Heathen,</hi> armed at our ſides.</l>
               <l>Or els let vs vpon their weapons fall,</l>
               <l>&amp; of their hands to be diſtroyed all:</l>
               <l>Or we this drougth &amp; deadly venim haue,</l>
               <l>with languiſhing to ſend vs to the graue.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>My brethen deare (the ruler then gan ſay)</l>
               <l>our whole deſire hath beene both night &amp; day.</l>
               <l>Not for to ſee the ſeede of <hi>Abrham</hi> loſte,</l>
               <l>for which we ſtriue againſt this furious hoſte.</l>
               <l>VVhat? haue ye paine? ſo likewiſe paine haue we:</l>
               <l>For in one bote we both imbarked be.</l>
               <l>Vpon one tide, one tempeſt doeth vs toſſe,</l>
               <l>Your common ill, it is our common loſſe.</l>
               <l>Th <hi>Aſſyrian</hi> plague ſhall not vs <hi>Hebrews</hi> grieue,</l>
               <l>when pleaſeth <hi>God</hi> our miſchiefe to relieue,</l>
               <l>which he will doe if ye can be content</l>
               <l>&amp; not with grudge his clemencie preuent.</l>
               <l>Then ſtriue not you againſt that puiſſant king</l>
               <l>who creat all, and gouerns euerie thing</l>
               <l>For confort of his church &amp; children deare,</l>
               <l>&amp; ſuccours them though time do long appeare.</l>
               <l>Sometime an Archer leaues his bow vnbent</l>
               <l>&amp; hong vpon an naile to that intent:</l>
               <pb n="45" facs="tcp:11277:32"/>
               <l>It may the ſtronger be to bend againe,</l>
               <l>And ſhoot the ſhot with greater might &amp; maine:</l>
               <l>Right ſo th'eternall doth witholde his ill</l>
               <l>A longer time (perchaunce) for that he will</l>
               <l>More egerly reuenge him of their crime,</l>
               <l>who do abuſe his long forbearing time.</l>
               <l>When men applauds to ſinne, they count it light,</l>
               <l>And but a matter ſmall in ſinners ſight.</l>
               <l>But in the end the weight doth ſo encreaſe,</l>
               <l>that Iuſtice leaues the ſinner no releaſe,</l>
               <l>Like th'<hi>Vſerer</hi> who lends vpon the ſkore,</l>
               <l>&amp; maks the reckles debters debt the more.</l>
               <l>What if the thundring Lord his iuſtice ſtay,</l>
               <l>And (for ſuch ſinne) do not this tyrant ſlay?</l>
               <l>The waters of the ground and in the aere,</l>
               <l>Are in the hand of <hi>God,</hi> then who is there,</l>
               <l>that dare ſediciouſly his yoke refuſe,</l>
               <l>Although he haue not water now to vſe?</l>
               <l>No, no, though heavne do ſeeme ſerene &amp; cleare,</l>
               <l>On euerie part, &amp; wete doth not appeare.</l>
               <l>He may with moiſture mildly wete the land,</l>
               <l>As fell when <hi>Saull</hi> the Scepter had in hand:<note place="margin">
                     <hi>Sam</hi> 1.12.</note>
               </l>
               <l>For all the ſtarres that do the heavne fulfill,</l>
               <l>Are all but executors of his will.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>All this could not the peoples thriſt aſſwage,</l>
               <l>But thus with murmurs they their Lords outrage:</l>
               <l>what? ſhall we dye, ô ſacred ſoldiers bolde,</l>
               <l>for pleaſure of our lords theſe traytours olde?</l>
               <l>what? ſhall we dye on credit, for to pleaſe</l>
               <l>Theſe wyzard fooles who winks at our vneaſe,</l>
               <pb n="46" facs="tcp:11277:32"/>
               <l>who with our blood, would win the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> ſelfs renown,</l>
               <l>So louable, as neuer ſhall go downe?</l>
               <l>Nay, nay, let vs cut off this ſeruile chaine,</l>
               <l>to free our ſelfs, let vs in hands retaine</l>
               <l>the ruling of this towne, the forte and all:</l>
               <l>Leaſt we into theſe deadly dangers fall.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>Then like a wiſe <hi>Phiſitian</hi> who perſaues</l>
               <l>His patient that in feruent feuer raues:</l>
               <l>Yet hights him more then Art can well performe</l>
               <l>So Prince <hi>Oſias</hi> in this rurall ſtorme,</l>
               <l>He promiſt to the people their intent</l>
               <l>If <hi>God</hi> within fiue dayes no ſuccour ſent.</l>
               <l>Then <hi>Izak</hi> left their ſorrowes all and ſome,</l>
               <l>&amp; preſent wo and feare of chaunce to come</l>
               <l>for that, if they through this, gat not their will:</l>
               <l>At leaſt they would auoyd, the greateſt ill.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>But <hi>Iudtih</hi> the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> whoſe eyes (like fountains two)</l>
               <l>were neuer dry which witneſt well her wo:</l>
               <l>Right ſad in ſound th'<hi>Almightie</hi> ſhe beſought,</l>
               <l>And on the ſacred ſcriptures fed her thought?</l>
               <l>Her prayers much auailde to raiſe her ſpreete</l>
               <l>Aboue the ſkye &amp; ſo, the ſcriptures ſweete:</l>
               <l>A holy garden was where ſhe might finde,</l>
               <l>the medcyne meete for her moleſted minde.</l>
               <l>Then <hi>Iudith</hi> reading there as was her grace:</l>
               <l>She (not by hazard) hapned on that place,<note place="margin">Iudicium. 3.</note>
               </l>
               <l>where the lamehanded <hi>Ahud</hi> (for diſdaine</l>
               <l>to ſee the <hi>Iewes</hi> the <hi>Heathen</hi> yock ſuſtaine)</l>
               <l>Smote <hi>Eglon</hi> with a dagger to the heft,</l>
               <l>And from his flanke the blood and life bereft.</l>
               <pb n="47" facs="tcp:11277:33"/>
               <l>The more ſhe red, the more ſhe wonder had</l>
               <l>of <hi>Ahuds</hi> act, and hote deſire her lad</l>
               <l>t enſue his vertue: yet her feeble kinde</l>
               <l>Empeached oft the purpoſe of her minde</l>
               <l>Propoſing oft the horrour of the deed,</l>
               <l>The feare of death, the danger to ſucceede,</l>
               <l>with haſzard of her name, and more then that,</l>
               <l>Though ſhe likewiſe the peoples freedome gat:</l>
               <l>yet for a man, this act more ſeemly weare,</l>
               <l>than for a wife to handle ſword or ſpeare:</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>VVhile <hi>Iudith</hi> thus with <hi>Iudith</hi> did debate,</l>
               <l>a puft of wind blew downe that leafe by fate:</l>
               <l>Diſcovring vp the ſtorie of <hi>Iacll</hi> how</l>
               <l>ſhe droue a naile into <hi>Siſaras</hi> brow,</l>
               <l>And ſlew that Pagan ſleeping on her bed</l>
               <l>VVho from the <hi>Hebrewes</hi> furious hoſte was fled.</l>
               <l>In teaching vs albeit a tyrant flee,</l>
               <l>yet can he not auoyde the lords decree.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>This laſt example now ſuch courage lent,</l>
               <l>to feeble <hi>Iudith</hi> that ſhe now was bent:</l>
               <l>with wreakful blade to ſley &amp; to deuorſe</l>
               <l>the <hi>Heathen</hi> ſoule from ſuch a ſinfull corſe.</l>
               <l>But while ſhe did her carefull minde imploy</l>
               <l>to find ſome meanes to murder this <hi>Vizroy:</hi>
               </l>
               <l>She hard report (that made her hart to ſwoune)</l>
               <l>Of the determination of the toune:</l>
               <l>Then all the preſent periols to preuent,</l>
               <l>Vnto the rulers of the towne ſhe went:</l>
               <l>Reprouing then with words of bitter ſweete,</l>
               <l>what do ye meane? O princes indiſcreete.</l>
               <pb n="48" facs="tcp:11277:33"/>
               <l>Will ye the helping hand of God reſtraine,</l>
               <l>And captiue it within your councels vaine?</l>
               <l>VVill ye include him vnder courſe of tymes,</l>
               <l>who made days, yeares, all ſeaſons &amp; their prymes:</l>
               <l>Do not abuſe your ſelfs, his power profound</l>
               <l>Is not to mens Imaginations bound:</l>
               <l>God may all that he wills, his will is iuſt,</l>
               <l>God wils all good to them that in him truſt.</l>
               <l>Now fathers: that which doth my hope reuiue</l>
               <l>Is onely this: there is no wight on liue:</l>
               <l>within this towne that hath contracted hands,</l>
               <l>to ſerue du<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>me gods like folke of forraine lands.</l>
               <l>All ſinnes are ſinne, but ſure this ſinne exceeds</l>
               <l>our former faults, by which our blind miſdeeds</l>
               <l>offends the heavne, by which the lord of might,</l>
               <l>Is frauded of his honours due &amp; right.</l>
               <l>In wreſting of the titles of his name:</l>
               <l>To ſtocks, and ſtones, and mettels, men do frame,</l>
               <l>Since <hi>Izak</hi> then from ſuch a fault is free,</l>
               <l>Let vs to gods protection caſt our ee.</l>
               <l>Conſider that all <hi>Iuda</hi> reſts in feare,</l>
               <l>Aſpecting onely our proceedings heare.</l>
               <l>Conſider that all <hi>Iacob</hi> in this treſſe</l>
               <l>will follow either-our force or feebleneſſe.</l>
               <l>Conſider that this houſe and alter ſtands</l>
               <l>(next vnder God) vpholden with your hands.</l>
               <l>Thinke that of <hi>Izrell</hi> whole ye keepe the kaye</l>
               <l>which if ye quite &amp; giue this tyrant waye.</l>
               <l>VVho more then death hates all of <hi>Izaks</hi> kinne,</l>
               <l>we ſhall the name of kinbetrayers winne.</l>
               <pb n="49" facs="tcp:11277:34"/>
               <l>Then ſayd the Captaine I cannot denye,</l>
               <l>that we offended haue the Lord moſt hye.</l>
               <l>Vnwiſe are we, our promiſes are vaine,</l>
               <l>But what? we may not call our word againe.</l>
               <l>But if thou feele thy hart ſo ſore oppreſt,</l>
               <l>that moueth thee to teares for our vnreſt,</l>
               <l>Alas, weep night &amp; day and neuer tyre,</l>
               <l>So that thy weepings may appeaſe the yre</l>
               <l>Of that hie Iudge, who heares in euerie parte</l>
               <l>the perfit prayer of the humble harte.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>I will (quoth ſhe) and if god giue me grace</l>
               <l>Repell the ſiege of this afflicted place</l>
               <l>By famous ſtroke. But ſtay me in no wiſe,</l>
               <l>But byde the ende of my bold enterpriſe:</l>
               <l>And let me goe when night his mantle ſpreeds</l>
               <l>to th'enmies Camp (quod he) if thou wilt needs.</l>
               <l>The great repreſſour of oppreſſors pride</l>
               <l>Preſerue thy hart and hand, and be thy guide.</l>
            </lg>
            <trailer>FINIS.</trailer>
         </div>
         <div n="4" type="book">
            <pb n="50" facs="tcp:11277:34"/>
            <argument>
               <head>THE SOMMARIE OF THE IIII. BOOK.</head>
               <p>¶ According to the promis that <hi>Iudith</hi> made to the beſieged Captaines in <hi>Be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thulia,</hi> the prepareth her ſelfe with armour meete for the execution of her en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>terpriſe: to wit, The inuocation of the name of God, with a holy determinatio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> to deliuer her countrey from the hand of the <hi>Tyrant:</hi> whome she deliberate to ouercome with the ſweete and faire apparence of her amiable beutie and be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hauiour. At her departing to the enemies camp, our <hi>Poet</hi> introduceth one of the chiefe Captaines of the towne diſcriuing to another, her ſtock and vp<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bringing, with the progreſſe of her three eſtates, <hi>Virginitie, Mariage,</hi> and <hi>Widowhood:</hi> Thereby ſetting forth a ſingular example of all womanly be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hauiour and vertue. After her enterance to the Camp, she is brought to <hi>Ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lophernes,</hi> who was curious to know the cauſe of her comming there. And after audience giuen, he is ſo ſurpriſed with her beutie &amp; eloquent language, that she obtaineth licence to withdrawe herſelf by night to the next valley, there to pray to God and continuing this exerciſe, she requireth ſtrength of the Hyest that in taking away the chieftaine, she might as one inſtant de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtroye all the <hi>Heathen</hi> Armie. Herein giuing example that the beginning and end of all high attempts, ought to be grounded vpon the fauour and ear<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſt calling vpon him, without whome all wiſedome, and humaine force is nothing but wind: and who contrariewiſe, may by the moſt feeble inſtrume<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ts of the world, execute things moſt incredible and incomprehenſible to humaine capacitie.</p>
            </argument>
            <head>THE FOVRTH BOOKE OF IVDITH.</head>
            <lg>
               <l>THen wofull <hi>Iudith</hi> with her weeping ees</l>
               <l>Beholding heavn &amp; proſtrate on her knees:</l>
               <l>Held vp her guiltles hands and <hi>God</hi> beſought,</l>
               <l>Diſcovring him the ſecrets of her thought.</l>
               <l>O God (quod ſhe) who armed with a ſpeare</l>
               <l>Dan <hi>Symeon,</hi> who reuengde his ſiſter deare:</l>
               <l>Lend me the blade in hand, that I may kill</l>
               <l>this <hi>Tyrant</hi> that exceedes all <hi>Sichems</hi> ill.</l>
               <pb n="51" facs="tcp:11277:35"/>
               <l>Who not contents to ſoile the ſacred bed</l>
               <l>of wedlocke chaſte, but more with miſchiefe leds</l>
               <l>Entends thy holie name for to confound,</l>
               <l>And race <hi>Solyma</hi> temple to the ground.</l>
               <l>Ambitious <hi>Satrap</hi> he, whoſe hope doth ſtand</l>
               <l>In mortall men, led with vnrighteous hand.</l>
               <l>who rules a hundreth thouſand ſtalworth ſteeds</l>
               <l>that combat craues &amp; in our paſtures feeds.</l>
               <l>Not dreading thee, who dau<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ts both man &amp; beaſt,</l>
               <l>And kills &amp; captiues them when they weene leaſt.</l>
               <l>who ſtre<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>gths the pore &amp; prydful me<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> down thrings</l>
               <l>&amp; wracks at once the powers of puiſſant kings.</l>
               <l>Grant gratious <hi>God</hi> that his be witched wit</l>
               <l>May with my criſped haire be captiue knit.</l>
               <l>Grant that my ſweet regards may gall his hart</l>
               <l>with darts of loue to cauſe his endles ſmart.</l>
               <l>Grant that theſe gifts of thine my beutie ſmall</l>
               <l>may bind his furious rage, &amp; make him thrall:</l>
               <l>grant that my artificiall tong may moue</l>
               <l>His ſubtill craft &amp; ſnare his hart in loue:</l>
               <l>But chiefly lord grant that this hand of mine</l>
               <l>may be the <hi>Pagans</hi> ſcourge &amp; whole ruine:</l>
               <l>to th'end that all the world may know our race,</l>
               <l>Are ſhrouded ſo in rampiers of thy grace.</l>
               <l>that neuer none againſt vs durſt conſpire,</l>
               <l>that haue not felt at laſt thy furious yre:</l>
               <l>Euen ſo good Lord let none of theſe prophane</l>
               <l>Returne to drinke of <hi>Euphrate</hi> nor <hi>Hytane.</hi>
               </l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>Thus <hi>Iudith</hi> prayd with many-a trickling teare,</l>
               <l>And with her ſighs her words retrenched weare.</l>
               <pb n="52" facs="tcp:11277:35"/>
               <l>At night, ſhe left her chamber ſole and colde,</l>
               <l>Attyrde with <hi>Ceres</hi> gifts and <hi>Ophir</hi> golde.</l>
               <l>O ſiluer <hi>Diane,</hi> regent of the night,</l>
               <l>Darſt thou appeare before this lucent light?</l>
               <l>This holy ſtarre whoſe contr'a ſpect moſt clear,</l>
               <l>Doth ſteine thy brothers brightnes in his <hi>Sphears</hi>
               </l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>While thus ſhe ment (vnſeene) away to ſlide,</l>
               <l>Her pearles and Iewels cauſd her to be ſpide.</l>
               <l>the muſk and ciuet Amber as ſhe paſt</l>
               <l>Long after her a ſweete perfume did caſt.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>A <hi>Carboncle</hi> on her Chriſtall brow ſhe pight,</l>
               <l>whoſe firie gleames expeld the ſhadie night.</l>
               <l>Vpon her head a ſiluer criſp ſhee pind,</l>
               <l>Loſe wauing on her ſhoulders with the wind.</l>
               <l>Gold, band her golden haire: her yvrie neck,</l>
               <l>the Rubies rich, and Saphirs blew did deck.</l>
               <l>And at her eare, a Pearle of greater vallewe</l>
               <l>ther hong, the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> that th'Egiptia<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> Quene did ſwallew.</l>
               <l>And through her collet ſhewde her ſnowie breſt,</l>
               <l>Her vtmoſt robe was coulour blew Coeleſt,</l>
               <l>Benetted all with twiſt of perfite golde,</l>
               <l>Beſeeming well her comely corps tenfolde.</l>
               <l>VVhat els ſhe weare, might well bene ſene vpon,</l>
               <l>that Queene who built the tours of <hi>Babylon.</hi>
               </l>
               <l>And though that ſhe moſt modeſt was indeede</l>
               <l>yet borrowd ſhe ſome garments at this neede.</l>
               <l>From Dames of great eſtate, to that entent</l>
               <l>this <hi>Pagan</hi> Prince ſhe rather might preuent.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>
                  <hi>Achior</hi> then who watched at the gate,</l>
               <l>And ſaw this Lady paſſing out ſo late,</l>
               <pb n="53" facs="tcp:11277:36"/>
               <l>To <hi>Carmis</hi> ſpak, who warded eke that night</l>
               <l>what is ſhe this? where goes this gallant wight</l>
               <l>ſo trim in ſuch a tyme: hath ſhe no pittie</l>
               <l>of this moſt wretched perſecuted Cittie?</l>
               <l>Quod <hi>Carmis</hi> then, their flouriſht heare of late</l>
               <l>
                  <hi>Merari</hi> one, that was of great eſtate.</l>
               <l>Who had no childe but one &amp; this is ſhe,</l>
               <l>The honour of that houſe and familie.</l>
               <l>The fathers now do venture bodie and ſoule,</l>
               <l>that treaſures vpon treaſures they may roule:</l>
               <l>But for the wit or learning neuer cairs,</l>
               <l>that they ſhould leaue to their ſucceeding hairs,</l>
               <l>Like thoſe that charely keepes their rich araye</l>
               <l>In coffers cloſe &amp; lets it their decaye:</l>
               <l>while that the naked bodies dyes for cold,</l>
               <l>for whome the clothes are dearly bought &amp; ſold.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>But as the painfull plowman plyes his toyle,<note place="margin">Compari<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon.</note>
               </l>
               <l>with ſhare and culter ſhearing throug the ſoyle</l>
               <l>that coſt him deare, and ditches it about,</l>
               <l>Or crops his hedge to make it vnder ſprout,</l>
               <l>And neuer ſtayes to warde it from the weede:</l>
               <l>But moſt reſpects to ſo we therin good ſeede:</l>
               <l>to thend, whe<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> ſommer decks the medowes plaine,</l>
               <l>He may haue recompence of coſts &amp; paine:</l>
               <l>Or like the mayd who carefull is to keepe,</l>
               <l>the budding flowre that firſt begins to peepe</l>
               <l>Out of the knop, and waters it full oft</l>
               <l>to make it ſee nly ſhow the head aloft,</l>
               <l>that it may (when ſhe drawes it from the ſtocks)</l>
               <l>Adorne her gorget white, and golden locks:</l>
               <pb n="54" facs="tcp:11277:36"/>
               <l>So wiſe <hi>Merari</hi> all his ſtudie ſtilde,</l>
               <l>to facion well the maners of this childe,</l>
               <l>that in his age he might of her retire,</l>
               <l>Both honour &amp; confort to his harts deſire:</l>
               <l>For looke how ſoone her childiſh cou<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>g could chat</l>
               <l>as children do, of this thing or of that.</l>
               <l>He taught her not to reade inuentions vaine,</l>
               <l>As fathers dayly do that are prophaine:</l>
               <l>But in the holy ſcriptures made her reade,</l>
               <l>that with her milke ſhe might eue<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> ſuck the dreade</l>
               <l>of the moſt high. And this was not for nought</l>
               <l>Inſomuch as in ſhort time ſhe out brought</l>
               <l>Apparant frutes of that ſo worthie ſeede,</l>
               <l>which chaungde her earthly nature far indeede:</l>
               <l>As done the pots that long retains the taſte</l>
               <l>Of licour ſuch, as firſt was in them plaſte:</l>
               <l>Or like the tree that bends his eldren braunch,</l>
               <l>that way, wher firſt the ſtroke has made him lau<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ch.</l>
               <l>So ſee we wolfs, and bears, and harts full olde,</l>
               <l>Some tamenes from their dau<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ted youth to holde.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>Thus ere the Moone twelf doſen chau<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ges paſt,<note place="margin">Virginitie</note>
               </l>
               <l>the maydens maners faire in forme were caſt.</l>
               <l>For as the perfite pylot feares to runne</l>
               <l>Vpon the rocks, with ſingling ſheet doth ſhunne</l>
               <l>
                  <hi>Cyanes</hi> ſtraites or <hi>Syrtes</hi> ſinking ſands,</l>
               <l>Or cruell <hi>Capharois</hi> with ſtormy ſtrands:</l>
               <l>So wyſely ſhe diſhaunted the reſort</l>
               <l>Of ſuch as were ſuſpect of light report.</l>
               <l>Well knowing that th'acquaintance with the ill</l>
               <l>Corrupts the good. And though they euer ſtill</l>
               <pb n="55" facs="tcp:11277:37"/>
               <l>Remain vpright: yet ſome will quarrell pike</l>
               <l>&amp; common brute will deeme them all alike.</l>
               <l>For looke how your Companions you clect</l>
               <l>for good, or ill, ſo ſhall you be ſuſpect.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>This prudent Dame delyted not in daunce,</l>
               <l>Nor ſitting vp nor did her ſelfe aduaunce:</l>
               <l>In publike place, where playes &amp; banquets beene</l>
               <l>In euerie houſe to ſee, &amp; to be ſeene.</l>
               <l>But rather vnderſtanding ſuch a trade,</l>
               <l>Had bene the wrak of many-a modeſt mayd:</l>
               <l>who following wandring <hi>Dina</hi> wanton dame,</l>
               <l>Haue ofty me put their noble houſe to ſhame:</l>
               <l>ſhe kept at home her fathers habitation,</l>
               <l>Both day and night in godly conuerſation.</l>
               <l>She pittious Nurſe applyde her painfull thought,</l>
               <l>to ſerue &amp; nouriſh them that her vpbrought:</l>
               <l>Like to the gratefull ſtork that gathereth meate,</l>
               <l>&amp; brings it to her elders for to eate,</l>
               <l>And on a firtree high, with <hi>Boreas</hi> blowne,</l>
               <l>Giues life to thoſe, of whome ſhe had her owne.</l>
               <l>But if ſhe might ſome howre from trauell quite</l>
               <l>At vacant tyme it was her chiefe delyte</l>
               <l>to read the ſcriptures, where her faithfull mind</l>
               <l>Might confort of the heavnly <hi>Manna</hi> finde.</l>
               <l>Sometyme ſhe broyded on the anuas gall,</l>
               <l>Some bird or beaſt, or Aegle or Eliphant tall.</l>
               <l>VVhile ſubtely with ſiluer nedle fine</l>
               <l>ſhe works on cloth ſome hiſtorie deuine.</l>
               <l>Hear <hi>Lot</hi> eſcaping the deuouring fire</l>
               <l>From ſinnefull <hi>Zodom</hi> ſhortly doth retire</l>
               <pb n="56" facs="tcp:11277:37"/>
               <l>To <hi>Segor,</hi> where his wife that was vnwittie</l>
               <l>Caſt back her eye to ſee the ſinfull Cittie.</l>
               <l>And for hir miſbeliefe <hi>God</hi> plagued the falt,</l>
               <l>tranſforming her into a Piller of ſalt:</l>
               <l>Here ſhe <hi>Suſannes</hi> ſtory viuely wrought,</l>
               <l>How neare ſhe was to execution brought,</l>
               <l>And yet how God the ſecret did diſcloſe,</l>
               <l>And made the miſchiefe fall vpon her foes</l>
               <l>Here <hi>Ioſephs</hi> ſtorie ſtands with wondrous art,</l>
               <l>And how he left his cloke &amp; not his hart</l>
               <l>to his laſciuious Dame &amp; rather choſe</l>
               <l>the Priſon, then her armes him to encloſe.</l>
               <l>Here cruell <hi>Iephte</hi> with his murdring knife.</l>
               <l>to keepe his vow, bereaues his daughters life.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>(Her trauell done) her lute ſhe then aſſayes,</l>
               <l>and vnto <hi>God</hi> ſhe ſings immortall prayes.</l>
               <l>not folowing thoſe that plyes their thriftles paine</l>
               <l>In wanton vearſe and waſtefull ditties vaine,</l>
               <l>Thereby t'entrapt great men with luring lookes</l>
               <l>But as the greedy fiſher layes his hookes</l>
               <l>Alongſt the coſte to catch ſome mightie fiſh</l>
               <l>More for his gaine, then holeſome for the diſh.</l>
               <l>Of him that byes, euen ſo theſe ſiſters braue,</l>
               <l>Haue louers mo, then honeſt maydens haue.</l>
               <l>But none are brunt with their impudent flame,</l>
               <l>Saue fooles &amp; light lunatickes voyde of ſhame.</l>
               <l>Of vertue only, perfite loue doth growe,</l>
               <l>whoſe firſt be ginning thought it be more ſlow,</l>
               <l>then that of luſt and quicknes not ſo faſt:</l>
               <l>Yet ſure it is, and longer tyme doth laſt.</l>
               <pb n="57" facs="tcp:11277:38"/>
               <l>The ſtraw enkendles ſoone, &amp; ſlakes againe:</l>
               <l>But yron is ſlow, and long will hote remaine.</l>
               <l>Thus was the holie <hi>Iudiths</hi> chaſte renowne</l>
               <l>ſo happly ſpred, through <hi>Izrell</hi> vp and downe,</l>
               <l>that many-a man diſdaind the dameſels fine,</l>
               <l>with Iewels rich and haire in golden twine,</l>
               <l>to ſerue her beutie: yet loues firie dart,</l>
               <l>Could neuer vnfrieſe the froſt of her chaſt hart.</l>
               <l>But as the <hi>Diamant</hi> byds the ha<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>mer ſtrong,</l>
               <l>ſo ſhe reſiſted all her ſuters long</l>
               <l>Vnminded euer for to wed, but rather</l>
               <l>to ſpend her dayes with her beloued father</l>
               <l>till at the laſt her parents with great care,</l>
               <l>ithſtood her will, and for her did prepare.</l>
               <l>
                  <hi>Manaſſes,</hi> one who was of noble race</l>
               <l>Both rich and faire aſwell of ſprite as face:</l>
               <l>Her mariage then was not a ſlight contract</l>
               <l>Of ſecrete billes, but by willing act<note place="margin">Mariage.</note>
               </l>
               <l>'before her frends: The chaunce that once befell</l>
               <l>'to wandring <hi>Dina</hi> may be witneſſe well,</l>
               <l>'that ſecret mariage that to few is kend,</l>
               <l>'doth neuer leade the louers to good end.</l>
               <l>For of our bodies we no power may clame</l>
               <l>'except our parents do confirme the ſame,</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>Then ſee how loue ſo holily begunne,</l>
               <l>Betweene theſe two, ſo holy a race they runne,</l>
               <l>this chaſte young-man &amp; his moſt chaſteſt wife,</l>
               <l>as if their bodies twaine had but one life.</l>
               <l>what th'one did will, the other wild no leſſe,</l>
               <l>As by one mouth, their wils they do expreſſe:</l>
               <pb n="58" facs="tcp:11277:38"/>
               <l>And as a ſtroke giuen on the righter eye</l>
               <l>Offends the left, euen ſo by <hi>Simpathie:</hi>
               </l>
               <l>Her huſ bands dolours made her hart vnglad,</l>
               <l>And <hi>Iudiths</hi> ſorrowes made her huſband ſad.</l>
               <l>
                  <hi>Manaſſes</hi> then, is wife would not controule</l>
               <l>tyraniouſly, but looke how much the ſoule</l>
               <l>Exceeds the corſe, &amp; not the corſe doth grieue,</l>
               <l>But rather to preſerue it and relieue,</l>
               <l>So <hi>Iudith</hi> with <hi>Manaſſes</hi> did accorde,</l>
               <l>In tender loue and honourde him as Lord.</l>
               <l>Their houſe at home ſo holy was too tell</l>
               <l>it ſeemd a church, and not a priuate Cell:</l>
               <l>No ſeruant there, with villaine ieſtes vncouth,</l>
               <l>was ſuffred to corrupt the ſhamefaſt youth.</l>
               <l>No ydle drunkard, nor no ſwearing wight</l>
               <l>Vnpuniſt durſt blaſpheme the lord of might.</l>
               <l>No pleaſant ſkoffer, nor no lying knaue:</l>
               <l>No daylie Dyce, nor no Ruffian braue,</l>
               <l>Had there abode: but all the ſeruants weare</l>
               <l>taught of their Rulers <hi>Gods</hi> eternall feare.</l>
               <l>
                  <hi>Manaſſes,</hi> he who ſaw that in his tyme</l>
               <l>All iuſtice was corrupt with many-a cryme,</l>
               <l>And that the moſt peruers and ignorant,</l>
               <l>For money, or fauour, would none office want</l>
               <l>of high eſtate, refuſde all publike charge:</l>
               <l>Contenting him with eaſe to liue at large.</l>
               <l>from court, and pallace, free from worldly pelf,</l>
               <l>but ſince he thought him borne not for himſelf:</l>
               <l>But alſo that ſome charge he ought to beare</l>
               <l>for confort of his friends &amp; countrey deare:</l>
               <pb n="59" facs="tcp:11277:39"/>
               <l>Yet did he more, not being magiſtrate,</l>
               <l>for publike weale, then men of more eſtate.</l>
               <l>So that his houſe, was euen the dwelling due</l>
               <l>Of Iuſtice, and his mouth a ſentence true.</l>
               <l>Th'afflicted poore he dayly did defend,</l>
               <l>and was the widowes ayde &amp; tutor kend,</l>
               <l>to <hi>Orphelines,</hi> and was the whole ſupport</l>
               <l>And chieſe conforter of the godly ſorte.</l>
               <l>The vaine deſire of <hi>Indian</hi> treaſurs great,</l>
               <l>Made neuer his ſhip to ſaile nor oare to beat.</l>
               <l>The greedy hope of gaine with ventruous da<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ger,</l>
               <l>Made neuer his ſword be drawn to ſerue the ſtra<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
                  <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ger.</l>
               <l>He neuer ſold within the wrangling Barre,</l>
               <l>Deceitfull clatters, cauſing clients Iarre.</l>
               <l>But quietly manurde his litle feilde,</l>
               <l>And took th'encreaſe therof that tyme did yeilde.</l>
               <l>He ſowde, and planted, in his proper grange</l>
               <l>(vpon ſome ſauage ſtock) ſome frutrie ſtrange.</l>
               <l>The ground our common Dame, he vndermines</l>
               <l>On ſtake &amp; ryce, he knits the crooked vines,</l>
               <l>and ſnoddes their bowes, ſo neither hote nor cold</l>
               <l>might him (from labour) in his chamber holde.</l>
               <l>But once as he beheld his harueſt traine,</l>
               <l>with crooked Cickle cutting do wne the graine</l>
               <l>the ſunne a diſtillation on him ſent,</l>
               <l>whereof he dyed, his ſoule to heauen it went.</l>
               <l>He that the nomber of the leaues could caſt,</l>
               <l>that in <hi>Nouember</hi> fals by winter blaſt,</l>
               <l>He that could tell the drops of raine or ſlete,</l>
               <l>that <hi>Hyad Orion</hi> or <hi>Pleiades</hi> wete</l>
               <pb n="60" facs="tcp:11277:39"/>
               <l>ſheds on the ground, that man might only tell,<note place="margin">W<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 chunk">
                        <desc>…</desc>
                     </gap> head<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>.</note>
               </l>
               <l>what teares from <hi>Iudiths</hi> eyes inceſſant fell.</l>
               <l>VVhat treaſur-and golde &amp; what he left her tho,</l>
               <l>In place of pleaſure, cauſed all her woe.</l>
               <l>The ſight of them made her in hart recorde,</l>
               <l>their olde poſſeſſor, and her louing Lord.</l>
               <l>Though ſhe had had aſmuch of gold and good,</l>
               <l>As <hi>Lydia</hi> land, or <hi>Tagus</hi> golden flood:</l>
               <l>(yet loſing him) of treaſure ſhe was bare:</l>
               <l>For whome, all other treaſures cauſ de her care.</l>
               <l>Yet in this ſtate ſhe ſtoutly did ſuſtaine,</l>
               <l>Like patient <hi>Iob</hi> (contempning) all her paine.</l>
               <l>Three times the ſunne returned had his prime,</l>
               <l>'Si<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ce this befell, and yet the ſlyding tyme</l>
               <l>'That wonted is to weare all woes awaye,</l>
               <l>Could neuer for his death her dolour ſtaye:</l>
               <l>But alwayes in ſome black attyre ſhe went</l>
               <l>Right modeſtly &amp; liu'd on litle rent.</l>
               <l>Deuout ſhe was &amp; moſt tymes ſole and ſad</l>
               <l>with dole in hart &amp; mourning veſture clad,</l>
               <l>Outſhedding teares as doth the turtle doue</l>
               <l>on withred ſtalke that waills her abſent loue:</l>
               <l>And widow like all pleaſure doth forſake</l>
               <l>And neuer intends to take a ſecound make.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>Thus <hi>Iudith</hi> chaſt within her houſe abode,</l>
               <l>And ſeldome was ſhe ſene to come abrode,</l>
               <l>Vnleſſe it weare to ſee ſome wofull wife,</l>
               <l>whoſe childe or huſband was bereft of life,</l>
               <l>Or for to viſit ſome in ſickneſſe rage,</l>
               <l>their longſome paine and dollours to aſſwage:</l>
               <pb n="61" facs="tcp:11277:40"/>
               <l>Or for to go to Church as God allowes</l>
               <l>to pray and offer, &amp; to performe her vowes.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>Thus haue I ſhortly told you brother deare,</l>
               <l>the ſtate of her, on whome our citie heare</l>
               <l>haue fixed all their eyes: but I can nought</l>
               <l>tell wher ſhe goes, much les whats in her thought.</l>
               <l>But if we may of paſſed things collect</l>
               <l>the things to come: then may we well aſpect</l>
               <l>Great good of her, for that euen in her face</l>
               <l>Is ſigne of ioy, and great preſage of grace.</l>
               <l>Or ſome good hap. With this and other talke</l>
               <l>they cut the night as they together walke.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>This while the worthie widow with her mayd</l>
               <l>Paſt towards th'enmies camp not vnafrayde:</l>
               <l>For ere ſhe had two hundreth paces paſt,</l>
               <l>The <hi>Syrian</hi> Soldiers in her way were caſt:</l>
               <l>VVho ſpack her thus. O faire excellent wight</l>
               <l>whence? what art thou? what doeſt thou here this night</l>
               <l>In <hi>Syrian</hi> camp? I am (quod ſhe) a gaine</l>
               <l>An <hi>Izralite</hi> whome dollours doth conſtraine,</l>
               <l>To flee this towne, and for my lifes relief,</l>
               <l>ſubmits me to the mercie of your chiefe.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>They tooke her to the Duke, but who hath ſene</l>
               <l>the throngs of folke where proclamations bene</l>
               <l>In ſo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>e great woen, or where ſome mo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ſtrous beaſt</l>
               <l>Is brought &amp; wondred at by moſt &amp; leaſt,</l>
               <l>that ma<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> might Iudge what flocks of ſoldiers came</l>
               <l>From euerie part to ſee that <hi>Hebrew</hi> Dame,</l>
               <l>To ſee that faire, ſo chaſt, ſo amiable:</l>
               <l>the more they gaſde, ſhe ſeemd more admirable.</l>
            </lg>
            <pb facs="tcp:11277:40"/>
            <lg>
               <l>Her wavring haire diſparpling flew apart</l>
               <l>In ſeemely ſhed, the reſt with reckles art</l>
               <l>with many-a curling ring decord her face,</l>
               <l>and gaue her laſhie browes a greater grace.</l>
               <l>Tow bending bowes of <hi>Heben</hi> coupled right,</l>
               <l>two lucent ſtarres that were of heavnly light.</l>
               <l>two geaty ſparks where <hi>Cupid</hi> chaſtly hydes.</l>
               <l>His ſubtill ſhafts that from his quiuer glydes.</l>
               <l>Tweene theſe two ſunnes and front of equall ſiſe,</l>
               <l>A comely figure formally did ryſe</l>
               <l>VVith draught vnleuell to her lip deſcend</l>
               <l>where <hi>Momus</hi> ſelf could nothing diſcomend.</l>
               <l>Her pitted cheekes aperde to be depaint,</l>
               <l>with mixed roſe &amp; lillies ſweete and ſaint:</l>
               <l>Her dulcet mouth with precious breath repleate</l>
               <l>Excelde the <hi>Saben</hi> Queene in ſauour ſweete.</l>
               <l>Her <hi>Corall</hi> lips diſcovred as it were</l>
               <l>two ranks of <hi>Orient</hi> pearle with ſmyling chere.</l>
               <l>Her yvrie neck and breſt of <hi>Alabaſtre,</hi>
               </l>
               <l>Made Heathen men of her, more <hi>Idolaſtre.</hi>
               </l>
               <l>Vpon her hand no wrinkled knot was ſeene,</l>
               <l>But as each nail of mother of pearle had beene.</l>
               <l>In ſhort this <hi>Iudith</hi> was ſo paſſing faire,</l>
               <l>that if the learned <hi>zeuxis</hi> had bene thaire</l>
               <l>And ſeene this Dame, when he with penſile drew,</l>
               <l>the <hi>Croton</hi> Dames, to forme the picture trew</l>
               <l>Of her, for whome both <hi>Grece</hi> and <hi>Aſia</hi> fought:</l>
               <l>this onely patron chief be would haue ſought.<note place="margin">Heſen.</note>
               </l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>No ſooner <hi>Iudith</hi> entred his Pauillion,</l>
               <l>But in her face aroſe the red vermillion</l>
               <pb n="61" facs="tcp:11277:41"/>
               <gap reason="duplicate" extent="1 page">
                  <desc>〈1 page duplicate〉</desc>
               </gap>
               <pb facs="tcp:11277:41"/>
               <gap reason="duplicate" extent="1 page">
                  <desc>〈1 page duplicate〉</desc>
               </gap>
               <pb facs="tcp:11277:42"/>
               <l>with ſhamefaſt feare: but then with la<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>guage ſweet</l>
               <l>The courteous Genrall mildly gan her greet.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>My loue, I am, I am not yet ſo fell,</l>
               <l>As fals reporte doth to you <hi>Hebrews</hi> tell.</l>
               <l>They are my ſonnes &amp; I wilbe their father</l>
               <l>that honours me: and them I loue the rather,</l>
               <l>that worſhips for their <hi>God</hi> th' <hi>Aſſyrian</hi> King:</l>
               <l>They ſhalbe well aſſurde to want nothing.</l>
               <l>And this ſhall <hi>Izak</hi> know if they will render</l>
               <l>Vnto that bonte ous king as their defender.</l>
               <l>For thy (my loue) tell me withouten feare,</l>
               <l>the happie motyf of thy comming heare.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>O Prince (quoth ſhe with an aſſured face)</l>
               <l>Moſt ſtrong and wiſe &amp; moſt in heauens grace,</l>
               <l>that drawes the ſword, with ſteele vpon his breſt</l>
               <l>with helme on head, and Iaunce in yron reſt:</l>
               <l>Since that my feeble <hi>Sex</hi> and tender youth,</l>
               <l>Cannot longtime endure, the cruell drouth,</l>
               <l>the wakrife trauels, frayes, and haſzards great,</l>
               <l>That day and night, our Burgeſſes doth threat:</l>
               <l>Yet neuertheleſſe this is not whole the cauſe</l>
               <l>that from my Citties body me withdrawes</l>
               <l>to this your Camp: but that moſt grudging griefe,</l>
               <l>Which burnes my zealous hart without reliefe:</l>
               <l>Is this (my Lord) I haue a holy feare</l>
               <l>to eate thoſe meates that <hi>God</hi> bids vs forbeares</l>
               <l>But Sir, I ſee that our beſieged towne,</l>
               <l>Is ſo beſet with miſchiefe vp and downe.</l>
               <l>The people wilbe forſt to eate in th'end</l>
               <l>the meats that God expreſly doth defend:</l>
               <pb facs="tcp:11277:42"/>
               <l>Then will the lord with iuſt reue<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ge him wreak</l>
               <l>Vpon all thoſe, that do his ſtatutes break.</l>
               <l>Withouten fight their Citties he will ſack,</l>
               <l>And make one man of thine ten thouſand wrack,</l>
               <l>that flyes his furie, and thy furious face,</l>
               <l>Nowe I of <hi>Bethull</hi> am, and in this place</l>
               <l>Beſeech thy noble grace if ſo thee pleaſe,</l>
               <l>with courteous ayde, to giue my dolours eaſe,</l>
               <l>'Of common ſence he is depriued cleene,</l>
               <l>'that falls with cloſed eye on danger ſeene.</l>
               <l>'And he that may both paine and hurt eſchewe,</l>
               <l>'Is vaine if he his proper death purſewe,</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>Then in this quiet dale if I may byde</l>
               <l>(in ſecret) for to pray ech evning tyde</l>
               <l>to God: I ſhall as he doth me enſpyre,</l>
               <l>Aſſure you when enkendled is his yre,</l>
               <l>Againſt our folke. Then ſhall I take on hand,</l>
               <l>to leade thine Armie through all <hi>Iurie</hi> land,</l>
               <l>And ſtreaming ſtandarts ſet on <hi>Syon</hi> hill,</l>
               <l>where none with weapons dare reſiſt thy will.</l>
               <l>No, not a verie dog in euening dark,</l>
               <l>At noyſe of harnes ſhall againſt thee bark.</l>
               <l>Thy onely name ſhall fray the Armies bold,</l>
               <l>Before thy face the mountaine tops ſhall fold.<note place="margin">R</note>
               </l>
               <l>The floods ſhall drye &amp; from their running ſtay,</l>
               <l>To make thine Hoſte, a new &amp; vncouth way.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>O Iewell of the world (quoth he) ô Dame,</l>
               <l>For gratious ſpech and beutie worthie fame,</l>
               <l>Now welco<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>e here, would God it might you pleaſe</l>
               <l>Longtime with vs to dwell in reſt and caſe,</l>
               <pb facs="tcp:11277:43"/>
               <l>For if your faith and trouth concurrant be,</l>
               <l>to this your talke, which greatly pleaſeth me:</l>
               <l>I will from this time forth with you accord,</l>
               <l>to ſerue your onely <hi>Hebrewes</hi> God &amp; Lord,</l>
               <l>And will my ſeruice whole to you enrowle:</l>
               <l>Not of my Scepter onely, but my ſoule.</l>
               <l>I will your name and honour ay defend</l>
               <l>From <hi>Hebrew</hi> bounds vnto the world his end.</l>
               <l>This ſayd: with ſilence as the moone aroſe,</l>
               <l>The widow her withdrew, and forth ſhe goes</l>
               <l>Vnto a valley cloſe on euerie part,</l>
               <l>where as ſhe waſht her corſe &amp; clenſt her harte:</l>
               <l>And with her weeping eyes the place beraid,</l>
               <l>And to the God of <hi>Izak</hi> thus ſhe praide.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>O Lord withdraw not now thy helping hand</l>
               <l>from thoſe, that at thy mercie onely ſtand.</l>
               <l>O Lord defend them that deſires to ſpend</l>
               <l>their goods and blood, thy cauſe for to defend.</l>
               <l>O Lord grant that the cryes of Children may</l>
               <l>with plaints of oldmen weeping night and day.</l>
               <l>And virgins voyces ſad in ſhroude of ſhame</l>
               <l>And laudes of <hi>Leuits</hi> ſounding forth thy fame.</l>
               <l>Mount to thy throne, and with diſſundring breake</l>
               <l>thy heauie ſleepe. VVherefore doeſt thou awreake</l>
               <l>thy ſelf on <hi>Hermon</hi> with thy burning blaſt?</l>
               <l>or why? doeſt thou on carefull <hi>Carmell</hi> caſt</l>
               <l>Thy dreadfull darts? forgetting all this ſpace,</l>
               <l>theſe <hi>Giants</hi> that thy Scepter would diſplace?</l>
               <l>Ah wretch what ſay I? lord apardon me,</l>
               <l>thy burning zeale (and none hypocriſie)</l>
               <pb facs="tcp:11277:43"/>
               <l>that frets my heauie hart at euerie howre</l>
               <l>Compels my toung this language out to powre.</l>
               <l>O thou, the euerliuing <hi>God,</hi> and Guide</l>
               <l>of all our race, I know thou wilt prouide</l>
               <l>For our reliefe againſt this furious boſte,</l>
               <l>And iuſtly kill the Captaine of this hoſte.</l>
               <l>I know, that thou wilt help my onely hand,</l>
               <l>to be the wrak, of all this heathen band.</l>
            </lg>
            <trailer>FINIS.</trailer>
         </div>
         <div n="5" type="book">
            <argument>
               <head>THE SOMMARIE OF THE V. BOOK.</head>
               <p>¶ <hi>Holophernes</hi> being ſurpriſed with the ſweete language, and excellent beu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tie of the chaſte <hi>Iudith</hi> becommeth altogether negligent of his charge &amp; go<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uernement. Wherein is repreſented the vnhabilitie of the reprobate, who can not withſtand ſuch temptations as the lord ſendeth vpon them But as they become ſlaues to their owne affections, ſo by the ſame they are enforced to fall into perdition. In place of ſome faithfull ſeruant to warne him of his vyces, <hi>Holophernes</hi> conferreth with <hi>Bagos</hi> an <hi>Eunuch,</hi> who feedeth him in his humour, and bringeth <hi>Iudith</hi> to his Tent. And here the <hi>Poet</hi> reprooues all flatterers &amp; bawdes with the vyces of all Courts in Generall. <hi>Iudith</hi> ſeing her chaſtitie in perill, and the time vnmeete to execute her enterpriſe: Subtily drawes the Tyrant to talke of other affaires. He thinking to inſinuate himſelf the more into her fauour, taketh pleaſure to crack of his conqueſts and of his ſpeciall worthineſſe: diſcourſing ſo long till ſuppertyme aproached and she auoided the inconuenience: And here is to be noted that whileſt the tyrants boste of their cruellie againſt the Church. God prouideth for his owne and preſerueth them for that worke, that he hath ordeined by them to be done.</p>
            </argument>
            <head>THE FIFTH BOOKE OF IVDITH.</head>
            <lg>
               <l>IN ſtead of mary-in bone, and blood in vaines,</l>
               <l>Great <hi>Holopherne</hi> doth feed his cruell paines:</l>
               <pb n="67" facs="tcp:11277:44"/>
               <l>He bootleſſe flees, and feeles, but he ne knowes</l>
               <l>the quenched fire that of his aſhes growes.</l>
               <l>For ſo the charming Image of this Dame,</l>
               <l>the onely mark wherat his ſoule did ame,</l>
               <l>Tran ſported him in paſſions of diſpare,</l>
               <l>that of his mightie camp he quits the care,</l>
               <l>And goes no more his matters to diſpatch,</l>
               <l>Nor vewes his corpſgard, nor relieues his watch,</l>
               <l>Nor counſell calls, nor ſent to ſpye the coſte,</l>
               <l>Nor vewes the quarters of his ſpacious hoſte.</l>
               <l>But as the ſheep that haue no hirde nor guide,</l>
               <l>But wandring ſtrayes along the riuers ſide:</l>
               <l>Throu burbling brookes, or throu the foreſts grene</l>
               <l>Throw medows, cloſures, or throu ſhadows ſhene:</l>
               <l>Right ſo the Heathen hoſte, without all bridle,</l>
               <l>Runns inſolent, to vicious actions ydle,</l>
               <l>where none obeyes ech one commanding ſpeaks,</l>
               <l>Eche one at pleaſure from his ba<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ner breaks:</l>
               <l>What do you <hi>Hebrews</hi> now within your wall?</l>
               <l>Now time to fight, or neuer time at all,</l>
               <l>To pay theſe <hi>Pagans,</hi> whoſe confuſed corſe,</l>
               <l>Combats againſt themſelfs with deadly forſe,</l>
               <l>Nay, ſtay a while, of ſuch a great victorie,</l>
               <l>Your onely <hi>God</hi> will haue the onely glorie.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>Before this tyrant was with loue yblent</l>
               <l>To winne the towne, he plyde his whole entent:</l>
               <l>But now both night &amp; day his mynd doth frame</l>
               <l>to conquer, this moſt chaſt vnconqueſt Dame.</l>
               <l>So luſt him led: th'vndaunted <hi>Theban</hi> knight,</l>
               <l>with weightie mace had neuer him affright:</l>
               <pb facs="tcp:11277:44"/>
               <l>But now a womans looke his hart enfeares,</l>
               <l>And in his breſt the cureleſſe wound he beares.</l>
               <l>Ambition erſt, ſo had him ouercumme,</l>
               <l>that made him dayly ryſe by ſound of drumme.</l>
               <l>Now <hi>Cupid</hi> him awaks with whote allarmes,</l>
               <l>That his witholds to do the <hi>Hebrewes</hi> harmes.</l>
               <l>Before he rulde aboue both prince and king,</l>
               <l>now can he not himſelf in order bring.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>Alas (quod he) what life is this I haue</l>
               <l>Becomming captiue to my captiue ſlaue?<note place="margin">Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>plaint.</note>
               </l>
               <l>(vnhappie chance) what life is this I ſay?</l>
               <l>My vertue gone, my forces falls away.</l>
               <l>Nay ſure no life, it is more paine I feele,</l>
               <l>The <hi>Ixion</hi> torne vpon th' <hi>Eternall</hi> wheele:<note place="margin">Pronit. there.</note>
               </l>
               <l>My life is like the theefes that ſtoale the fire</l>
               <l>On whoſe mor tall hart doth alwayes tire.</l>
               <l>A rauenous fowle that gnaues him to the bone,</l>
               <l>Reuiuing ſtill bound to the <hi>Scythian</hi> ſtone,</l>
               <l>what ſerues it me t'haue won wher I haue hau<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ted?</l>
               <l>what ſerues my victor arme for to haue daunted?</l>
               <l>The people ſituate tweene <hi>Hydaſpe</hi> large,</l>
               <l>And port wher <hi>Cydnus</hi> doth in ſea diſcharge?</l>
               <l>Since I am vanquiſht by the feeble ſight,</l>
               <l>Of captiue <hi>Iudith</hi> what auaills my might?</l>
               <l>My targe of ſteele, my Burguinet of Braſſe,</l>
               <l>My guard of warriours ſtout where ſo I paſſe,</l>
               <l>Since her ſweete eye hath ſent the pointed dart</l>
               <l>Throgh men &amp; weapo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>s pearcing throu my hart.</l>
               <l>Whatſerues my courſers, who with ſwiftnes light</l>
               <l>Exceeds the ſwallow ſwifteſt bird of flight:</l>
               <pb n="69" facs="tcp:11277:45"/>
               <l>ſince I on him cannot auoide one ynch,</l>
               <l>the care that night and day my hart doth pinch.</l>
               <l>Then cha<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ge (ô <hi>Hebrews</hi>) cha<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ge your tears in ſong,</l>
               <l>And triumphe ore-my hoſte and army ſtrong.</l>
               <l>I am no more that Duke whoſe name allone,</l>
               <l>hath made great wariours quake both lim &amp; bone</l>
               <l>But I am he, whoſe hart was ſometime braue:</l>
               <l>Now leſſe then nought, the ſlaue but of a ſlaue.</l>
               <l>I come not here your <hi>Izak</hi> to annoy,</l>
               <l>with fire and ſword, your houſes to diſtroy:</l>
               <l>But to require your <hi>Iudith</hi> her to render</l>
               <l>More milde to me. What is my wit ſo ſlender</l>
               <l>(berapt with loue) haue I not here my ioye.</l>
               <l>that onely may relieue me from annoye?</l>
               <l>yet neuertheleſſe I clieue the aire in vaine,</l>
               <l>with plaints and makes myne eyes but fountaines twaine</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>I wretch am like the wretched man indeed:<note place="margin">Tantalus</note>
               </l>
               <l>the more he hath the greater is his need.</l>
               <l>Although he deeply plonge in water cleare,</l>
               <l>To quenche his thriſt: yet is he not the neare,</l>
               <l>for ſo do I reſpect the heavnly grace,</l>
               <l>that largely is beſtowde vpon hir face,</l>
               <l>that with mine eyes I dare not her behold,</l>
               <l>My toung doth ſtay &amp; in the pallet folde.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>Why haue not I a hart of <hi>Chryſtall</hi> cleare,</l>
               <l>
                  <hi>Tranſparant</hi> through to let my paine appeare?</l>
               <l>that there ſhe might of all my torments reed,</l>
               <l>Which loue withholds within my hart in dreed?</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>Now ſince, that <hi>Iudith</hi> to this camp aryvde,</l>
               <l>the light of heavn had thriſe his courſe revyvde,</l>
               <pb n="70" facs="tcp:11277:45"/>
               <l>And darkned thriſe, and gan with ſaffron hewe</l>
               <l>to light the <hi>Ynds,</hi> the fourth day to renewe:</l>
               <l>when thus the Duke who left repaſt and reſt</l>
               <l>Vnto his <hi>Eunuch</hi> this like porpos dreſt.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>O <hi>Bagos</hi> ſonne adoptife not by chaunce,</l>
               <l>whome I haue choſe of nought thee to aduance</l>
               <l>By ſpeciall grace, and made thee (though I boſte)</l>
               <l>firſt of my hart, and ſecond of myne Hoſte:</l>
               <l>Irage, I burne, I dye in deſprate thought,</l>
               <l>Throgh loue by this ſame ſtra<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>gers beutie broght.</l>
               <l>Go ſeeke her then, and ſhortly to her ſaye,</l>
               <l>what ſecrete flame torments me day by day:</l>
               <l>ſhew that I ſhall her to ſuch honours bring,</l>
               <l>As he that beares the Scepter of a King:</l>
               <l>But chiefly ſee thy talke be framed thus,</l>
               <l>that ſhe do come this night and ſuppe with vs.</l>
               <l>Now ſhould it not to me be folly and ſhame,</l>
               <l>to haue within my holde the faireſt dame,</l>
               <l>That ground doth beare, if I dare not aſpire,</l>
               <l>to quench the burning flame of my deſire?</l>
               <l>I ſhould but ſerue my ſoldiers for a Ieaſt,</l>
               <l>And <hi>Iudith</hi> faire wold count me but a beaſt.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>Then <hi>Bagos</hi> well acquaint with ſuch a caſt</l>
               <l>He fed the lamp that brunt but ouerfaſt.</l>
               <l>If priuate men (quoth he) and people poore,</l>
               <l>that goes not ouer the threſhold of their doore,</l>
               <l>But ſpends their dayes in trauell and debate,</l>
               <l>And neuer ſeeks to win a better ſtate:</l>
               <l>Liues not content, if that the <hi>Cyprian</hi> Dame</l>
               <l>Do not ſometime their frozen harts enflame?</l>
               <pb facs="tcp:11277:46"/>
               <l>what ſlaues are thoſe then on whoſe baks ar dreſt</l>
               <l>The burdens of this world? who takes no reſt,</l>
               <l>for Publike weale: but wakes with <hi>Argus</hi> eyes</l>
               <l>For others eaſe that to no care applyes:</l>
               <l>If they among ſo many great vexations,</l>
               <l>May not receiue in loue ſome recreations?</l>
               <l>Purſue your loue my Lord, and make no let,</l>
               <l>to take the fiſh that els is in your net.</l>
               <l>And as ere this you haue me faithfull found,</l>
               <l>In like Ambaſſades when ye them propound</l>
               <l>So ſhall you find me in this loue of new,</l>
               <l>To be as faithfull ſecret treſt and trew.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>Alas how many ſuch are in our tymes</l>
               <l>In princes Courts that high to honour clymes,</l>
               <l>More for their handling ſuch an enterpriſe,</l>
               <l>Then for their being valiant learnde or wiſe?</l>
               <l>So<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>times the Courts of kings were verteous ſkooles</l>
               <l>now find we nought in Court but curious fooles.</l>
               <l>O you whoſe noble harts cannot accord,</l>
               <l>to be the ſclaues to an infamous lord:</l>
               <l>And knowes not how to mixe with perlous art,</l>
               <l>the deadly poyſon with the Amorus dart:</l>
               <l>whoſe natures being free wills no conſtraint,</l>
               <l>Nor will your face with flattring penſile paint,</l>
               <l>for well nor wo, for pittie, nor for hyre,</l>
               <l>Of good my Lords their fauours to acquyre:</l>
               <l>Go not to court if yee will me beleue:</l>
               <l>For in that place where ye think to retreue,</l>
               <l>the honour due for vertue, ye ſhall find</l>
               <l>nought but co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>te<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>pt, which leaues good me<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> behind.</l>
            </lg>
            <pb facs="tcp:11277:46"/>
            <lg>
               <l>Ye worthy Dames, that in your breſts do beare</l>
               <l>Of your Al-ſeing God no ſeruile feare:</l>
               <l>ye that of honour haue a greater care,</l>
               <l>then ſights of Courts I pray you come not thare.</l>
               <l>Let men that in their purſe hath not a myte,</l>
               <l>Cloth them like kings, and play the hypocryte,</l>
               <l>And with a lying tale and feined cheare,</l>
               <l>Courtcozen them whom they wold ſee on beare:</l>
               <l>Let their, the <hi>Pandar</hi> ſell his wife for gaine,</l>
               <l>with ſeruice vyle, his nobleſſe to attaine.</l>
               <l>Let him that ſerues the time, chaunge his entent,</l>
               <l>VVith ſaith vnconſtant ſaile at euerie vent.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>
                  <hi>Ye</hi> ſonnes of craft, beare ye as many faces,</l>
               <l>As <hi>Proteus</hi> taks among the Marine places,</l>
               <l>And force your nature all the beſt ye can</l>
               <l>to counterfait the grace of ſome great man:</l>
               <l>
                  <hi>Camelion</hi> like, who take to him ech hewe</l>
               <l>Of black or white, or yellowe greene or blew,</l>
               <l>that comes him next. So you that finds the façion</l>
               <l>to hurt the poore, with many-a great taxaçion:</l>
               <l>you that do preaſe to haue the princes eare,</l>
               <l>to make your names in Prouinces appeare,</l>
               <l>ye ſubtill <hi>Thurims,</hi> ſell your fumiſh wind,</l>
               <l>to wicked wights whoſe ſences ye do blind.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>Ye fearefull Rocks, ye ymps of <hi>Achelois,</hi>
               </l>
               <l>who wracks the wiſeſt youth with charming vois:</l>
               <l>ye <hi>Circes,</hi> who by your enchantment ſtraunge,</l>
               <l>In ſtones and ſwine, your louers true do chaunge:</l>
               <l>ye <hi>Stimphalids,</hi> who with your youth vptaks,</l>
               <l>ye rauens that from vs our riches raks:</l>
               <pb n="73" facs="tcp:11277:47"/>
               <l>Ye who with riches art, and painted face,</l>
               <l>For <hi>Priams</hi> wife, puts <hi>Caſtors</hi> ſiſter-in place:</l>
               <l>ye <hi>Myrrhas, Canaces,</hi> and <hi>Semirames,</hi>
               </l>
               <l>And if there reſt yet mo defamed dames.</l>
               <l>Come all to Court, and there ye ſhall reſaue</l>
               <l>A thouſand gaines vnmeete for you to haue.</l>
               <l>There ſhall you ſell the gifts of great prouinces,</l>
               <l>there ſhall you ſell the grace of graceles princes.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>Stay heare my muſe, it thee behoues to haue</l>
               <l>Great conſtancie and many-a <hi>Hercles</hi> braue</l>
               <l>to purge this age, of vyces more notable,</l>
               <l>then was the ſtals of foule <hi>Aegeans</hi> ſtable.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>Returne to <hi>Iudith,</hi> who to bring to paſſe,</l>
               <l>Her high atempt, before her ſets her glaſſe</l>
               <l>And ginnes to deck her hair like burniſht gold,</l>
               <l>whoſe beutie had no pere for to behold.</l>
               <l>Then went ſhe to his tent where ſhe eſpide,</l>
               <l>the gorgious tappeſtries on euerie ſide,</l>
               <l>Of <hi>Perſian</hi> Kings, of <hi>Meds,</hi> and <hi>Syrian</hi> ſtories,</l>
               <l>How <hi>Ninꝰ</hi> firſt (prict forth with great vainglories)</l>
               <l>Subdewde the Eaſt Then next in order came</l>
               <l>(diſguiſde in kinde) his wife Quene <hi>Semirame:</hi>
               </l>
               <l>who tooke the Scepter and with tourrets hye</l>
               <l>great <hi>Babylon</hi> erected to the ſkye.</l>
               <l>Lo, how a Prince with fingers white and fine</l>
               <l>In womans weede the tender twiſt doth twine,</l>
               <l>who bare a Rock in ſted of Royall mace,<note place="margin">Sardana<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>palus.</note>
               </l>
               <l>And for a man with woman changeth grace</l>
               <l>In geſturs all, hee friſles and he fards,</l>
               <l>He oynts, he bathes, his viſage he regards</l>
               <pb n="74" facs="tcp:11277:47"/>
               <l>In <hi>Chriſtall</hi> glaſſe, which for his ſword he wore,</l>
               <l>And loſt his crowne without all combat more.</l>
               <l>Amongſt his vertugals for ayde he drew</l>
               <l>from his Leutenant who did him purſew,</l>
               <l>And wan his Scepter. Yet with feeble yre,</l>
               <l>He brunt himſelf, and ended is empyre.</l>
               <l>Behold a Bitch then feeds a ſucking childe,</l>
               <l>Amongſt the prickiong thornes and brambles wild</l>
               <l>who grew ſo great &amp; was of ſuch a fame,<note place="margin">Cyrue.</note>
               </l>
               <l>that bond, and free, his waged men became,</l>
               <l>And afterward ſubuerted to his lawe,</l>
               <l>the <hi>Median</hi> ſcepter vnder <hi>Perſians</hi> awe.</l>
               <l>But what is he that ſo deformed goze</l>
               <l>Before the camp and want his eares and noze?</l>
               <l>that was that ſeruant true, who by that ſlight,<note place="margin">Zopyrut.</note>
               </l>
               <l>Brought <hi>Babylon</hi> againe in <hi>Darius</hi> might.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>While <hi>Iudith</hi> fed her eyes with figurs vaine,</l>
               <l>Her hart replete with paſſions and with paine:</l>
               <l>the <hi>Genrall</hi> came, and with a viſage gent,</l>
               <l>Saluted her, and by the hand her hent,</l>
               <l>And cauſed her ſit downe vpon a chare,</l>
               <l>the more at eaſe to vew her beuties rare.</l>
               <l>Then when he ſaw himſelf ſo neare his pleaſure,</l>
               <l>He brunt in hart &amp; ſcarſe could byde the leaſure,</l>
               <l>Till <hi>Venus</hi> with her garland ſhewde in ſight</l>
               <l>On his <hi>Horizon</hi> to renue the night.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>This widow finding then the tyme vnmete,</l>
               <l>Gods iuſt determination to complete</l>
               <l>Made much delay, and fand full many-a ſkuſe,</l>
               <l>with ſundrie talke this tyrant to abuſe:</l>
               <pb facs="tcp:11277:48"/>
               <l>And ſayd my Lord, I pray you ſhewe to me,</l>
               <l>what furie iuſt hath movde your maieſtie,</l>
               <l>what haue our people done (pleaſe it your grace)</l>
               <l>By whome or when that <hi>Izaks</hi> holy race,</l>
               <l>Might ſo prouoke a Prince to wrackfull warre</l>
               <l>In toungs, and lawes, ſo ſeprate from vs farre?</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>Then ſayd the Duke, vncourteous ſhould I be</l>
               <l>If I denye (ô faire) to anſwer thee.</l>
               <l>Now as the heavne two Sunnes cannot containe,</l>
               <l>So in this earth two kings cannot remaine</l>
               <l>Of equall ſtate. So doth ambition craue,</l>
               <l>One king will not another equall haue.</l>
               <l>My Prince is witneſſe who at warrs did fall,</l>
               <l>with king <hi>Arphaxat</hi> cauſe he raiſde his wall</l>
               <l>Of <hi>Ecbatane</hi> ſo high that it did ſhame</l>
               <l>to <hi>Niniuè,</hi> and <hi>Babell</hi> feard the ſame:</l>
               <l>For which, he vndertooke to ſpoyle his throne,</l>
               <l>And race his Scepter to the loweſt ſtone:</l>
               <l>with ſpite, his buildings braue, he caſt adowne.</l>
               <l>
                  <hi>Arphaxat</hi> then, a man of great renowne,</l>
               <l>And worthie of his Scepter and his ſtate,</l>
               <l>thought better in the field to make debate,</l>
               <l>Then beare a ſcorne, his <hi>Meds</hi> to battell drew.</l>
               <l>Thus tweene them two did cruell warre enſewe.</l>
               <l>
                  <hi>Arphaxat</hi> armed all the yles of <hi>Greece,</hi>
               </l>
               <l>where <hi>Iaſon</hi> was, but ſought no golden fleece,</l>
               <l>But golden lingots with aboundant gaine,</l>
               <l>wher <hi>Phaſis</hi> ſtreame bedewes the pleaſant plaine.</l>
               <l>The <hi>Harmaſtans,</hi> and <hi>Albans,</hi> ſtrong, and wiſe,</l>
               <l>that ſowes but once, and haue their harueſt thriſe.</l>
               <pb facs="tcp:11277:48"/>
               <l>The men that neare to <hi>Oxus</hi> banks a bydes,</l>
               <l>And thoſe that <hi>Antitaurus</hi> horns deuydes.</l>
               <l>And thoſe that mans the mount vpon whoſe breſt</l>
               <l>the ſhipt that ſcapt the genrall flood did reſt:</l>
               <l>And thoſe that are (not hyd) within the Reame,</l>
               <l>wher proude <hi>Iaxartes</hi> flowes with furious ſtreame.</l>
               <l>In ſhort: the <hi>Meds</hi> brought men to ayde their plea</l>
               <l>From <hi>Pontus</hi> farre beyond the <hi>Caſpian</hi> ſea:</l>
               <l>And of this Hoſte <hi>Arphaxat</hi> was commander</l>
               <l>with hope and hart more high then <hi>Alexander.</hi>
               </l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>My prince deſirons then to winne or dye,</l>
               <l>Left nought vndone that furthred to ſupplye:</l>
               <l>His troubled ſtate. he armed <hi>Syttacene,</hi>
               </l>
               <l>And waged Archers out of <hi>Osrohene:</hi>
               </l>
               <l>ye lords of lands that yelds the hundreth corne,</l>
               <l>Leaue <hi>Euphrates</hi> &amp; bounds where ye were borne:</l>
               <l>ye <hi>Carmans</hi> bolde that all on fiſh do feede,</l>
               <l>And of their pelts do make your warlike weede:</l>
               <l>Leaue <hi>Hytan</hi> bounds, go ſeeke the golden ſands,</l>
               <l>ye <hi>Parths,</hi> ye <hi>Coſſes, Arabs,</hi> and ye lands,</l>
               <l>That of your <hi>Magi</hi> Prophets thinks ye know,</l>
               <l>their ſpells deuine, your ſelf for pikmen ſhow,</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>O <hi>Calde,</hi> chaunge thine <hi>Aſtrolab</hi> and ſquare</l>
               <l>To ſpeare and ſhield: for, we no wight will ſpare</l>
               <l>Of able age, of high or lowe degrie,</l>
               <l>that trails the pik or launce layes on his thie.</l>
               <l>Let women, Children, and the burghers olde</l>
               <l>At home alone, let them their houſes holde.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>VVe ſomond eke the <hi>Perſians</hi> and <hi>Phoenicians,</hi>
               </l>
               <l>the ſoft <hi>Aegyptians, Hebrewes,</hi> and <hi>Cilicians:</hi>
               </l>
               <pb facs="tcp:11277:49"/>
               <l>
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap> come in haſt. &amp; ioyne their force to ours:</l>
               <l>But they diſdainfully deteind their powrs:</l>
               <l>And with their wicked hands and words vnſage,</l>
               <l>They did our ſacred meſſengers outrage.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>My maiſter for a time, put vp this wrong,</l>
               <l>Attending tyme, to quite theſe enmies ſtrong,</l>
               <l>with purpoſe more at leaſure to prouyde,</l>
               <l>t'abate this ſacrilegious peoples pride.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>Two greater kings were neuer ſeene beforne,</l>
               <l>then camped was in <hi>Ragau</hi> field at morne,<note place="margin">Battell.</note>
               </l>
               <l>with hautie harts enarmed all in yre:</l>
               <l>Ech ſoldier ſet an other ſo on fire,</l>
               <l>that ſcarſly they could keep them in their bound</l>
               <l>till pype or <hi>Cymball</hi> or the trumpets ſound,</l>
               <l>Denounce the choke: but with ther furious faces,</l>
               <l>they thret their foes afarre with fell menaces,</l>
               <l>And ſtrokes at hand, two thouſand Lads forlorne,</l>
               <l>(to blunt the ſword) were downe in battell borne.</l>
               <l>Vpon their flanks flew feruently the ſtones,</l>
               <l>that bet their bucklers to their bruſed bones,</l>
               <l>The ſquadrons then, ſteps ſternly to the ſtrokes,</l>
               <l>with harts in humain all the battell yokes,</l>
               <l>And are ſupplyde with many mightie bands,</l>
               <l>Some counters them, and ſternly them withſtands,</l>
               <l>with foote to foote ech other ouer plyes,</l>
               <l>Both <hi>Meds</hi> and <hi>Caldes</hi> claſp with gaſtly cryes,</l>
               <l>Like <hi>Nilus</hi> ſtreame that fro<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> the rocks doth ro<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ble,</l>
               <l>Or <hi>Encelade</hi> when he in tombe doth tomble.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>Here ſome lyes headles: ſome that cannot ſtand,</l>
               <l>trails on his wombe &amp; wants both foote &amp; hand,</l>
               <pb facs="tcp:11277:49"/>
               <l>cut off with ſtroks, ſome perſt throu plate &amp; mail<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>,</l>
               <l>Some ſhoulder ſlaſht, ſome panched in th'entrails.</l>
               <l>Some brains outbet, ſome in the guts were gorde,</l>
               <l>Some dying vomit blood, &amp; ſome were ſmorde.</l>
               <l>Some neither quicke nor dead do yet attend,</l>
               <l>what place it pleaſeth god their ſoules to ſend:</l>
               <l>So loth the litle life that doth abyde,</l>
               <l>Is from the dying body to deuyde.</l>
               <l>The ground that erſt was yellow, grene, &amp; blew</l>
               <l>Is ouercled with blood in purpure hew.</l>
               <l>While this man giues ſome one his deadly baine,</l>
               <l>He of another gets the like againe.</l>
               <l>The rage encreaſing growes with yrefull flame,</l>
               <l>the field is ſpred with bodies dead and lame.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>Like as ye ſee the wallowing ſea to ſtriue,</l>
               <l>Flood after floode, and waue with waue to driue,<note place="margin">Compari<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon.</note>
               </l>
               <l>Then waues with waues the floods with floods do chace</l>
               <l>And eft returnes vnto their former place:</l>
               <l>Or like the crops of corne in mids of May,</l>
               <l>(blowne with the weſtren wind) aſide doth ſway:</l>
               <l>Both to and fro, as force doth them conſtraine,</l>
               <l>And yet their tops redreſſeth vp againe:</l>
               <l>So whiles the <hi>Syrians,</hi> are by <hi>Meds</hi> diſplaced,</l>
               <l>And whiles the <hi>Meds,</hi> by <hi>Syrians</hi> are rechaced.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>Then like two raging floods that down doe fall</l>
               <l>From two contrarie mutine mountaines tall:</l>
               <l>Downe bearing bridge &amp; bank, and all deſtroyes,</l>
               <l>And ſtriues which one may do the moſt annoyes:</l>
               <l>So theſe two kings in force and courage ſtout,</l>
               <l>Exceld the reſt with ſlaughter them about,</l>
               <pb facs="tcp:11277:50"/>
               <l>VVherſo they preaſt, they left on either ſide,</l>
               <l>Behind them two long opned wayes and wide:</l>
               <l>for all their bucklers <hi>Morions</hi> and <hi>Quiraces,</hi>
               </l>
               <l>were of no proofe againſt their peiſant maces.</l>
               <l>Yet (for the time) the <hi>Meds</hi> ſo fearcely fought,</l>
               <l>that they th' <hi>Aſſyrian</hi> bands in terrour brought,</l>
               <l>And pauld their ſoldiers harts &amp; brak their might:</l>
               <l>Who (ouercome) tooke them to ſhamefull flight.</l>
               <l>The <hi>Meds</hi> purſewde and wounded in that chace,</l>
               <l>ten thouſand men, but none vpon the face.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>In ſhort, this day our Scepter had depriued,</l>
               <l>Had I not like the thunder dint arriued</l>
               <l>In battels brunt. Their male &amp; their vantbras,</l>
               <l>Their helme and ſhield, before my Coutelas,</l>
               <l>Were fraile as glas: and neuer a ſtroke Hent,</l>
               <l>But deadly was, and them more terrour ſent,</l>
               <l>then all our camp. The ſoldier then in feare</l>
               <l>with tre<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>bling hand could ſcarſly weild his ſpeare.</l>
               <l>the palhewd knight with hart in breſt that quakes</l>
               <l>His thyes in ſadle, and feete in ſtirrops ſhakes</l>
               <l>for dread of me. There ſome with trenchant glaiue</l>
               <l>From hight of head, to midle downe I claiue.</l>
               <l>And ſome ſo farre I foyned through the Iack:</l>
               <l>the blade aperde a foote behind his back:</l>
               <l>So that the <hi>Meds</hi> afrayd at ſuch a thing,</l>
               <l>In heat of fight they fled &amp; left their king,</l>
               <l>who ſeing himſelf betrayd: his clothes he rent,</l>
               <l>And bloodie towards <hi>Ragau</hi> towne he went,</l>
               <l>where we him met, yet <hi>(Braue)</hi> did him defend,</l>
               <l>And ſought amongſt his foes a famous end.</l>
               <pb facs="tcp:11277:50"/>
               <l>As doth the <hi>Tyger</hi> wilde who ſees her den</l>
               <l>Beſet about with hunters dogs and men,</l>
               <l>that turns her feare to furious raging rife</l>
               <l>&amp; will not vnre uenged loſe her life:</l>
               <l>So he them thunderbet wherſo he went,</l>
               <l>that neuer-a ſtroke in vaine his righthand ſpent:</l>
               <l>But er with murdring blade they could him quell,</l>
               <l>Full many-a bold precurſor-he ſent to hell.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>At laſt <hi>Arphaxat</hi> gan of ſlaughter tyre</l>
               <l>And (wounded ſore) left both his life and yre:</l>
               <l>And fell, as doth ſome huge high planted oak,</l>
               <l>that long hath byde the winds, &amp; many-a ſtroak</l>
               <l>Of many an axe: yet ſtoutly doth ſuſtaine</l>
               <l>their trauels long and fruſtrats all their paine,</l>
               <l>The roote doth ſigh, the dale doth roring ſound,</l>
               <l>And to the heavne the noyſe doth high rebound,</l>
               <l>his head now here, now there, ſeemes to encline,</l>
               <l>&amp; threats them here &amp; there with great ruine:</l>
               <l>Yet ſtands vpright aboue the higheſt okes,</l>
               <l>till, vanquiſht with a thouſand thouſand ſtrokes,</l>
               <l>He falls at laſt &amp; brings with him to ground</l>
               <l>Both trees &amp; cattell to the plaine profound.</l>
               <l>So with <hi>Arphaxat</hi> fell the <hi>Meds</hi> empyre:</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>My king, the king of kings then in his yre</l>
               <l>Raſd <hi>Ecbatan,</hi> and now growes weed &amp; herbe,</l>
               <l>where ſometime ſtood his palaces ſuperbe.</l>
               <l>So that where erſt the lute and lowde <hi>Haubois,</hi>
               </l>
               <l>were wont to ſound with ſweete concordant nois,</l>
               <l>Now ſhriking owles and other monſters moe</l>
               <l>In funerall ſound fulfils the place with woe.</l>
            </lg>
            <pb facs="tcp:11277:51"/>
            <lg>
               <l>My potent Prince when all this warre was ceaſt</l>
               <l>Conſumed moneths foure in Royall feaſt,</l>
               <l>In <hi>Niniuè</hi> the great, which banket done,</l>
               <l>He me commanded to aſſemble ſone,</l>
               <l>His Royall hoſte, to puniſh all and ſome,</l>
               <l>that to his former ayd diſdaind to come:</l>
               <l>And that I ſhortly ſhould with ſword and flame</l>
               <l>Reuenge his honour, but alas <hi>Madame</hi>
               </l>
               <l>Full farre am I from that I would purſewe,</l>
               <l>for comming here thy nation to ſubde we:</l>
               <l>I va<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>quiſht am by thee, ſo that deaths might,</l>
               <l>ſhall ſhortly cloſe mine eyes with endles night:</l>
               <l>If you not (with a louing kiſſe) to me</l>
               <l>Reſtore my life. O worthie Prince, quoth ſhe,</l>
               <l>Continue your diſcours, and to me tell,</l>
               <l>what great aduentures to your Hoſte befell.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>Then he retooke his tale he left <gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> late,</l>
               <l>And made a long diſcours of all his ſtate:</l>
               <l>Part true, part fals, as do ſome warriours braue,</l>
               <l>who ſpeaking of their Acts will lye and raue.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>My camp aſſembled, then gan I t'enflame</l>
               <l>My ſoldiers harts thus for to win them fame.<note place="margin">Oration.</note>
               </l>
               <l>Companions now, if euer ye pretend</l>
               <l>To winne renoume that neuer ſhall hane end.</l>
               <l>Go forwards now, plague theſe inhumain lands,</l>
               <l>that on our ſacred legats layd their hands.</l>
               <l>Reuenge, reuenge, ye men your moſt hie prince,</l>
               <l>that euer Scepter bare in rich prouince,</l>
               <l>that euer came adowne with mightie arme.</l>
               <l>From circled ſtarres. <hi>Alarm'</hi> ſoldats alarme:</l>
               <pb n="82" facs="tcp:11277:51"/>
               <l>Take blades in hand, &amp; brands of burning yre,</l>
               <l>to waſt the weſtren world with ſword and fyre,</l>
               <l>with bloody ſeas bedewe ech mount and wood,</l>
               <l>And make your horſes fearce to ſwimme in blood.</l>
               <l>Receiue the Scepter great &amp; crowne of might,</l>
               <l>of all this world which is to you behight.</l>
               <l>Receiue this laude that for your conqueſt braue,</l>
               <l>ſhall draw your fames from the forgetfull graue:</l>
               <l>Receiue ye valiant men the noble ſpoyle</l>
               <l>of many-a land that ye ſhall put to foyle.</l>
               <l>Let men behold that ſees you day by daye,</l>
               <l>How ye are cloyde with honour ſpoyle &amp; pray,</l>
               <l>thus ended I. And as my words were ſpent</l>
               <l>They bet their bucklers, ſhowing them content</l>
               <l>with courage bolde, to fight with me and byde.</l>
               <l>Then ſixſcore thouſand men I had to guide,</l>
               <l>Or moe: and ſo from <hi>Niniuè</hi> we paſt</l>
               <l>And marched vnto <hi>(Bectile)</hi> at laſt,</l>
               <l>I through <hi>Edeſſi, Amidi,</hi> and <hi>Carran</hi> came,</l>
               <l>where ſomtime dwelt you father <hi>Abrahame:</hi>
               </l>
               <l>I wan the mount whoſe thwarting hornes deuyds</l>
               <l>All <hi>Aſie,</hi> and ſerues for bounds on ſundrie ſyds,</l>
               <l>to many great Empyrs: I ſlewe, I brent</l>
               <l>All in my way. My fellon ſoldiers went</l>
               <l>Like maowers with their ſithes in ſowple hands,</l>
               <l>who leaues not after them a ſtraw that ſtands:</l>
               <l>But ample ſwathes of graſſe on ground doth caſt,</l>
               <l>&amp; ſhowes what way their ſharped ſiths haue paſt.</l>
               <l>All <hi>Lydia</hi> knowes, that nought now growes in it</l>
               <l>but weeds. And <hi>Phuli</hi>-and <hi>Tharſis</hi> feeles it yit.</l>
               <pb n="83" facs="tcp:11277:52"/>
               <l>I was welneare the ſtraits that cloſeth all,</l>
               <l>
                  <hi>Phoenice</hi> and th'<hi>Iſhique</hi> Rouers, like a wall,</l>
               <l>when <hi>Roſea, Solea, Mops, Anchiali</hi> and <hi>Iſcia,</hi>
               </l>
               <l>And ſweete <hi>Egei:</hi> and (ſhort) the whole <hi>Cilicia,</hi>
               </l>
               <l>This paſſage took before and lay in wait,</l>
               <l>to ſtay my Armie for to paſſe this ſtrait.</l>
               <l>If I the harmes and haſſards all ſhould tell</l>
               <l>of all th'affairs and bloody frayes that fell</l>
               <l>and ſuccours ſent: the day would ſlide away</l>
               <l>Before my tale. For that <hi>Cilicia</hi> I ſay,</l>
               <l>through great auantage of their grou<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>d ſo narrow</l>
               <l>Defended them from both the ſpeare &amp; arrow:</l>
               <l>So that my Hoſte that gaue before the chace,</l>
               <l>to puiſſant kings: now fled with great diſgrace.</l>
               <l>Then foming in diſpite, diſpaire, and yre,<note place="margin">Craking.</note>
               </l>
               <l>I caſt my ſelf where ſhot flew like the fyre,</l>
               <l>and though they hurt me in a hundreth parts,</l>
               <l>And though my Buckler bare a wood of darts:</l>
               <l>yet left not I, but with audacious face:</l>
               <l>I brauely fought, &amp; made them all giue place.</l>
               <l>My Armie followde where my arme made way</l>
               <l>with trenching blade, on bodies dead that lay.</l>
               <l>The greateſt coward that my captains led,</l>
               <l>Purſewd &amp; ſlew, the moſt of them that fled.</l>
               <l>The <hi>Cidnus</hi> ſtreame (who for his ſiluer flood</l>
               <l>Eſteemd a king ran now with humaine blood.</l>
               <l>The <hi>Pyram</hi> fearce, in ſeas diſcharged than</l>
               <l>Full many-a helm, &amp; ſword and worthie man.</l>
               <l>In ſhort as your owne riuer ſeemes to reſt</l>
               <l>with ſwelling tyds and frothy floods repreſt</l>
               <pb n="84" facs="tcp:11277:52"/>
               <l>within his bank: yet furiouſly him wreaks</l>
               <l>with weightie force &amp; banks and bridges breaks,</l>
               <l>&amp; ſtroyes the plaines, and maks for many-a day</l>
               <l>More wrak, then if his channels open lay:</l>
               <l>In ſemble ſort their bands I did enchace,</l>
               <l>that kept the entrance of that craggie place.</l>
               <l>I brunt, I ſlew, caſt downe, all that I fand,</l>
               <l>And <hi>Aſia</hi> ſpoild, I entred th'eaſter land.</l>
               <l>I wan <hi>Celei,</hi> and raged pittie les</l>
               <l>Vpon the frutefull ſhore of <hi>Euphrates.</hi>
               </l>
               <l>I betthe deſart <hi>Rapſe,</hi> &amp; <hi>Eagria</hi> land,</l>
               <l>who knowes the vertue of my conquering hand.</l>
               <l>From thence to ſeaward ſewing mine entent</l>
               <l>I waſted <hi>Madian.</hi> North ward then I went</l>
               <l>to <hi>Liban</hi> ward, <hi>Damaſcus</hi> ouerrinning,</l>
               <l>with other towns, <hi>Abilia</hi> &amp; <hi>Hippas</hi> winning.</l>
               <l>Fro<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> thence, with curious mind my ſtanderds ſtyes,</l>
               <l>the hill, where ſunne is ſene to ſet and ryes.</l>
               <l>And ſo from thence I forward led mine hoſte,</l>
               <l>To th'<hi>Occident</hi> on the <hi>Phoenician</hi> coſte.</l>
               <l>Then <hi>Sidon, Bible, Beryte, Tyre,</hi> &amp; <hi>Gaze,</hi>
               </l>
               <l>with <hi>Aſcalon,</hi> and <hi>Aſſot,</hi> in a maze,</l>
               <l>For feare, ſent humblie to my ſacred ſeat,</l>
               <l>wiſe meſſengers, my fauour to entreat.</l>
               <l>We come not here, my lord ſayd they, with armes</l>
               <l>for to reſiſt the chok of thy <hi>Gensd'armes:</hi>
               </l>
               <l>But Prince, we come, of thee for to reſaue,</l>
               <l>Both life and death, &amp; what lawe we ſhall haue.</l>
               <l>Our townes ar thine, our citties &amp; our hills,</l>
               <l>Our fields, our flocks, our wealth is at your wills.</l>
               <pb n="85" facs="tcp:11277:53"/>
               <l>Our ſeruice, and our treaſures, great and ſmall,</l>
               <l>Our ſelfs, our wyues, and our faire children all:</l>
               <l>Now onlie reſts to thee, if ſo thee pleaſe</l>
               <l>to take vs thus. O <hi>God</hi> what greater eaſe:</l>
               <l>O god what greater good may vs befall,</l>
               <l>Then vnto ſuch a chiefe for to be thrall?</l>
               <l>who weilds the valiant lance &amp; ballance right,</l>
               <l>with vertue like the Gods of greateſt might</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>So weare to me, as gracious to beholde</l>
               <l>Their townes &amp; Citties both, for yong and olde</l>
               <l>with crownes, and preſents of the <hi>Flora</hi> ſweete,</l>
               <l>&amp; coſtly odours, humbly did me greete.</l>
               <l>At ſounds of hornes &amp; pypes they dauncing went</l>
               <l>with goods and bodyes me for to preſent.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>Then I abuſing not the law of armes</l>
               <l>Entreated them, and did to them no harmes,</l>
               <l>nor to their lands. But firſt their forts I mand,</l>
               <l>with men of mine, and theirs tooke in my band.</l>
               <l>For where that I, my people fartheſt drew,</l>
               <l>My camp in bands, from bands, to armies grew,</l>
               <l>As doth the <hi>Danow</hi> which begins to flow</l>
               <l>By <hi>Raurak</hi> fields with ſnakiſh crangling ſlow,</l>
               <l>then ſwels his floods with ſixtie riuers large,</l>
               <l>that in the <hi>Golfe Euxinꝰ</hi> doth diſcharge:</l>
               <l>I wende <hi>Malame</hi> that <hi>Izrell</hi> like the reſt,</l>
               <l>would yeald to me, that I ſhould not be ſtreſt</l>
               <l>Againſt their breſt to moue my murdring ſpeare,</l>
               <l>But as I came the <hi>Soythique</hi> rampier neare</l>
               <l>(the Tombe of her whoſe milk had ſuch a hap</l>
               <l>To feede the twice borne <hi>Denis</hi> in her lap)</l>
               <pb n="86" facs="tcp:11277:53"/>
               <l>I hard their wilfull rage firſt in that place,</l>
               <l>which doubtles will diſtroye all <hi>Abrahms</hi> race.</l>
            </lg>
            <trailer>FINIS.</trailer>
         </div>
         <div n="6" type="book">
            <argument>
               <head>THE SOMMARIE OF THE VI. BOOK.</head>
               <p>¶ <hi>Iudith</hi> hauing eſcaped the perill of her chaſtitie is brought to a ſumpteous banquet prepared by <hi>Holophernes</hi> for the intertainement of her, and far<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der prouocation of his filthie lust: In which the abhominable vice of gluttonie as by the <hi>Poet</hi> viuely deſcriued, and sharply reprehended And whereas the <hi>Tyrant</hi> thought by ſuch exceſſe to ouercome the chaſte widow: himſelfe is ſo ouercome with wine, that vpon a verie ſimple delay he lets her goe till he was in his bed. And here is noted that the ſnares that the wicked layes for others, they fall in them their ſelfs. W<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>les the <hi>Tyrant</hi> contemplated his luſt, <hi>Iu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dith</hi> in trouble called vpon her God, who made way for her worke through the Tyrants owne wickedneſſe: who heaping ſin vpon ſinne, approched at laſt to the end of his tragaedie, and mounting vpon the ſkaffold of the yre of God<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> falles a ſleepe in his ſinfull bed, and is by <hi>Iudith</hi> beheaded in his beaſtly dron<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>kennes. True it is that in this execution she felt her great infirmitie, but like<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wiſe she found that God was able to ſtrengthen the moſt feeble for the exe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cution of his luſtice. And as before she was preſerued in the midſt of her e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nemies: ſo the Lord to make a miraculous end of his worke, brings her ſafe home to her people. The <hi>Bethulians</hi> giues thankes to <hi>God.</hi> The <hi>Ammo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nit</hi> rauished with this miracle, embraced the true religion. The head of <hi>Ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lophernes</hi> (that <hi>Iudiths</hi> ſeruant brought) being ſet vp for a terrible ſpecta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>kle to the Heathen, encouraged the Cittezens to giue aſſault vpon the camp. <hi>Bagos,</hi> who had bent an inſtrument of the tyrants wickednes, is the firſt that finds his maiſters headles Carkas, and putts the camp in ſuch affray, that they fled all before <hi>Iſraell,</hi> in ſuch ſort that ſcarſe one was left to bring newes to <hi>Niniuè,</hi> of the fortune of the battell. And that was Gods Iuſtice, that thoſe that had followed this tyrant in his wickedneſſe, should be companions of his death. <hi>Iudith</hi> laſt of all celebrates the deliuerance of God with a ſong, to the honour and glorie of his almightie name.</p>
            </argument>
            <head>THE SIXTH BOOKE OF IVDITH.</head>
            <lg>
               <l>BEfore the Pagan had his purpoſe ended,</l>
               <l>the night obſcure fro<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> mo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>tains high deſce<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ded</l>
               <pb facs="tcp:11277:54"/>
               <l>And ſewers ſet the bord with coſtly meate,</l>
               <l>Of paſſing price, ſo delicate to eate,</l>
               <l>that <hi>Holopherne</hi> vnto his ioyous feaſt</l>
               <l>Aperd t' haue cald the kings of weſt and Eaſt.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>O glutton throtes, ô greedy guts profound,</l>
               <l>the choſen meats within the world his bound</l>
               <l>By th' <hi>Abderois</hi> inuented may not ſtau<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>che,<note place="margin">Exclama<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion.</note>
               </l>
               <l>Nor ſatiſfie your foule deuouring pau<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>che:</l>
               <l>But muſt in <hi>Moluke</hi> ſeeke the ſpices fine.</l>
               <l>
                  <hi>Canarie</hi> ſuger and the <hi>Candy</hi> wine.</l>
               <l>Your appetits (O gluttons) to co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>tent,</l>
               <l>the ſacred breſt of <hi>Thetis</hi> blew is rent:</l>
               <l>the Aire muſt be diſpeopled for your mawes</l>
               <l>the <hi>Phoenix</hi> ſole can ſkarſe eſcape your iawes.<note place="margin">Gluttonie</note>
               </l>
               <l>'O plague, O poyſon to the warriour ſtate,</l>
               <l>'thou maks the noble harts effeminate,</l>
               <l>'while <hi>Rome</hi> was rulde by <hi>Curioes</hi> and <hi>Fabrices,</hi>
               </l>
               <l>'who fed on roots and ſought not for delices,</l>
               <l>'and when the onely <hi>Creſſon</hi> was the foode</l>
               <l>'moſt delicate to <hi>Perſia,</hi> then they ſtoode</l>
               <l>'in happy ſtate, renowinde in peace and warre,</l>
               <l>'&amp; throu the world, their triumphes ſpred afarres</l>
               <l>'But when they after in th <hi>Aſſyrian</hi> hall,</l>
               <l>'Had learnd the leſſons of <hi>Sardanapall.</hi>
               </l>
               <l>'and when the other, giuen to belly cheare,</l>
               <l>'By <hi>Galbaes, Veroes, Vitells</hi> gouernd weare,</l>
               <l>'who gloried more to fill a coſtly plate,</l>
               <l>'then kill a <hi>Pyrrhus</hi> or a <hi>Mythridate:</hi>
               </l>
               <l>'then both of them were ſeene for to be ſacked</l>
               <l>'by natio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>s poore, who<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> they before had wracked.</l>
            </lg>
            <pb facs="tcp:11277:54"/>
            <lg>
               <l>'Of litle nature liues ſuperfluous meate,</l>
               <l>'But duls the ſprite, and doth the ſtomack freate,</l>
               <l>When they were ſet, then throw that Royall rout,</l>
               <l>the <hi>Malueſie</hi> was quaffed oft about.</l>
               <l>One drinks out of an <hi>Alabaſter</hi> Cuppe,</l>
               <l>one out of <hi>Chriſtall</hi> doth the <hi>Nectar</hi> ſuppe:</l>
               <l>Some out of curious ſhells of <hi>Vnicorne:</hi>
               </l>
               <l>Some ſpills the wine, &amp; ſome to beds were borne:</l>
               <l>But namely there the <hi>
                     <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>izroy</hi> would not tyre,</l>
               <l>But more he drank, the more he had deſyre:</l>
               <l>Like to the <hi>Ocean</hi> Sea, though it reſaues</l>
               <l>All <hi>Nilus</hi> floods, yet all freſh water craues</l>
               <l>From Eaſt to Weſt, yet growes he not a graine,</l>
               <l>But ſtill is ready foraſmuch againe.</l>
               <l>One glas drawes on another glas, and whan</l>
               <l>the butler ment to ceaſe he but began,</l>
               <l>to ſkinck good <hi>Bacchus:</hi> thus this dronken wight,</l>
               <l>Among his dronkards tippled till midnight,</l>
               <l>then ech of them with ſtackring ſteps out went,</l>
               <l>And groping hands retyring to his tent.</l>
               <l>This tyrant wiſht them oft away before,</l>
               <l>to whome ech moment ſeemd to be a ſkore.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>Aſſoone as they were gone, then gan he preaſe,</l>
               <l>the trembling <hi>Iudith.</hi> Ceaſe great prince ô ceaſe</l>
               <l>the widow ſayd: what haſt neede you to make</l>
               <l>to reap the flowre that none other ca<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> fro<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> you take?</l>
               <l>My Lord go to your bed &amp; take your eaſe,</l>
               <l>wher I your ſweet embracings will compleaſe,</l>
               <l>Aſſoone as I my garments may remoue,</l>
               <l>that binds my body brunt with ardent loue.</l>
            </lg>
            <pb facs="tcp:11277:55"/>
            <lg>
               <l>Now if that ſober wits and wylie brains</l>
               <l>Cannot auoyde the female tricks &amp; trains.</l>
               <l>Abaſh not reader though this reckles Roy</l>
               <l>(Bewitcht by <hi>Semels</hi> ſonne, and <hi>
                     <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>enus</hi> boy)</l>
               <l>was thus beguilde: conſidring both theſe twaine,</l>
               <l>Confounds the force of thoſe that them retaine.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>So letting <hi>Iudith</hi> ſlide out of his arme,</l>
               <l>He gins to loſe his garments ſoft and warme:</l>
               <l>But throw his haſt, his hand came leſſer ſpeed,</l>
               <l>And though he was deceivd, yet tooke no heed,</l>
               <l>But wening well t'vntrus his peuiſh points,</l>
               <l>He knits them twyfold with his trembling ioints:</l>
               <l>ſo long till he with anger diſcontent,</l>
               <l>cuts me them all, and off his clothes he rent,</l>
               <l>And naked went to bed. Then as ye ſee</l>
               <l>the bloodie bowman ſtand behind a tree,</l>
               <l>who warely watches for the wandring deare:</l>
               <l>to euerie part, where he doth thinke to heare</l>
               <l>Some trembling buſh, ſome beaſt or <hi>Lezard</hi> ſmal,</l>
               <l>that mocion maks, ſo turneth he withall</l>
               <l>His face, and hand to ſhoot, but all in vaine</l>
               <l>for to relieue his long aſpecting paine:</l>
               <l>Euen ſo, this fooliſh tyrant when he hard</l>
               <l>ſome rat or mouſe, then thought he to himward:</l>
               <l>His Miſtris came: and when he hard no more,</l>
               <l>yet thought (ſhe came) whome moſt he did adore.</l>
               <l>VVhile vp he lifts his head, while lets it fall:</l>
               <l>while lookes about, while counts the paces all,</l>
               <l>that ſhe ſhould paſſe, to come vnto his bed.</l>
               <l>Thus turning oft, as ardent luſt him led:</l>
               <pb facs="tcp:11277:55"/>
               <l>he thoght his bed was ſown with pricking thorne<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>
               </l>
               <l>but now the drink that he had dro<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>k beforne,</l>
               <l>Brewd in his braine, and from his minde it tooke,</l>
               <l>the ſweete remembrance of her louing looke.</l>
               <l>So fell on ſleepe: and then to him appears</l>
               <l>Ten thouſand flames, ten thouſand dinns he hears,</l>
               <l>and dreames of Deuils, and <hi>Daemons</hi> dark &amp; dim</l>
               <l>
                  <hi>Meduſas, Minotaurs,</hi> and <hi>Gorgons</hi> grim.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>This while the hart of <hi>Iudith</hi> gan to beat</l>
               <l>Inceſſantly beſet with battell great:</l>
               <l>Onewhile her feare refeld her firſt entent:</l>
               <l>onewhile her action Iuſt her courage lent.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>Then ſayd ſhe <hi>Iudith,</hi> now is tyme, go to it,</l>
               <l>And ſaue thy people: Nay, I will not do it.</l>
               <l>I will, I will not, Go, feare not againe:</l>
               <l>wilt thou the ſacred geſtning then prophaine?</l>
               <l>Not it prophane, but holyer it ſhall ſtand,</l>
               <l>when holy folke are helped by my hand.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>But ſhamefull liues the traitour euermore,</l>
               <l>No traitour ſhe who doth her towne reſtore:</l>
               <l>But murdrers all, are of the heavne forſaken?</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>All murder-is not for murder alwayes taken.</l>
               <l>Alas are they not murdrers ſleys their Prince?</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>This tyrant is no prince of my prouince:</l>
               <l>But what if God will haue vs vnder his-awe?</l>
               <l>Hees not of <hi>God</hi> that fights againſt his lawe.</l>
               <l>For then ſhould <hi>Ahud, Iahell,</hi> and <hi>Iehewe,</hi>
               </l>
               <l>Be homicids, becauſe thy tyrants ſlewe.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>But what? they were commanded of the lord,</l>
               <l>to ſuch an act, my hart ſhould ſoone accord.</l>
            </lg>
            <pb n="91" facs="tcp:11277:56"/>
            <lg>
               <l>Alas my hart is weak for ſuch a deed,</l>
               <l>th'are ſtrong ynough whom God doth ſtrength at need</l>
               <l>But when t'is dune who ſhall my warrant be?</l>
               <l>
                  <hi>God</hi> brought me here, <hi>God</hi> will deliuer me.</l>
               <l>VVhat if the Lord leaue thee in <hi>Heathen</hi> hands?</l>
               <l>were this <hi>Duke</hi> dead, I feare no death nor bands.</l>
               <l>but what if they polute thee like a ſlaue?</l>
               <l>my body with my hart they ſhall not haue.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>Thus ſhe reſolued in her mind at laſt,</l>
               <l>Her hands and eyes vnto the heavne ſhe caſt,</l>
               <l>And with an humble voyce to God ſhe prayde,</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>O gratious God that alwayes art the ayde</l>
               <l>to thy beloued <hi>Izak,</hi> I thee pray,</l>
               <l>to ſtrength my hand, euen my right ha<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>d this day,</l>
               <l>that I may make this bloodie tyrant dye,</l>
               <l>that to diſcepter thee would ſkale the ſkye.</l>
               <l>But ſince thy goodneſſe hath preſerued me,</l>
               <l>&amp; brought my bote ſo neare the ſhoare to be:</l>
               <l>Graunt that ſome ſleepie drink I may prouide,</l>
               <l>To dull this tyrants hart and daunt his pride,</l>
               <l>to thend that I may free thy congregation</l>
               <l>Vnto thy honour, and our conſolation.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>This prayer done, ſhe looked round about,</l>
               <l>And hard this dronken prince in ſleeping rout,</l>
               <l>then ſtept ſhe to his ſword that by him ſtood,</l>
               <l>whichoft had bathd the world with humain blood</l>
               <l>But as ſhe preaſt this tyrant for to quell.</l>
               <l>Feare, reft the ſword from her, &amp; down ſhe fell,</l>
               <l>and loſt at once the ſtrength of hart and corſe.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>O God (quoth ſhe) now by thy mightie forſe,</l>
               <pb n="92" facs="tcp:11277:56"/>
               <l>Reſtore my ſtrength. This ſaid (with pale annoy)</l>
               <l>ſhe rudly roſe, and ſtroke this ſleeping <hi>Roy</hi>
               </l>
               <l>ſo fell, that from his ſhoulders flew his powle,</l>
               <l>and from his body fled his <hi>Ethnique</hi> ſowle</l>
               <l>hye way to hell. His bulk all blood beſtaind</l>
               <l>Lay ſtill, his head in <hi>Iudiths</hi> hand remaind.</l>
               <l>The which her mayd put vp into a ſack,</l>
               <l>thus throw the camp they cloſe away do pack</l>
               <l>Empecht of none. For thoſe that had her ſeene,</l>
               <l>Supoſde ſhe went (as ſhe had wonted bene</l>
               <l>the nights before) vnto the valley wheare,</l>
               <l>they thought ſhe went to ſerue <hi>Diana</hi> cleare.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>Whe<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> 
                  <hi>Iudith</hi> chaſt came near the <hi>Hebrew</hi> wall:</l>
               <l>Let in (quoth ſhe) for our great god of all</l>
               <l>hath broke this night the whole <hi>Aſſyrian</hi> powre,</l>
               <l>and raiſd the horne of <hi>Izak</hi> at this howre.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>Then men amazde of her vnhoped ſtate,</l>
               <l>About her ran aſſembling at the gate,</l>
               <l>where holy <hi>Iudith</hi> on a hill was mounted,</l>
               <l>And all her chaunce fro<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> point to point recounted,</l>
               <l>And there, diſcovring drew out of the ſack,</l>
               <l>The bloody head of thenmie of <hi>Izak,</hi>
               </l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>The Citezins that ſaw how ſhe did ſtand</l>
               <l>with th'ead of <hi>Aſſurs</hi> head in her right hand:</l>
               <l>they praiſed God who by her hand had ſlaine,</l>
               <l>&amp; puniſhed that traitour inhumaine.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>'But moſt of all Duke <hi>Ammon</hi> did admyre</l>
               <l>'the work of God. Then he t'eſcape the yre</l>
               <l>'of <hi>Iacobs</hi> God who aydes the weakeſt part:</l>
               <l>'he ſhortly Circunciſde his fleſh and hart.</l>
            </lg>
            <pb n="93" facs="tcp:11277:57"/>
            <lg>
               <l>'O <hi>God</hi> that rightly by foreſight deuine,</l>
               <l>'repels the purpoſe of all mens engine,</l>
               <l>'who for to lead th'elect to deſtnyed health,</l>
               <l>'Eue<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> whe<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> it ſeemes them fardeſt fro<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> their wealth.</l>
               <l>'of ill, thou drawes the good, and ſome in ill</l>
               <l>'thou letſt them runne thy Iuſtice to fulfill.</l>
               <l>'(O lord) the vile deſire of blood and ſak,</l>
               <l>'made <hi>Holopherne</hi> to warre vpon <hi>Izak.</hi>
               </l>
               <l>'But where that he would <hi>Izaks</hi> blood haue ſhed,</l>
               <l>'he loſt his owne for <hi>Izak</hi> on his bed.</l>
               <l>'Thus thy good grace hath made his vaine inuen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>,</l>
               <l>'to take effect contrarie his intencion.</l>
               <l>'So <hi>Paull</hi> became a <hi>Saint,</hi> who was a <hi>Pheriſee,</hi>
               </l>
               <l>'and of a tyrant, teacher of thy veritee:</l>
               <l>'So was the theef that hong with our <hi>Meſſias,</hi>
               </l>
               <l>'(for all his ſinne) preſerued with <hi>Elias:</hi>
               </l>
               <l>'his vitious corps could haue no life here downe,</l>
               <l>'his ſoule by grace yet got a heavnly crowne.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>'Change the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> (ô <hi>God</hi>) the harts of chriſtia<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> princes</l>
               <l>'who ſheds the faithfuls blood in their prouinces.</l>
               <l>'Let thou that ſword that thou giues the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> to guide</l>
               <l>'vpon thy enmies onely be applyde.</l>
               <l>'Vpon thoſe tyrants whoſe vnrighteous horne</l>
               <l>'deteins the land where thy dear ſon was borne.</l>
               <l>'not on the backs of thoſe who with humilitie,</l>
               <l>'Adores the <hi>Triple</hi> one great God in vnitie.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>Then at commandement of this widow chaſte,</l>
               <l>A ſoldier tooke the tyrants head in haſte,</l>
               <l>And for to giue the <hi>Hebrews</hi> hart withall,</l>
               <l>He fixed it vpon the foremoſt wall.</l>
               <pb facs="tcp:11277:57"/>
               <l>There, fathers came, and ſonns, &amp; wiues, &amp; mayds,</l>
               <l>who erſt had loſt amongſt the <hi>Heathen</hi> blayds,</l>
               <l>There ſonnes, their parents, maks, &amp; louers deare,</l>
               <l>with heauie harts &amp; furious raging cheare.</l>
               <l>They pilde &amp; paird his beard of paled hew,</l>
               <l>Spit in his ſpace &amp; out his toung they drew,</l>
               <l>which vſde to ſpeak of God great blaſphemies,</l>
               <l>And with their fingers poched out his eyes.</l>
               <l>The rife remembrance of ſo late an ill,</l>
               <l>Made vulgar folke ſuch vengeance to fulfill.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>This while <hi>Aurora</hi> ceaſed to embrace,</l>
               <l>Her ancient loue and roſe with ruddy face,</l>
               <l>Vpon the <hi>Indian</hi> heavne, the warriours ſtrong,</l>
               <l>take kept the towne: now ſorted forth in throng.</l>
               <l>Enarmed all, with ſuch a hideous ſound:</l>
               <l>as ſeemde the elements foure for to confound.</l>
               <l>And break the ba<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ds that keeps the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> in their border,</l>
               <l>Retyring them vnto their old diſorder.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>The <hi>Pagan</hi> watches next the Citties ſide</l>
               <l>(Awaked with this din) ſtart vp and cryde:</l>
               <l>
                  <hi>Alarme, Alarme,</hi> like fearefull men agaſt,</l>
               <l>then through the Camp, the whote Alarum paſt.</l>
               <l>Some takes his neighbours armour firſt he finds,<note place="margin">Confuſio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>.</note>
               </l>
               <l>And wrong on armes the bracels both he binds.</l>
               <l>Some takes a ſtaf for haſt, and leaues his launce:</l>
               <l>Some madling runnes, ſome trembles in a trau<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ce:</l>
               <l>Some on his horſe ill ſadled ginnes to ryde,</l>
               <l>And wants his ſpurres, ſome boldly do abyde:</l>
               <l>Some neither wakes nor ſleeps, but mazing ſta<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ds:</l>
               <l>Some braue in words, are beaſtly of their hands.</l>
               <pb facs="tcp:11277:58"/>
               <l>This brute from hand to hand, from man to man,</l>
               <l>Vnto the <hi>Pagans</hi> court at laſt it ran.</l>
               <l>Then <hi>Bagos Eunuch</hi> ſadly forth he went</l>
               <l>t'awake the ſleeping <hi>Ethnique</hi> in his tent,</l>
               <l>&amp; knockt once twiſe, or thriſe with trembling ha<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>d</l>
               <l>But ſuch eternall ſleep his temples band,</l>
               <l>that he had paſt already (miſerable)</l>
               <l>Of <hi>Styx</hi> ſo black the flood irrepaſſable.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>Yet <hi>Bagos</hi> hearing <hi>Izaks</hi> crye encreaſe,</l>
               <l>He with his foote, the dore began to preaſe:</l>
               <l>And entred where the bed he did beholde</l>
               <l>All bled with <hi>Holophernes</hi> carcaſſe colde:</l>
               <l>He tore his haire &amp; all his garments rent,</l>
               <l>and to the heavne his houling cryes he ſent.</l>
               <l>But when he miſt the <hi>Hebrew</hi>-Dame away</l>
               <l>then raginghe began a gaſtly fray.</l>
               <l>And from the bloody tent as he rant out,</l>
               <l>Among the <hi>Heathen</hi> thus he gan to ſhout.</l>
               <l>Woe, woe to vs, a ſlaue (they <hi>Iudith</hi> call)</l>
               <l>In ſleaing <hi>Holopherne</hi> hath ſlaine vs all:</l>
               <l>That daunted all the world. Theſe nouels laſt,</l>
               <l>loynde the former feare that lately paſt,</l>
               <l>Affrighted ſo the ſoldiers one and all,</l>
               <l>that pike and dart, and target they let fall,</l>
               <l>And fled through mo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>tains, valeis, &amp; throw heaths</l>
               <l>where evrie chaunce, procurde the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> worſer deaths.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>Then all th aſſieged folk in flocks deſcended,</l>
               <l>&amp; on their enmies backs their bowes they be<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ded.</l>
               <l>Both parties ran, but th one that other chaſed,</l>
               <l>The wearie flyers flight, themſelfs defaced.</l>
               <pb facs="tcp:11277:58"/>
               <l>The <hi>Hebrewes</hi> there, in fight not one they loſte,</l>
               <l>But they bet downe and ſlew the Heathen hoſte,</l>
               <l>As doth a Lyon of <hi>Getulia</hi> woode</l>
               <l>Beſpred the land with woried beaſts &amp; bloode</l>
               <l>So long as he may find a beaſt abide,</l>
               <l>that dare oppone him to his cruell pride.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>Some headlong throwes themſelfs fro<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> craggie Rocks,</l>
               <l>&amp; breaks their bones &amp; al their brains out knocks</l>
               <l>Some hath forgot that <hi>Parcas</hi> euerie wheare,</l>
               <l>waits on their end that drowne in water cleare:</l>
               <l>But if that any ſkapt by ſome great hap,</l>
               <l>He ſkapte the firſt, but not the after clap:</l>
               <l>fore all the ſtraits and paſſages were ſet,</l>
               <l>that none ſhould ſcape aliue wher they were met:</l>
               <l>Yea ſcarſly one was left to tell the king,</l>
               <l>At <hi>Niniuè</hi> of all this wondrous thing.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>This battell done, all thoſe whoſe <hi>Sex</hi> and age</l>
               <l>withheld at home (their dolours to aſſwage)</l>
               <l>Came forth out of their fort to ſee and heare,</l>
               <l>what God had done for them his people deare.</l>
               <l>They found ſome men diſme<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>bred hauing breath,</l>
               <l>that cride in vaine a hundreth tymes for death.</l>
               <l>Another gnaſhes with his teeth in paines</l>
               <l>ſome dead, in face their former rage retains.</l>
               <l>And ſome is ſhot directly throw the hart</l>
               <l>Ech ſoule departs to his appointed part,</l>
               <l>According to the valew, or the chaunce,</l>
               <l>that fortunde them to dye on ſword or launce.</l>
               <l>In ſhort to ſee this ſight ſo dreadfull was,</l>
               <l>That euen the <hi>Hebrews</hi> would haue ſaid alas:</l>
               <pb n="95" facs="tcp:11277:59" rendition="simple:additions"/>
               <l>If they had vanquiſht any enmie els,</l>
               <l>This while amongſt the corſes infidels,</l>
               <l>Among a hundreth thouſand there was found,</l>
               <l>the cheftains carcas rent with many-a wound,</l>
               <l>Of ſpeare and ſword, by th <hi>Hebrewes</hi> in their yre.</l>
               <l>There was no ſinew, Arter, vaine, nor lyre,</l>
               <l>that was not mangled with their vulgar rage,</l>
               <l>No time nor moment might their yre aſſwage.</l>
               <l>If <hi>Holophern</hi> had bene like <hi>Atlas</hi> long:</l>
               <l>Or like in limmes vnto <hi>Briarius</hi> ſtrong,</l>
               <l>Yet ſhould his body bene to ſmall a praye,</l>
               <l>to ſatiſfie their fury evrie waye.</l>
               <l>For in that camp was not ſo ſmall a knaue,</l>
               <l>but of his fleſh ſome collup he would haue.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>O tyrant now (quod they) giue thy right hand,</l>
               <l>to the <hi>Cilicians,</hi> and to <hi>Media land,</hi>
               </l>
               <l>leaue thou thy left. And to <hi>Celea</hi> ſweete,</l>
               <l>to <hi>Iſmaell</hi> and <hi>Aegypt</hi> leaue thy feete,</l>
               <l>to thend that all the world by thee offenced</l>
               <l>with ſuch a preſent may be recompenced.</l>
               <l>But here I faile thy corps thus to deuiſe</l>
               <l>In <hi>Attomy</hi> for it will not ſuffiſe.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>This thankfull widow then, who neuer thought</l>
               <l>to ſmore this wo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>droꝰ work that god had wrought,</l>
               <l>Entunde her vearſe and ſong to ſweet confort</l>
               <l>Of inſtruments &amp; paſt with gratious port</l>
               <l>Before the choſen Dames and virgins thair,</l>
               <l>that were eſteemde for honeſt chaſt and fair.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>Sing ſing with hart &amp; voyce &amp; ſou<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ding ſtrings,</l>
               <l>And praiſe the Lord of lords, and king of kings,</l>
               <pb n="96" facs="tcp:11277:59" rendition="simple:additions"/>
               <l>who doth diſthrone the great, and in their place</l>
               <l>Erects the poore that leanes vpon his grace.</l>
               <l>Who would haue thought that in a day one town</l>
               <l>Could ouercome a camp of ſuch renown?</l>
               <l>who daunted all the world whoſe pride was felt</l>
               <l>From <hi>Indian</hi> ſhore to where the <hi>Calpees</hi> dwelt?</l>
               <l>Great God who will beleeue that <hi>Holopherne,</hi>
               </l>
               <l>who did a hundreth famous princes derne,</l>
               <l>ſhould be diſcreptred, ſlaine, left in a midow,</l>
               <l>by no great <hi>Gyant,</hi> but a feeble widow?</l>
               <l>great <hi>God</hi> who will beleue that he who raind,</l>
               <l>From north to ſouth, &amp; in his hands retaind</l>
               <l>Both Eaſt and Weſt: now gets not grace to haue</l>
               <l>An ynch of <hi>Gazon</hi> ground to be his graue?</l>
               <l>This Conqurour that came with no armie ſmall,</l>
               <l>now lyes on ground abandond of them all.</l>
               <l>Not ſole: for thoſe companions him in death,</l>
               <l>that followde him while he had life and breath.</l>
               <l>Not now the grou<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>d, but Reauens hunger ſterude,</l>
               <l>Are now his tombe as he hath well deſerude.</l>
               <l>No vaults of Marble, rich nor <hi>Porphyr</hi> pure,</l>
               <l>that he had built could be his ſepulture.</l>
               <l>Euen ſo good Lord from henceforth let vs finde,</l>
               <l>thee, not our Iudge, but for our father kinde.</l>
               <l>But let all Tyrants that againſt thee gather,</l>
               <l>finde thee their Iudge, but not their louing father.</l>
               <l>Here <hi>Iudith</hi> ends. <hi>And alſo heare</hi> I <hi>ſtaye</hi>
               </l>
               <l>
                  <hi>With thanks to God. So for his state</hi> I <hi>praye,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">The tra<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
                     <gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>
                     <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſlatour.</note>
               </l>
               <l>
                  <hi>At whoſe command</hi> I <hi>vndertooke this deed,</hi>
               </l>
               <l>
                  <hi>To pleaſe his Grace, and thoſe that will it reed.</hi>
               </l>
            </lg>
         </div>
         <trailer>FINIS.</trailer>
      </body>
      <back>
         <div type="glossary">
            <pb facs="tcp:11277:60" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <head>A TABLE OF SIGNIFI<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>CATION OF SOME WORDS AS THEY AR VSED BEFORE.</head>
            <p>
               <table>
                  <row>
                     <cell>Words.</cell>
                     <cell>Significations.</cell>
                  </row>
                  <row>
                     <cell>
                        <hi>ABderois.</hi>
                     </cell>
                     <cell>Prophane &amp; delicate Epicurs.</cell>
                  </row>
                  <row>
                     <cell>
                        <hi>Abile.</hi>
                     </cell>
                     <cell>A hill in <hi>Affrica,</hi> one of the <hi>Pillers</hi> of <hi>Hercules.</hi>
                     </cell>
                  </row>
                  <row>
                     <cell>
                        <hi>Abraham.</hi>
                     </cell>
                     <cell>Father of the Iewes or the faithfull.</cell>
                  </row>
                  <row>
                     <cell>
                        <hi>Achelois</hi> Ympes.</cell>
                     <cell>
                        <hi>Sirenes</hi> or <hi>Mermaids.</hi>
                     </cell>
                  </row>
                  <row>
                     <cell>
                        <hi>Amram.</hi>
                     </cell>
                     <cell>The father of <hi>Moyſes.</hi>
                     </cell>
                  </row>
                  <row>
                     <cell>
                        <hi>Aſſur. Aſſurs</hi> head.</cell>
                     <cell>the countrey of <hi>Aſſyria</hi> or their king.</cell>
                  </row>
                  <row>
                     <cell>
                        <hi>Aſſyrian</hi> Prince.</cell>
                     <cell>
                        <hi>Holophernes.</hi> Vizroy or ge<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>rall.</cell>
                  </row>
                  <row>
                     <cell>
                        <hi>Agamemnon.</hi>
                     </cell>
                     <cell>The generall of the <hi>Grekes,</hi> being preſent at the ſacrificing of his onely Doughter was painted with a bend about his eies, either forth vnſkilfulnes of the <hi>painter,</hi> who could not ſufficiently expres the fathers ſpeciall teares; or els for that he thought it not decent to paint ſo mightie a Prince weeping, or vnna<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>turall not to weepe.</cell>
                  </row>
                  <row>
                     <cell>
                        <hi>Aconite.</hi>
                     </cell>
                     <cell>A poiſonable herbe.</cell>
                  </row>
                  <row>
                     <cell>
                        <hi>Autan.</hi>
                     </cell>
                     <cell>the South or ſouth wind.</cell>
                  </row>
                  <row>
                     <cell>
                        <hi>Aurora.</hi>
                     </cell>
                     <cell>the morning.</cell>
                  </row>
                  <row>
                     <cell>
                        <hi>Arphaxat.</hi>
                     </cell>
                     <cell>ſuppoſed to be <hi>Arbactus,</hi> King of <hi>Medes.</hi>
                     </cell>
                  </row>
                  <row>
                     <cell>
                        <hi>Atlas.</hi>
                     </cell>
                     <cell>A great <hi>Gyant.</hi>
                     </cell>
                  </row>
                  <row>
                     <cell>
                        <hi>Argus.</hi>
                     </cell>
                     <cell>Had a hundreth eyes.</cell>
                  </row>
                  <pb facs="tcp:11277:60" rendition="simple:additions"/>
                  <row>
                     <cell>
                        <hi>Alexander.</hi>
                     </cell>
                     <cell>The great.</cell>
                  </row>
                  <row>
                     <cell>
                        <hi>Apelles.</hi>
                     </cell>
                     <cell>An excellent painter.</cell>
                  </row>
                  <row>
                     <cell>
                        <hi>Bethull or Bethulia.</hi>
                     </cell>
                     <cell>the Citie where <hi>Iudith</hi> dwelt.</cell>
                  </row>
                  <row>
                     <cell>
                        <hi>Babell.</hi>
                     </cell>
                     <cell>
                        <hi>Babylo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>,</hi> or the whole coütrey.</cell>
                  </row>
                  <row>
                     <cell>
                        <hi>Bellona.</hi>
                     </cell>
                     <cell>Goddeſſe of Battell.</cell>
                  </row>
                  <row>
                     <cell>
                        <hi>Briccoll.</hi>
                     </cell>
                     <cell>an engine of warre.</cell>
                  </row>
                  <row>
                     <cell>
                        <hi>Briarius.</hi>
                     </cell>
                     <cell>a Giant with a hu<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>dreth ha<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ds.</cell>
                  </row>
                  <row>
                     <cell>
                        <hi>Bacchus.</hi>
                     </cell>
                     <cell>Wyne or drunkennes.</cell>
                  </row>
                  <row>
                     <cell>
                        <hi>Boreas.</hi>
                     </cell>
                     <cell>the north or north wind.</cell>
                  </row>
                  <row>
                     <cell>
                        <hi>Camelion.</hi>
                     </cell>
                     <cell>a beaſt that chaungeth his collours.</cell>
                  </row>
                  <row>
                     <cell>
                        <hi>Cteſiphon.</hi>
                     </cell>
                     <cell>a cunning <hi>Architectu<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="2 letters">
                              <desc>••</desc>
                           </gap>
                        </hi> or builder.</cell>
                  </row>
                  <row>
                     <cell>
                        <hi>Chaos.</hi>
                     </cell>
                     <cell>a confuſion before the worlds creation.</cell>
                  </row>
                  <row>
                     <cell>
                        <hi>Capharois.</hi>
                     </cell>
                     <cell>TWO perilous Rocks.</cell>
                  </row>
                  <row>
                     <cell>
                        <hi>Cyanes</hi> ſtraits</cell>
                     <cell> </cell>
                  </row>
                  <row>
                     <cell>
                        <hi>Calpe.</hi>
                     </cell>
                     <cell>A hill in <hi>Spaine</hi> one of the pil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lours of <hi>Hercules.</hi>
                     </cell>
                  </row>
                  <row>
                     <cell>
                        <hi>Cyprian</hi> Dame</cell>
                     <cell>
                        <hi>
                           <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>enus,</hi> loue, or luſt.</cell>
                  </row>
                  <row>
                     <cell>
                        <hi>Cupido.</hi>
                     </cell>
                     <cell>Loue or luſt.</cell>
                  </row>
                  <row>
                     <cell>
                        <hi>Cornies.</hi>
                     </cell>
                     <cell>crooked yrons to draw down buildings.</cell>
                  </row>
                  <row>
                     <cell>
                        <hi>Caſtors</hi> ſiſter.</cell>
                     <cell>
                        <hi>Helen</hi> the diſhoneſt wife of <hi>Menelaus.</hi>
                     </cell>
                  </row>
                  <row>
                     <cell>
                        <hi>Canaces.</hi>
                     </cell>
                     <cell>Inceſtuous wemen.</cell>
                  </row>
                  <row>
                     <cell>
                        <hi>Circes.</hi>
                     </cell>
                     <cell>witches, abuſers of louers.</cell>
                  </row>
                  <row>
                     <cell>
                        <hi>Cyrene.</hi>
                     </cell>
                     <cell>a dry ſandy cou<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>trie, or drouth.</cell>
                  </row>
                  <row>
                     <cell>
                        <hi>Carmell.</hi>
                     </cell>
                     <cell>a montain in <hi>Iudea,</hi> or the whole co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>trey.</cell>
                  </row>
                  <row>
                     <cell>
                        <hi>Danow.</hi>
                     </cell>
                     <cell>
                        <hi>Danubius,</hi> a riuer in <hi>Germanie.</hi>
                     </cell>
                  </row>
                  <pb facs="tcp:11277:61" rendition="simple:additions"/>
                  <row>
                     <cell>
                        <hi>Denis</hi> twice borne.</cell>
                     <cell>
                        <hi>Bachus.</hi>
                     </cell>
                  </row>
                  <row>
                     <cell>
                        <hi>Diana</hi> or <hi>Cynthia,</hi>
                     </cell>
                     <cell>The Moone.</cell>
                  </row>
                  <row>
                     <cell>
                        <hi>Dina.</hi>
                     </cell>
                     <cell>The daughter of <hi>Iacob.</hi>
                     </cell>
                  </row>
                  <row>
                     <cell>
                        <hi>Aegiptian</hi> Queene.</cell>
                     <cell>
                        <hi>Cleopatra</hi> the Concubine of <hi>M. Antonius,</hi> who ſwallowed a rich pearle.</cell>
                  </row>
                  <row>
                     <cell>
                        <hi>Elimia</hi> Land.</cell>
                     <cell>The Elamits.</cell>
                  </row>
                  <row>
                     <cell>
                        <hi>Eurus.</hi>
                     </cell>
                     <cell>The Eaſt, or Eaſt wind.</cell>
                  </row>
                  <row>
                     <cell>
                        <hi>Aegeans</hi> ſtable.</cell>
                     <cell>where horſes deuoured men.</cell>
                  </row>
                  <row>
                     <cell>
                        <hi>Encelade.</hi>
                     </cell>
                     <cell>a Giant burried vnder mount <hi>Etna.</hi>
                     </cell>
                  </row>
                  <row>
                     <cell>
                        <hi>Genrall.</hi>
                     </cell>
                     <cell>
                        <hi>Holophernes.</hi>
                     </cell>
                  </row>
                  <row>
                     <cell>
                        <hi>Gibaltar.</hi>
                     </cell>
                     <cell>A Cittie in <hi>Spaine,</hi> neare to <hi>Calpe</hi>-hill, one of the Pillers of <hi>Hercules.</hi>
                     </cell>
                  </row>
                  <row>
                     <cell>
                        <hi>Holopherne.</hi>
                     </cell>
                     <cell>Vizroy, chiefe of the Armie.</cell>
                  </row>
                  <row>
                     <cell>
                        <hi>Hermon.</hi>
                     </cell>
                     <cell>a Hill in <hi>Iudea,</hi> or the cou<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>trey of <hi>Iudea.</hi>
                     </cell>
                  </row>
                  <row>
                     <cell>
                        <hi>Heſperian</hi> coſte.</cell>
                     <cell>The weſt.</cell>
                  </row>
                  <row>
                     <cell>
                        <hi>Hyade.</hi>
                     </cell>
                     <cell>a water nymph or watrie ſtar.</cell>
                  </row>
                  <row>
                     <cell>
                        <hi>Heraults.</hi>
                     </cell>
                     <cell>Apoſtles, or preachers.</cell>
                  </row>
                  <row>
                     <cell>
                        <hi>Iacobs</hi> ſonnes.</cell>
                     <cell>the people of <hi>Izrell.</hi>
                     </cell>
                  </row>
                  <row>
                     <cell>
                        <hi>Izrell</hi> or <hi>Iacob.</hi>
                     </cell>
                     <cell>the land of <hi>Iudea.</hi>
                     </cell>
                  </row>
                  <row>
                     <cell>
                        <hi>Izaak.</hi>
                     </cell>
                     <cell>the people of the Iewes.</cell>
                  </row>
                  <row>
                     <cell>
                        <hi>Iſmaell.</hi>
                     </cell>
                     <cell>
                        <hi>Idumeans</hi> or <hi>Edom.</hi>
                     </cell>
                  </row>
                  <row>
                     <cell>
                        <hi>Ixion.</hi>
                     </cell>
                     <cell>One tormented in Hell</cell>
                  </row>
                  <row>
                     <cell>
                        <hi>Iebus</hi> place.</cell>
                     <cell>
                        <hi>Ieruſalem</hi> or <hi>Syon.</hi>
                     </cell>
                  </row>
                  <row>
                     <cell>
                        <hi>Iudith.</hi>
                     </cell>
                     <cell>of <hi>Bethulia</hi> of the trybe of <hi>Ru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ben.</hi>
                     </cell>
                  </row>
                  <row>
                     <cell>
                        <hi>Ieſſies</hi> race.</cell>
                     <cell>
                        <hi>Dauid</hi> and his ſeede.</cell>
                  </row>
                  <row>
                     <cell>
                        <hi>Iethro.</hi>
                     </cell>
                     <cell>Father in law to <hi>Moyſes.</hi>
                     </cell>
                  </row>
                  <row>
                     <cell>
                        <hi>Latmies</hi> ſonne.</cell>
                     <cell>
                        <hi>Endymion,</hi> the long ſleper ſup<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſed to lye with the Moone.</cell>
                  </row>
                  <row>
                     <cell>
                        <hi>Lyſippus.</hi>
                     </cell>
                     <cell>a cunning caruer.</cell>
                  </row>
                  <row>
                     <cell>
                        <hi>Monark.</hi>
                     </cell>
                     <cell>One ſole gouernour.</cell>
                  </row>
                  <pb facs="tcp:11277:61" rendition="simple:additions"/>
                  <row>
                     <cell>
                        <hi>Memphits.</hi>
                     </cell>
                     <cell>Men of that Cittie in <hi>Aegypt.</hi>
                     </cell>
                  </row>
                  <row>
                     <cell>
                        <hi>Miſraim.</hi>
                     </cell>
                     <cell>The land of <hi>Egypt.</hi>
                     </cell>
                  </row>
                  <row>
                     <cell>
                        <hi>Mocmur.</hi>
                     </cell>
                     <cell>the riuer neare <hi>Bethulia.</hi>
                     </cell>
                  </row>
                  <row>
                     <cell>
                        <hi>Momus.</hi>
                     </cell>
                     <cell>a ſcornfull detractour of all thing.</cell>
                  </row>
                  <row>
                     <cell>
                        <hi>Mars.</hi>
                     </cell>
                     <cell>God of ſtrife or battell.</cell>
                  </row>
                  <row>
                     <cell>
                        <hi>Myrrhaes &amp; Syllaes.</hi>
                     </cell>
                     <cell>wemen betrayers of their co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
                        <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trey.</cell>
                  </row>
                  <row>
                     <cell>
                        <hi>Minotaurs.</hi>
                     </cell>
                     <cell>Vnnaturall monſters.</cell>
                  </row>
                  <row>
                     <cell>
                        <hi>Meduſaes.</hi>
                     </cell>
                     <cell>furies of hell.</cell>
                  </row>
                  <row>
                     <cell>
                        <hi>Neptunes</hi> back.</cell>
                     <cell>the Sea.</cell>
                  </row>
                  <row>
                     <cell>
                        <hi>Niphathaei.</hi>
                     </cell>
                     <cell>A mightie ſtrong Roch or mountaine in Syria.</cell>
                  </row>
                  <row>
                     <cell>
                        <hi>Paleſtene.</hi>
                     </cell>
                     <cell>the land of the <hi>Philiſtins.</hi>
                     </cell>
                  </row>
                  <row>
                     <cell>
                        <hi>Pharia.</hi>
                     </cell>
                     <cell>a famous tower in <hi>Egypt.</hi>
                     </cell>
                  </row>
                  <row>
                     <cell>
                        <hi>Phlegon.</hi>
                     </cell>
                     <cell>One of the foure horſes that was ſuppoſed to draw the ſunne.</cell>
                  </row>
                  <row>
                     <cell>
                        <hi>Phoebus.</hi>
                     </cell>
                     <cell>the ſunne.</cell>
                  </row>
                  <row>
                     <cell>
                        <hi>Phoebe.</hi>
                     </cell>
                     <cell>His ſiſter the moone.</cell>
                  </row>
                  <row>
                     <cell>
                        <hi>Proteus.</hi>
                     </cell>
                     <cell>A man changing him ſelfe in ſundry formes, there is a fiſh of like nature.</cell>
                  </row>
                  <row>
                     <cell>
                        <hi>Priams</hi> wife.</cell>
                     <cell>
                        <hi>Hecuba</hi> the honorable.</cell>
                  </row>
                  <row>
                     <cell>
                        <hi>Peſlmell.</hi>
                     </cell>
                     <cell>all mixt confuſedly together.</cell>
                  </row>
                  <row>
                     <cell>
                        <hi>Ramme.</hi>
                     </cell>
                     <cell>an ingine of warre for battrie.</cell>
                  </row>
                  <row>
                     <cell>
                        <hi>Sina</hi>-hill.</cell>
                     <cell>
                        <hi>Sinai</hi>-hill.</cell>
                  </row>
                  <row>
                     <cell>
                        <hi>Salem.</hi>
                     </cell>
                     <cell>
                        <hi>Ieruſalem.</hi>
                     </cell>
                  </row>
                  <row>
                     <cell>
                        <hi>Solyma</hi>
                     </cell>
                     <cell>
                        <hi>Ieruſalem.</hi>
                     </cell>
                  </row>
                  <row>
                     <cell>
                        <hi>Sichem.</hi>
                     </cell>
                     <cell>the rauiſher of <hi>Dina.</hi>
                     </cell>
                  </row>
                  <row>
                     <cell>
                        <hi>Sabean</hi> Queene.</cell>
                     <cell>Sauours of <hi>Saba</hi> land.</cell>
                  </row>
                  <row>
                     <cell>
                        <hi>Simeon.</hi>
                     </cell>
                     <cell>
                        <hi>Dinaes</hi> brother.</cell>
                  </row>
                  <row>
                     <cell>
                        <hi>Scythique Rampier.</hi>
                     </cell>
                     <cell>The tombe of <hi>Semele,</hi> mother of <hi>Bacchus.</hi>
                     </cell>
                  </row>
                  <pb facs="tcp:11277:62" rendition="simple:additions"/>
                  <row>
                     <cell>
                        <hi>Styx.</hi>
                     </cell>
                     <cell>a Riuer in hell.</cell>
                  </row>
                  <row>
                     <cell>
                        <hi>Sympathie.</hi>
                     </cell>
                     <cell>Concordance of natures and things.</cell>
                  </row>
                  <row>
                     <cell>
                        <hi>Sentinelles.</hi>
                     </cell>
                     <cell>watchmen.</cell>
                  </row>
                  <row>
                     <cell>
                        <hi>Semirames.</hi>
                     </cell>
                     <cell>wemen <hi>
                           <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>iragoés.</hi>
                     </cell>
                  </row>
                  <row>
                     <cell>
                        <hi>Syrtes.</hi>
                     </cell>
                     <cell>Dangerous ſands.</cell>
                  </row>
                  <row>
                     <cell>
                        <hi>Satrap.</hi>
                     </cell>
                     <cell>Prince.</cell>
                  </row>
                  <row>
                     <cell>
                        <hi>ſtymphalids.</hi>
                     </cell>
                     <cell>Rauenous foules with female faces <hi>Harpyes.</hi>
                     </cell>
                  </row>
                  <row>
                     <cell>
                        <hi>Syrian</hi> camp.</cell>
                     <cell>the Hoſte of <hi>Holophernes.</hi>
                     </cell>
                  </row>
                  <row>
                     <cell>
                        <hi>Semels</hi> ſonne.</cell>
                     <cell>Bacchus or wine.</cell>
                  </row>
                  <row>
                     <cell>
                        <hi>Tranſparant.</hi>
                     </cell>
                     <cell>that which may ſeene through and whole like glaſſe.</cell>
                  </row>
                  <row>
                     <cell>
                        <hi>Tortuſé.</hi>
                     </cell>
                     <cell>An engine of warre.</cell>
                  </row>
                  <row>
                     <cell>
                        <hi>Trepan.</hi>
                     </cell>
                     <cell>An engine of warre.</cell>
                  </row>
                  <row>
                     <cell>
                        <hi>The forrain tyde.</hi>
                     </cell>
                     <cell>Suppofed to haue beene the flood of <hi>Noah,</hi> or the deluge of <hi>Deucalion</hi> that <gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>iuided <hi>Affrica</hi> from <hi>Europe,</hi> &amp; <hi>Sicilia</hi> fro<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> 
                        <hi>Italia.</hi>
                     </cell>
                  </row>
                  <row>
                     <cell>
                        <hi>Thetis.</hi>
                     </cell>
                     <cell>The ſea.</cell>
                  </row>
                  <row>
                     <cell>
                        <hi>Thurims.</hi>
                     </cell>
                     <cell>Deceitfull Aduocats.</cell>
                  </row>
                  <row>
                     <cell>
                        <hi>Theban</hi> knight.</cell>
                     <cell>Captain of the Grekes army.</cell>
                  </row>
                  <row>
                     <cell>
                        <hi>Theefe that ſtole the fire.</hi>
                     </cell>
                     <cell>
                        <hi>Prometheus,</hi> who ſtole fire fro<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> 
                        <hi>Iupiter.</hi>
                     </cell>
                  </row>
                  <row>
                     <cell>
                        <hi>Zedechias.</hi>
                     </cell>
                     <cell>Laſt king of the Iewes.</cell>
                  </row>
                  <row>
                     <cell>
                        <hi>Zephyrus.</hi>
                     </cell>
                     <cell>Weſt or weſt wind.</cell>
                  </row>
                  <row>
                     <cell>
                        <hi>Zeuxis.</hi>
                     </cell>
                     <cell>A painter of <hi>Italie,</hi> who being required to paint the picture of <hi>Helen,</hi> deſired to haue all the faireſt wemen of <hi>Croton</hi> to be pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſent for his paterne.</cell>
                  </row>
               </table>
            </p>
            <trailer>FINIS.</trailer>
            <pb facs="tcp:11277:62"/>
         </div>
      </back>
   </text>
</TEI>
